<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: d3 | Mountain Doodles]]></title>
  <link href="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/categories/d3/feed.atom" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/"/>
  <updated>2016-03-28T23:46:56-07:00</updated>
  <id>http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[MountainMath]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Physical SFH Form Over Time]]></title>
    <link href="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2016/03/05/physical-sfh-form-over-time/"/>
    <updated>2016-03-05T22:58:06-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2016/03/05/physical-sfh-form-over-time</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I was curious how the physical parameters of Single Family Houses changed over time.</p>

<p>Using the <a href="https://mountainmath.ca/map/assessment">assessment dataset</a> merged with the <a href="https://mountainmath.ca/land_use/map">land use dataset</a>
allows to fairly accurately pick out single family houses, and also holds the age of most properies. Together with
the City of Vancouver LIDAR-generated building dataset <a href="https://mountainmath.ca/vancouver_lidar/map">that I have played with before</a>
we can look at physical building parameters.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>The city dataset is a little coarse, it only contains the main building and does not map things like garages. It&rsquo;s a little
rough and should probably be interpreted cautiously on an individual building level. One could spend the time and derive the
building data directly from the raw LIDAR dataset optimized for this purpose, but for some overview statistics the building
dataset that was derived by the city is just fine. The LIDAR was taken in 2009, so we only consider houses built before that time.</p>

<h3>Site coverage</h3>

<p>One question is how the site coverage of the buildings have changed over time. We simply line up the buildings by the year
they were built, compute the site coverage of the main building relative to the parcel size and graph the quintiles for
each year. For good measure, we throw in the 10 and 90 percentile whiskers.</p>

<div style="margin:10px 50px;padding:5px;border: 1px solid black;border-radius:5px;" class="whiskers">
<div id="sfh_coverage" style="height:200px;max-width:640px;" data-url="/data/sfh_coverage.json"></div>
<div class="legend no-margin" style="padding-bottom:2em;">
</div>
</div>


<p>What jumps out immediately is that around 1988 there apparently was a change in zoning law that reduced site coverage
of the main building. <strike>I don&rsquo;t know anything about the history of building codes, maybe someone that does could shed some
light onto this.</strike> <a href="https://twitter.com/BrendanDawe/status/706737206484795392">Twitter was fast to provide the answer</a>
it appears that changes in building code were implemented to counteract the growing footprint of houses at the time, details
can be found in <a href="https://open.library.ubc.ca/cIRcle/collections/ubctheses/831/items/1.0086386">Barbara Pettit&rsquo;s Ph.D. thesis</a>.</p>

<h3>Building Height</h3>

<p>The next obvious point of analysis is how building height, in meters, changed over time.</p>

<div style="margin:10px 50px;padding:5px;border: 1px solid black;border-radius:5px;" class="whiskers">
<div id="sfh_height" style="height:200px;max-width:640px;" data-url="/data/sfh_height.json"></div>
<div class="legend no-margin" style="padding-bottom:2em;">
</div>
</div>


<p>We observe a similar jump in the data around 1988, with building height jumping up as site coverage decreases.</p>

<h3>Building Volumes</h3>

<p>Now let&rsquo;s look at how &ldquo;massive&rdquo; the buildings are, measured by volume in cubic metres.</p>

<div style="margin:10px 50px;padding:5px;border: 1px solid black;border-radius:5px;" class="whiskers">
<div id="sfh_volume" style="height:200px;max-width:640px;" data-url="/data/sfh_volume.json"></div>
<div class="legend no-margin" style="padding-bottom:2em;">
</div>
</div>


<p>The graph does show that in general houses have gotten more massive starting in the late 80s, but after that have more or less
maintained the same volume. It shows that the combined effect of the regulation change in the late 80s that resulted in
smaller building footprints and taller buildings was that buildings overall got bulkier.</p>

<h3>Roof Type</h3>

<p>Lastly we see how the roof type changes over time, plotting the number of buildings with given roof type for each year.</p>

<div style="margin:10px 50px;padding:5px;border: 1px solid black;border-radius:5px;" class="whiskers">
<div id="sfh_roof" style="height:200px;max-width:640px;" data-url="/data/sfh_roof.json"></div>
<div class="legend no-margin" style="padding-bottom:2em;">
</div>
</div>


<p>Flat roofs seem to have been quite popular between the mid 60s to mid 80s.</p>

<h3>Length to Width Ratio (Update)</h3>

<p>A question about a regulation change in 1938 <a href="https://twitter.com/GRIDSVancouver/status/706879555550613504">came up on Twitter</a>,
so I thought I should check into the length-to-width ratio to see if anything can be seen there. A ratio of 1
would mean a square footprint, a ratio of 2 means the house is twice as long as wide.</p>

<div style="margin:10px 50px;padding:5px;border: 1px solid black;border-radius:5px;" class="whiskers">
<div id="sfh_square" style="height:200px;max-width:640px;" data-url="/data/sfh_square.json"></div>
<div class="legend no-margin" style="padding-bottom:2em;">
</div>
</div>


<p>No obvious changes around 1938, but our houses became a lot more square after the late 80s zoning changes.</p>

<h3>Next Steps</h3>

<p>After starting to see what kind of data can be derived from LIDAR data we can start to explore different questions. The
graphs open a small window into the physical parameters of single family homes over time and are only of limited general
interest.</p>

<p>For
more serious analysis we would most likely have to start from the raw LIDAR data, which takes a little bit of effort.</p>

<div><script src="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/javascripts/box.js"></script></div>




<script>

function stacked_bar_graph(div,shiftAxis,domainFormatter,rangeFormatter,domainLabelFormatter){
    if (!domainFormatter) domainFormatter=d3.format("d")
    if (!rangeFormatter)
     rangeFormatter = function (y) {
        return y;
     };
     if (!domainLabelFormatter) domainLabelFormatter=domainFormatter;

var margin = {top: 20, right: 20, bottom: 40, left: 70},
    width = parseInt(div.style("width")) - margin.left - margin.right,
    height = parseInt(div.style("height")) - margin.top - margin.bottom;

var x = d3.scale.ordinal()
    .rangeRoundBands([0, width], .1);

var y = d3.scale.linear()
    .range([height, 0]);


var xAxis = d3.svg.axis()
    .scale(x)
    .tickFormat(domainFormatter)
    .orient("bottom");


var yAxis = d3.svg.axis()
    .scale(y)
    .orient("left")
    .tickFormat(rangeFormatter)
    .ticks(5, rangeFormatter);

var svg = div.append("svg")
    .attr("width", width + margin.left + margin.right)
    .attr("height", height + margin.top + margin.bottom)
  .append("g")
    .attr("transform", "translate(" + margin.left + "," + margin.top + ")");

var data_url=div[0][0].dataset.url;
var legend=d3.select(div.node().parentNode).select('.legend');


d3.json(data_url, function(error, json) {
  if (error) throw error;
  var graphData=json[0];
  var data=graphData.data;
  var color = d3.scale.ordinal().domain(graphData.colors.map(function(d,i){return i}))
  .range(graphData.colors);
  var domain=data.map(function(d){return d.date;});
  x.domain(domain);

  function graphValueId(i){
      return graphData.class + '_' + i + '_value'
  }

  graphData.labels.forEach(function(text,i){
    var color=graphData.colors[i];
    var html='<i style="background:' + color + '"></i> ' + text + ' <span style="float:right;margin-right:10px;" id="' + graphValueId(i) + '"></span>'
    legend.append('p').html(html);
  });
  
  data.forEach(function(d) {
      var y0 = 0;
      d.values = color.domain().map(function(i) { return {date: d.date, y0: y0, y1: y0 += +d.count[i]}; });
      d.total = d.values[d.values.length - 1].y1;
  });
  y.domain([0, d3.max(data, function(d) { return d.total; })]);

  var domainTickValues=[];
  var skip=Math.round(40/x.rangeBand());
  if (skip<=0) skip=1;
  for (var i=0;i<x.domain().length;i++) {
    if (i % skip==0) domainTickValues.push(x.domain()[i]);
  }
  if (x.domain().length % 5 !=0) domainTickValues.push(x.domain()[x.domain().length-1]);
  xAxis.tickValues(domainTickValues);

  var xShift=shiftAxis ?  x.rangeBand()/2.0 * 1.1 : 0;
  
  svg.append("g")
      .attr("class", "x axis")
      .attr("transform", "translate(" + xShift + "," + height + ")")
      .call(xAxis);

  svg.append("g")
      .attr("class", "y axis")
      .call(yAxis);
//    .append("text")
//      .attr("transform", "rotate(-90)")
//      .attr("y", 6)
//      .attr("dy", ".71em")
//      .style("text-anchor", "end")
//      .text("Probability");

    function updateTooltip(d,i){
       color.domain().forEach(function(j){
             var value=d && i==j ? (domainLabelFormatter(d.date) + ': ' +rangeFormatter(d.y1-d.y0)) : '';
             d3.select('#'+graphValueId(j)).text( value);
       });
    }

  var year=svg.selectAll(".year")
    .data(data)
        .enter().append("g")
          .attr("class", "g");
  year.selectAll(".color-bar")
      .data(function(d) { return d.values; })
    .enter().append("rect")
      .attr("class", graphData.class + " color-bar")
      .attr("fill", graphData.color)
      .attr("x", function(d) { return x(d.date); })
      .attr("width", x.rangeBand())
      .attr("y", function(d) { return y(d.y1); })
      .attr("height", function(d) { return Math.max(0, y(d.y0) - y(d.y1)); })
      .attr("fill",function(d,i) {return color(i);})
      .on('mouseover',updateTooltip)
      .on('click',updateTooltip)
      .on('touch',updateTooltip) 
      .on('mouseout',function(){updateTooltip(null,i)});

      
});

}

var yearFormatter=d3.format();
stacked_bar_graph(d3.select("#sfh_roof"),true,yearFormatter,null,yearFormatter);
</script>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Land Use, Roads (and Parking)]]></title>
    <link href="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2016/02/29/land-use/"/>
    <updated>2016-02-29T21:10:05-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2016/02/29/land-use</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The other day at the <a href="https://www.sfu.ca/publicsquare/upcoming-events/city-conversations/2016/Feb-18-2016.html">SFU&rsquo;s City Conversations</a>
someone asked a question about space dedicated to roads, and how that could be unlocked
to aid housing. He mentioned what percentage of space is currently dedicated to roads. I forgot the number,
but I thought to myself that I should look that up for all Metro Vancouver communities. So here we go.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>Actually, it would be interesting to compare how land is allocated to all kinds of land uses across Metro Vancouver, not just roads.
And with their excellent
<a href="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2016/01/31/land-use/">land use dataset</a> it&rsquo;s easy enough to do, justifying spending
two hours on this. <a href="https://mountainmath.ca/land_use/map">Looking at the land use map</a>
one can see that there are some issues with using the dataset for
that purpose, for example the roads within
Stanly Park are missing, as parking lots in Vancouver parks. So this slightly overestimates the green space. But when
added up this won&rsquo;t do much to change the overall area of each land use.</p>

<h3>Land Use Breakdown</h3>

<p>Let&rsquo;s start with a simple chart summing up the land use in each of Metro Vancouver&rsquo;s Municipalities. Just select the one
you are interested in from the dropdown.</p>

<div id="land_use_breakdown" class="land_use"></div>


<p>City of Vancouver stands out as the municipality with the largest proportion of area dedicated to roads right of way.
The right of way includes nature strips, sidewalks, and of course on-street parking.</p>

<h3>Built Area Land Use</h3>

<p>For some of the municipalities large &ldquo;Natural Areas&rdquo; and &ldquo;Undeveloped Area&rdquo; make it difficult to discern the makeup of
the built up areas. So here comes the same graph with some of the large space-cosuming categories taken out.</p>

<div id="land_use_breakdown2" class="land_use"></div>


<p>What&rsquo;s remarkable is that City of Vancouver still is the clear winner in terms of space taken up by roads right of way.</p>

<h3>Roads right of way</h3>

<p>It might be interesting to compute more precisely how the roads right of way is used. But that requires a lot more work.
The City of Vancouver has a dataset with road widths, which would help separate area taken by roads from area taken by
sidewalks and nature strips. One could use google maps to estimate to estimate the amount of space taking up by on-street
parking by sampling a couple of roads and scaling this according to road area. Too much work for me right now, maybe one day I will
have a good enough reason to dedicate some time to this.</p>

<h3>Parking</h3>

<p>Parking in particular is a land use that is artificially inflated. We pay lots of money to buy private property to live
on, and then continue to pay property taxes for that privilege. But we pay nothing to store our vehicles on public roads.</p>

<p>At current land values in Vancouver it just does not make any sense to socialize the cost of parking. A 12m&sup2; on-street
parking space at a low-balled $3000/m&sup2; value is worth $36,000. If we were to price parking at value, rather than
socializing the cost we could have a discussion about using that space more effectively. Killing the parking subsidy
would have a substantial impact on demand (and car ownership), freeing up space to be re-allocated for other uses. For
example for housing by increasing lot sizes and making multi-unit structures more feasible, especally on corner lots.</p>

<hr>


<h3>Update</h3>

<p>Saw a <a href="https://twitter.com/d3visualization/status/705421356222029824">great little data visualization fly by today</a> that
is just the missing link in the above visualizations. A simple way to visualize where all the municipalities stand in
relation to one another. Thought I would throw that in real quick.</p>

<div>
 <div id="radviz" class="radviz"></div>
<div class="radviz-list-container">
        <div class="muni"></div>
        <div class="list"></div>
</div>
<div style="clear:both;"></div>
</div>




<div><script src="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/javascripts/land_use_breakdown.js"></div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[On Condos]]></title>
    <link href="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2016/02/10/on-condos/"/>
    <updated>2016-02-10T11:01:47-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2016/02/10/on-condos</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Lots has been said about the upper end of owned dwellings. The movement of the &ldquo;million dollar line&rdquo;, the emergence of
the &ldquo;two million dollar line&rdquo; and &ldquo;multi-million dollar lines&rdquo;. Most of that discussion is focused on
<a href="http://www.mountainmath.ca/map/assessment?filter=sfh" target="_blank">single detached homes</a> or on proxies for &ldquo;single detached&rdquo; like
<a href="http://www.mountainmath.ca/map/assessment?filter=rs" target="_blank">RS zoned properties</a>.</p>

<p>But all of these maps have a clear bias toward the more expensive homes. Everyone knows by now where the most expensive properties
are. But where are the more affordable ones?</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>Before continuing and getting disappointed at the end, we want to highlight the huge limitations when looking for affordable homes.
There is no freely available data on the
floor area or number of bedrooms for each dwelling unit. Next to the price and location (which we have), these are the most
important features of a dwelling. And this limits the usefulness of all that follows.</p>

<p>Why continue? It gives a glimpse of what kind of analysis could be done if the information would be <em>freely</em> available.</p>

<h3>The Elephant in the Room</h3>

<p>In principle all this information is available, <a href="https://twitter.com/bcassessment">BCAssessment</a> has all this data. And they even make it
<a href="http://evaluebc.bcassessment.ca/Default.aspx#">available on their (quite nice) eValue website</a>. But their terms of use
prevent us and others from using this information. Most of the information used in the analysis here originates from BCAssessment,
but it comes via the City of Vancouver that has made the data available through their open data portal.</p>

<p>As I understand it, the main reason why this data is not freely available is that BCAssessment is charged to recover their
own operating cost. So they hold onto their data and try to sell it for cost recovery. In the process of which they harm
the ability of municipalities to plan properly and the public to get a clear idea where things are at and have a fact-based
discussion on how to move forward. Which creates large amounts of friction and may lead to social and economic damages far
exceeding any revenue collected by BCAssessment.</p>

<p>Personally, I don&rsquo;t believe that holding back data is a smart way to run a government. You might want to
<a href="http://twitter.com/home/?status=@bcassessment Please add %23openData license to information you publish on eValue! %23giveUsData" target="_blank">ask BCAssessment to #giveUsData</a>.</p>

<p>For now, let&rsquo;s put the data that we do have to the best use and see what we can tease out.</p>

<h3>Locating the Most Affordable Dwellings</h3>

<p><a href="https://mountainmath.ca/map/special/101" target="_blank"><img  src="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/images/strata.png" style="width:50%;float:left;margin-right:10px;"></a>
Stating the obvious, the most affordable homes aren&rsquo;t &ldquo;single detached&rdquo;, they are condos. And condos have been largely
absent from the affordability debate, although they make up the majority of owned dwelling units in the City of Vancouver.</p>

<p>Let&rsquo;s start off with a <a href="http://mountainmath.ca/map/special/101" target="_blank">map of the roughly 4,500 stratified residential or mixed use properties in Vancouver housing a total of about 10,2000 strata units</a>.
The exact numbers are hard to pin down. (<a href="http://twitter.com/home/?status=@bcassessment Please add %23openData license to information you publish on eValue! %23giveUsData" target="_blank">#giveUsData</a>)</p>

<p>The distribution of stratified units by the total number of strata units
per building gives an idea of the types of strata units that are out there.</p>

<div style="margin:10px 50px;padding:5px;border: 1px solid black;border-radius:5px;">
<div id="graph_strata_by_number" style="height:200px;max-width:640px;" data-url="/data/strata_by_number.json"></div>
<div class="legend no-margin">
  <p><i style="background:steelblue"></i> Number of strata units by size of strata <span style="float:right;margin-right:10px;" id="unit_counts_value"></span></p>
</div>
</div>


<p>The horizontal axis is not linear, and the bin sizes are not equal, which makes the graph a little difficult to read. We chose bins at
2, 4, 8, 10, 16, 20 at the low end, then of width 10 up to 200, from there width 20 up to 300 and then 400, 500 and 700 at
the top end. Lazy me apologizes for the poor graphic.</p>

<p>We immediately notice the 4,152 strata units in stratas with exactly 2 units usually referred to as &ldquo;duplexes&rdquo;.
There are a lot of strata units are in stratas of size between 20 and 50, but
otherwise the units are fairly well distributed over different building sizes. At the high end there are fewer buildings,
but each with lots of units. So there our graph becomes a little jerky and heavily depends on the cutoffs we choose.</p>

<p>To get a basic idea on how much these units cost we plot the number of strata units by price bracket.</p>

<div style="margin:10px 50px;padding:5px;border: 1px solid black;border-radius:5px;">
<div id="graph_strata_by_price" style="height:200px;max-width:640px;" data-url="/data/strata_by_price.json"></div>
<div class="legend no-margin">
  <p><i style="background:steelblue"></i> Number of strata units by price <span style="float:right;margin-right:10px;" id="affordable_value"></span></p>
</div>
</div>


<p>The distribution looks largely as one would expect. It peaks between the $400k and $500k mark, with a median value of
$482,000. But there are a couple of things that jump out. Firstly, there are suspiciously many condos
below $100k, more than half of which (445 to be precise), are less than $50k. There are places where one could by
a condo for that price, but not in Vancouver. These are stratified parking spaces or other amenity spaces.</p>

<p>Next let&rsquo;s focus in on the 8,313 duplex and multi-plex units with 8 or fewer units (in 2,995 buildings) and plot these
separately.</p>

<div style="margin:10px 50px;padding:5px;border: 1px solid black;border-radius:5px;">
<div id="graph_multiplex_by_price" style="height:200px;max-width:640px;" data-url="/data/multiplex.json"></div>
<div class="legend no-margin">
  <p><i style="background:steelblue"></i> Number of multiplex units by price <span style="float:right;margin-right:10px;" id="multiplex_value"></span></p>
</div>
</div>


<p>We see that the price distribution for multiplex units peaks at a higher price between $800k and $900k, but the overall
numbers are quite small when compared to all strata units.</p>

<h3>Affordable Strata Units</h3>

<p>Let&rsquo;s try to understand where the &ldquo;affordable&rdquo; housing stock is, which we take to be units below $500k, or roughly the
bottom half of the distribution. We would like to map the properties containing housing
units for each of our price brackets, but this gets tricky since the dataset does not hold
information which units are parking spaces and which are commercial.</p>

<p>We need to take care of the problem with needing to distinguish parking spaces from housing units. And from commercial units.
(<a href="http://twitter.com/home/?status=@bcassessment Please add %23openData license to information you publish on eValue! %23giveUsData" target="_blank">#giveUsData</a>) So we are left with
using proxies, so let&rsquo;s set a cutoff price so that most units below are parking stalls and most units above are (residential)
units.</p>

<p>Generally, parking spaces should not cost more than $50,000 which is roughly the cost to build underground
parking. Around $40,000 if it&rsquo;s only one level, getting up to $75,000 (or sometimes even more) when having to go down deeper or water becomes an issue. The
fact that some spaces go for significantly less is the result of mandatory parking minimums. Some parking spaces may be worth
more than $100,000 as some people are willing to pay a premium for a convenient spot. That may mean a spot next to the
elevator by the exit ramp, or simply a parking spot in a specific building that is under supplied and trekking across the
street to a spot somewhere else is inconvenient enough. Or some stratified parking spaces might consist of several
parking spots.</p>

<h3>Location of Affordable Condos</h3>

<p><a href="https://mountainmath.ca/map/special/110" target="_blank"><img  src="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/images/strata_500k.png" style="width:50%;float:left;margin-right:10px;"></a>
Since it is impossible to pick out the housing units out of all the strata units, all we can do is map all strata units,
understanding that
those below $50k are most likely parking spaces, those between $50k and $100k could be parking or housing (or commercial) and the
majority of units above $100k are housing.</p>

<p>And we can&rsquo;t actually map the individual units, only the buildings that house the units. Here are maps of the buildings
housing the units in each of the lower brackets.</p>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://mountainmath.ca/map/special/41" target="_blank">&lt; $100k (715 units in 17 buildings)</a></li>
<li><a href="https://mountainmath.ca/map/special/42" target="_blank">$100k &ndash; $200k (2,415 units in 198 buildings)</a></li>
<li><a href="https://mountainmath.ca/map/special/43" target="_blank">$200k &ndash; $300k (10,270 units in 644 buildings)</a></li>
<li><a href="https://mountainmath.ca/map/special/44" target="_blank">$300k &ndash; $400k (19,128 units in 1,112 buildings)</a></li>
<li><a href="https://mountainmath.ca/map/special/45" target="_blank">$400k &ndash; $500k (20,538 units in 1,219 buildings)</a></li>
</ul>


<p>Clickin into a particular building and hitting the &ldquo;more&rdquo; button will pull up (a slightly cleaned) tax roster where you
can get more information on the units. And if you are really interested in finding out more about a particular one
you can always <a href="http://evaluebc.bcassessment.ca/Default.aspx#">head on over to BCAssessment&rsquo;s eValue website</a> to look up
more of those details that BCAssessment keeps in public view but locked off from systematic public scrutiny.
(<a href="http://twitter.com/home/?status=@bcassessment Please add %23openData license to information you publish on eValue! %23giveUsData" target="_blank">#giveUsData</a>)</p>

<h3>Makeup of Condos</h3>

<p>The built quality of strata units is generally higher, dollar for dollar, than that of single family homes. This should not
come as a surprise as land is very expensive and stata units tend to use land more efficiently. There are only 27 residential
or mixed use strata buildings that classify as <em>teardowns</em>,
<a href="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2016/01/18/redevelopment/">with a teardown coefficient below 5%</a>.
And 25 of these are duplexes, one is a 3-plex and one an 8-plex. There are no condos buildings with more than 8 units that
fit our most restrictive definition of <em>teardown</em>.</p>

<p>Next we explore what kind of buildings the affordable units are in by graphing the number of units in several price ranges
per size of the strata building it is in.</p>

<div style="margin:10px 50px;padding:5px;border: 1px solid black;border-radius:5px;">
<div id="graph_affordable_strata_by_number" style="height:200px;max-width:640px;" data-url="/data/affordable_strata_by_number.json"></div>
<div class="legend no-margin">
</div>
</div>


<p>It looks like buildings with 20 to 60 units are quite good at producing affordable units. Partially that&rsquo;s due to their
abundance, but graphing the percentage of units in each price bracket confirms that these buildings tend to produce a
nice mixture of low and high value condos. But larger condo buildings can also achieve this, although the actual performance
of what has been built is mixed. Other factors, for example building age, are likely also at play here.</p>

<div style="margin:10px 50px;padding:5px;border: 1px solid black;border-radius:5px;">
<div id="graph_percentage_affordable_strata_by_number" style="height:200px;max-width:640px;" data-url="/data/percentage_affordable_strata_by_number.json"></div>
<div class="legend no-margin">
</div>
</div>


<p>To see what the distribution of strata units by age is, we use the same price cutoffs and sort the strata units into age
brackets. Since we are mostly interested in the more affordable units we sort out units in buildings with 4 or fewer units.
These units might skew some of the age brackets.</p>

<div style="margin:10px 50px;padding:5px;border: 1px solid black;border-radius:5px;">
<div id="graph_affordable_strata_by_age" style="height:200px;max-width:640px;" data-url="/data/affordable_strata_by_age.json"></div>
<div class="legend no-margin">
</div>
</div>


<p>To highlight the proportional makeup we again and graph this again as percentages.</p>

<div style="margin:10px 50px;padding:5px;border: 1px solid black;border-radius:5px;">
<div id="graph_percentage_affordable_strata_by_age" style="height:200px;max-width:640px;" data-url="/data/percentage_affordable_strata_by_age.json"></div>
<div class="legend no-margin">
</div>
</div>


<p>We see how generally the percentage of more affordable units increases with the age of the building. Newer units generally
tend to be more expensive at first and becoming more affordable over time as the building ages.</p>

<h3>Taking Stock</h3>

<p>If you read this far you probably agree that this exercise was mostly a waste of time. Hopefully you are earger to see this
analysis split up by number of bedrooms and floor area. If you are all riled up at the lack of data and BCAssessment
not giving out this information with a clean open data license you might want to drop them a line and
<a href="http://twitter.com/home/?status=@bcassessment Please add %23openData license to information you publish on eValue! %23giveUsData" target="_blank">ask for at least the information they publish eValue to be made available with an #openData license!</a></p>

<p>I am still hopeful that this might happen some day, and we can get a much better picture of the buildings in BC cities
and check how they perform in fulfilling the needs of the community. And learn from that to make informed policy choices.</p>

<script>

function stacked_bar_graph(div,shiftAxis,domainFormatter,rangeFormatter,domainLabelFormatter){
    if (!domainFormatter) domainFormatter=d3.format("d")
    if (!rangeFormatter)
     rangeFormatter = function (y) {
        return y;
     };
     if (!domainLabelFormatter) domainLabelFormatter=domainFormatter;

var margin = {top: 20, right: 20, bottom: 40, left: 70},
    width = parseInt(div.style("width")) - margin.left - margin.right,
    height = parseInt(div.style("height")) - margin.top - margin.bottom;

var x = d3.scale.ordinal()
    .rangeRoundBands([0, width], .1);

var y = d3.scale.linear()
    .range([height, 0]);


var xAxis = d3.svg.axis()
    .scale(x)
    .tickFormat(domainFormatter)
    .orient("bottom");


var yAxis = d3.svg.axis()
    .scale(y)
    .orient("left")
    .tickFormat(rangeFormatter)
    .ticks(5, rangeFormatter);

var svg = div.append("svg")
    .attr("width", width + margin.left + margin.right)
    .attr("height", height + margin.top + margin.bottom)
  .append("g")
    .attr("transform", "translate(" + margin.left + "," + margin.top + ")");

var data_url=div[0][0].dataset.url;
var legend=d3.select(div.node().parentNode).select('.legend');


d3.json(data_url, function(error, json) {
  if (error) throw error;
  var graphData=json[0];
  var data=graphData.data;
  var color = d3.scale.ordinal().domain(graphData.colors.map(function(d,i){return i}))
  .range(graphData.colors);
  var domain=data.map(function(d){return d.date;});
  x.domain(domain);

  function graphValueId(i){
      return graphData.class + '_' + i + '_value'
  }

  graphData.labels.forEach(function(text,i){
    var color=graphData.colors[i];
    var html='<i style="background:' + color + '"></i> ' + text + ' <span style="float:right;margin-right:10px;" id="' + graphValueId(i) + '"></span>'
    legend.append('p').html(html);
  });
  
  data.forEach(function(d) {
      var y0 = 0;
      d.values = color.domain().map(function(i) { return {date: d.date, y0: y0, y1: y0 += +d.count[i]}; });
      d.total = d.values[d.values.length - 1].y1;
  });
  y.domain([0, d3.max(data, function(d) { return d.total; })]);

  var domainTickValues=[];
  var skip=Math.round(40/x.rangeBand());
  if (skip<=0) skip=1;
  for (var i=0;i<x.domain().length;i++) {
    if (i % skip==0) domainTickValues.push(x.domain()[i]);
  }
  if (x.domain().length % 5 !=0) domainTickValues.push(x.domain()[x.domain().length-1]);
  xAxis.tickValues(domainTickValues);

  var xShift=shiftAxis ?  x.rangeBand()/2.0 * 1.1 : 0;
  
  svg.append("g")
      .attr("class", "x axis")
      .attr("transform", "translate(" + xShift + "," + height + ")")
      .call(xAxis);

  svg.append("g")
      .attr("class", "y axis")
      .call(yAxis);
//    .append("text")
//      .attr("transform", "rotate(-90)")
//      .attr("y", 6)
//      .attr("dy", ".71em")
//      .style("text-anchor", "end")
//      .text("Probability");

    function updateTooltip(d,i){
       color.domain().forEach(function(j){
             var value=d && i==j ? (domainLabelFormatter(d.date) + ': ' +rangeFormatter(d.y1-d.y0)) : '';
             d3.select('#'+graphValueId(j)).text( value);
       });
    }

  var year=svg.selectAll(".year")
    .data(data)
        .enter().append("g")
          .attr("class", "g");
  year.selectAll(".color-bar")
      .data(function(d) { return d.values; })
    .enter().append("rect")
      .attr("class", graphData.class + " color-bar")
      .attr("fill", graphData.color)
      .attr("x", function(d) { return x(d.date); })
      .attr("width", x.rangeBand())
      .attr("y", function(d) { return y(d.y1); })
      .attr("height", function(d) { return Math.max(0, y(d.y0) - y(d.y1)); })
      .attr("fill",function(d,i) {return color(i);})
      .on('mouseover',updateTooltip)
      .on('click',updateTooltip)
      .on('touch',updateTooltip) 
      .on('mouseout',function(){updateTooltip(null,i)});

      
});

}

function bar_graph(div,shiftAxis,domainFormatter,rangeFormatter,domainLabelFormatter){
    if (!domainFormatter) domainFormatter=d3.format("d")
    if (!rangeFormatter)
     rangeFormatter = function (y) {
        return y;
     };
     if (!domainLabelFormatter) domainLabelFormatter=domainFormatter;

var margin = {top: 20, right: 20, bottom: 40, left: 70},
    width = parseInt(div.style("width")) - margin.left - margin.right,
    height = parseInt(div.style("height")) - margin.top - margin.bottom;

var x = d3.scale.ordinal()
    .rangeRoundBands([0, width], .1);

var y = d3.scale.linear()
    .range([height, 0]);


var xAxis = d3.svg.axis()
    .scale(x)
    .tickFormat(domainFormatter)
    .orient("bottom");


var yAxis = d3.svg.axis()
    .scale(y)
    .orient("left")
    .tickFormat(rangeFormatter)
    .ticks(5, rangeFormatter);

var svg = div.append("svg")
    .attr("width", width + margin.left + margin.right)
    .attr("height", height + margin.top + margin.bottom)
  .append("g")
    .attr("transform", "translate(" + margin.left + "," + margin.top + ")");

var data_url=div[0][0].dataset.url;

d3.json(data_url, function(error, json) {
  if (error) throw error;
  var graphData=json[0];
  var data=graphData.data;
  x.domain(data.map(function(d) { return d.date }));
  y.domain([0, d3.max(data, function(d) { return d.count; })]);
  
  var domainTickValues=[];
  var skip=Math.round(40/x.rangeBand());
  if (skip<=0) skip=1;
  for (var i=0;i<x.domain().length;i++) {
    if (i % skip==0) domainTickValues.push(x.domain()[i]);
  }
  if (x.domain().length % 5 !=0) domainTickValues.push(x.domain()[x.domain().length-1]);
  xAxis.tickValues(domainTickValues);

  var xShift=shiftAxis ?  x.rangeBand()/2.0 * 1.1 : 0;
  
  svg.append("g")
      .attr("class", "x axis")
      .attr("transform", "translate(" + xShift + "," + height + ")")
      .call(xAxis);

  svg.append("g")
      .attr("class", "y axis")
      .call(yAxis);
//    .append("text")
//      .attr("transform", "rotate(-90)")
//      .attr("y", 6)
//      .attr("dy", ".71em")
//      .style("text-anchor", "end")
//      .text("Probability");

  svg.selectAll(".bar")
      .data(data)
    .enter().append("rect")
      .attr("class", graphData.class + " bar")
      .attr("fill", graphData.color)
      .attr("x", function(d) { return x(d.date); })
      .attr("width", x.rangeBand())
      .attr("y", function(d) { return y(d.count); })
      .attr("height", function(d) { return height - y(d.count); })
      .on('mouseover',function(d){
         d3.select('#'+this.classList[0]+'_value').text(domainLabelFormatter(d.date) + ': ' + rangeFormatter(d.count)) 
      }).on('click',function(d){
       d3.select('#'+this.classList[0]+'_value').text(domainLabelFormatter(d.date) + ': ' + rangeFormatter(d.count)) 
      }).on('touch',function(d){
         d3.select('#'+this.classList[0]+'_value').text(domainLabelFormatter(d.date) + ': ' + rangeFormatter(d.count)) 
      }).on('mouseout',function(){d3.select('#'+this.classList[0]+'_value').text('')});

      
});

}


var priceFormatter2=d3.format("$,");
    var priceFormatter = function (y) {
        return y>=1000000 ? (priceFormatter2(y/1000000) + 'm') : (priceFormatter2(y/1000) + 'k');
    };
    var brackets=[100000,200000,300000,400000,500000,600000,700000,800000,900000,1000000,2000000,10000000,20000000,40000000]

var binFormatter=function(top){
    var bottom=0;
    if (top<=1000000) bottom=top-100000;
    else if (top==2000000) bottom= 1000000;
    else if (top==10000000) bottom= 2000000;
    else if (top=20000000) bottom= 10000000;
    else bottom=20000000;
    return priceFormatter(bottom) + ' - ' + priceFormatter(top);
}
var percentageFormatter=d3.format("%");
var numberFormatter=d3.format(",");
var numberBinFormatter=function(top){
    var     bins=[0,1,2,4,8,10,16,20,30,40,50,60,70,80,90,100,110,120,130,140,150,160,170,180,190,200,300,400,500,700];
    var index=0;
    while (bins[index]<top && index<bins.length) index ++;
    bottom=bins[index-1]+1;
    return (bottom == top) ? numberFormatter(bottom) : numberFormatter(bottom) + ' - ' + numberFormatter(top);
}
var yearFormatter=d3.format();//function(d){return d;};
var yearBinFormatter=function(top){
     var     bins=[1970,1980,1990,1995,2000,2005,2010,2020];
     var index=0;
     while (bins[index]<top && index<bins.length) index ++;
     bottom=bins[index-1]+1;
     return (bottom == top) ? yearFormatter(bottom) : yearFormatter(bottom) + ' - ' + yearFormatter(top);
}
bar_graph(d3.select("#graph_strata_by_price"),true,priceFormatter,null,binFormatter);
bar_graph(d3.select("#graph_multiplex_by_price"),true,priceFormatter,null,binFormatter);
bar_graph(d3.select("#graph_strata_by_number"),true,numberFormatter,null,numberBinFormatter);
stacked_bar_graph(d3.select("#graph_affordable_strata_by_number"),true,numberFormatter,null,numberBinFormatter);
stacked_bar_graph(d3.select("#graph_percentage_affordable_strata_by_number"),true,numberFormatter,percentageFormatter,numberBinFormatter);
stacked_bar_graph(d3.select("#graph_affordable_strata_by_age"),true,yearFormatter,null,yearBinFormatter);
stacked_bar_graph(d3.select("#graph_percentage_affordable_strata_by_age"),true,yearFormatter,percentageFormatter,yearBinFormatter);
</script>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[On Teardowns]]></title>
    <link href="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2016/01/18/redevelopment/"/>
    <updated>2016-01-18T09:52:33-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2016/01/18/redevelopment</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="https://mountainmath.ca/map/special/17"><img  src="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/images/teardowns.png" style="width:50%;float:left;margin-right:10px;"></a>
On the heels of the <a href="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2016/01/17/updated-vancouver-assessment-data/">new assessment data</a> we
can start to slice the data in different ways to understand various aspects of the real estate landscape in Vancouver. The
fact that <a href="http://vancouver.ca/your-government/open-data-catalogue.aspx">Vancouver Open Data</a> makes historic data available
gives the ability to look for changes over time.</p>

<p><a href="https://mountainmath.ca/map/assessment">Our maps</a> explore this by visualizing some aspects of these changes for all
properties, but it might also be useful to filter the properties we show to focus in on specific criteria.</p>

<p>&ldquo;Teardowns&rdquo; always triggers lots of emotions in Vancouver. Without looking at the emotional side and trying to avoid any
judgement we will
investigate the data to understand what buildings have been torn down recently and predict which buildings will get torn
down next. And map them. Long story short, we predict that
1 in 6 buildings <a href="https://mountainmath.ca/map/special/17?layer=4">on this map</a> (and then some more with lower teardown probability)
will get torn down and rebuilt by 2026.</p>

<h3>Building age temporal distribution</h3>

<!-- more -->


<p>To start understanding teardowns and rebuilds let&rsquo;s look at the <a href="https://mountainmath.ca/map/assessment?layer=7">age of the building stock</a>.</p>

<p>To get a better overview of the building stock through time we can graph the number of buildings by age. We look at buildings, not units. So a stratified
building with 100 units would still count as one building in our graph. And it is not looking at how many buildings were
built in each year, but how many buildings that were built in a given year are still standing today.</p>

<p>We still have 7 buildings in Vancouver that were built before 1900 (the earliest from 1800). Skipping these we graph the
rest to get:</p>

<div style="margin:10px 50px;padding:5px;border: 1px solid black;border-radius:5px;">
<div id="graph_age" style="height:200px;max-width:640px;" data-url="/data/building_age.json"></div>
<div class="legend no-margin">
  <p><i style="background:steelblue"></i> Number of Buildings by Building Age <span style="float:right;margin-right:10px;" id="building_age_value"></span></p>
</div>
</div>


<p>Starting with 1950 the distribution of buildings by age is quite uniform, with a short peak around the early 1990s.</p>

<p>The dip at the end is due to some lag in new buildings showing up in the property dataset. Looking at the more recent history
it is safe to assume that the number of buildings still standing corresponds well to the buildings of units built in that year.
So the pace of new buildings right now seems to fit in quite well with the recent history and is a little lower than the
peak in the early 1990s.</p>

<h3>Recent Building stock (and recent teardowns) spatial distribution</h3>

<p><a href="https://mountainmath.ca/map/special/15"><img  src="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/images/rebuilds.png" style="width:50%;float:right"></a>
The next question is to focus on the spatial distribution of recent redevelopment by filtering out older buildings.
Being too lazy to add a bush for dynamic selection of time ranges I just made a static (in time) view only showing the
<a href="https://mountainmath.ca/map/special/15?zoom=13">6883 properties built after 2006</a>. It is quite safe to assume that most
of those new buildings replaced older ones that were torn down. So this map of new buildings is also a map of locations
of buildings that were torn down in the last 10 years.</p>

<p>What&rsquo;s interesting is when selecting
<a href="https://mountainmath.ca/map/special/15?zoom=16&amp;lat=49.2341&amp;lng=-123.1824&amp;layer=4">relative building value view</a> that
there are some properties that have been recently re-developed with increadibly low building value, like the property
at 5649 Dunbar St. <strike>This gives a window into some of the imperfections of the BC Assessment process where the building
value after re-development is not properly reflected in their dataset.</strike> In this case it seems to be
<a href="https://www.google.ca/maps/@49.2351182,-123.1853038,3a,75y,264.36h,81.1t/data=!3m6!1e1!3m4!1s_weW4bEWpmcKGA-Ppk0d_Q!2e0!7i13312!8i6656">a property whose only &ldquo;improvement&rdquo; seems to be the pavement on it</a>.</p>

<p>It also shows that recent building (or teardown) activity is fairly uniform across the city, with only some areas standing out as having little
development like the West End, parts of Kitsilano and Strathcona.</p>

<h3>What gets torn down and rebuilt next?</h3>

<p>The big question is of course where new buildings get built next. In a built up space like Vancouver there are few sites
left where building a new building does not mean tearing down an old one. So another way to ask that question is: What
gets torn down next?</p>

<h3>Teardown Probability</h3>

<p>Predicting which building will get torn down next is of course impossible. So what we try to do is assign a &ldquo;teardown
probability&rdquo; to each building.</p>

<p>Let&rsquo;s first try to understand why a particular building might get torn down as opposed to the one next door. Typically
buildings get torn down at the time when they change ownership. So if a building is not sold, it is far less likely to
get torn down. So what makes a building more likely to get torn down when it is sold? One hypothesis would be that the
value of the building relative to the land should play an important factor. Let&rsquo;s test this hypothesis using the data.</p>

<p>We take the 2006 tax dataset as a baseline and check how many of the buildings have been torn down by 2016. Refer to the
Methodology and Data section at the botton for the messy details. We only
count buildings, so we count a strata lot with 100 units in the same building as one building. Then we use the 2016 dataset
to check how many of them are still around, identifying them by their tax coordinate and again asking they be marked as
being built no later than 2006.</p>

<p>These criteria capture well what we are looking for, but they are not perfect. As a predictive variable we use the</p>

<div style="padding:5px;border: 1px solid grey;border-radius:4px;width:80%;margin:0 auto;">
<h5 style="text-align:center;">Teardown Coefficient</h5>
The *teardown coefficient* is the percentage of the total assessed value that is attributed to the building. More formally
it&#8217;s the ratio of the building value by the sum of the building and land values.
</div>


<p>So we sort the properties by their <em>teardown coefficient</em> using the
2006 tax assessment data and we check how each group fares.</p>

<p>First up a graph of the distribution of buildigs in 2006 by their <em>teardown coefficient</em>.</p>

<div style="margin:10px 50px;padding:5px;border: 1px solid black;border-radius:5px;">
<div id="graph_buildings_by_teardown" style="height:200px;max-width:640px;" data-url="/data/buildings_by_teardown.json"></div>
<div class="legend no-margin">
  <p><i style="background:steelblue"></i> Number of Buildings by *teardown coefficient* <span style="float:right;margin-right:10px;" id="buildings_by_teardown_value"></span></p>
</div>
</div>


<p>Next up the number of buildings in each category that got torn down and rebuilt by 2016:</p>

<div style="margin:10px 50px;padding:5px;border: 1px solid black;border-radius:5px;">
<div id="graph_teardowns" style="height:200px;max-width:640px;" data-url="/data/teardowns.json"></div>
<div class="legend no-margin">
  <p><i style="background:steelblue"></i> Number of Torn Down Buildings by *teardown coefficient* <span style="float:right;margin-right:10px;" id="teardowns_value"></span></p>
</div>
</div>


<p>We see that our initial hypothesis seems to hold up quite well. The number of buildings that got torn down and rebuilt
decreases as the <em>teardown coefficient</em> increases. Remember that we defined the <em>teardown coefficient</em> to be the percentage
of the building value out of the total value of the property.</p>

<p>Refer to the methodology and data section for further information on how these numbers were extracted.</p>

<p>To explore this further let&rsquo;s graph the frequency with which a building in a given <em>teardown coefficeint</em> range gets torn down.
To keep things cleaner where we only plot up to a <em>teardown coefficient</em> of 50%:</p>

<div style="margin:10px 50px;padding:5px;border: 1px solid black;border-radius:5px;">
<div id="graph_teardown_probability" style="height:200px;max-width:640px;" data-url="/data/teardown_probability.json"></div>
<div class="legend no-margin">
  <p><i style="background:steelblue"></i> Probability of Building being torn down<span style="float:right;margin-right:10px;" id="teardown_probability_value"></span></p>
</div>
</div>


<p>We see that the <em>teardown coefficient</em> has high predictive value for a building to be torn down and
being rebuilt in the following 10 years. Buildings with a <em>teardown coefficient</em> below 5% have about an 18% chance, and the
probability declines exponentially down to zero at a <em>teardown coefficient</em> of about 50%.</p>

<p>If we were more serious about this
we would fit and exponential curve to the data and compute how well it fits the data, repeat the computation for
other time frames, run it on individual neighbourhoods and maybe also on <a href="https://data.surrey.ca">data from other municipalities</a>
to properly validate our model. We could also refine the model by refining our filters, see the methodology and data section for
more details.</p>

<p>And we could add other factors that likely effect the teardown probability, like building age, proximity to arterials and
others. Of course these are not independent factors, so this kind of analysis requires more time.</p>

<h3>Predicting Teardowns</h3>

<p>Now to the main part: Predicting teardowns. How many buildings will get torn down and rebuilt in the next 10 years? Let&rsquo;s
use what we have just learned to extrapolate.</p>

<p>First up the graph of the 2016 building stock by <em>teardown coefficient</em>:</p>

<div style="margin:10px 50px;padding:5px;border: 1px solid black;border-radius:5px;">
<div id="graph_buildings_by_teardown_2" style="height:200px;max-width:640px;" data-url="/data/buildings_by_teardown_2.json"></div>
<div class="legend no-margin">
  <p><i style="background:steelblue"></i> 2016 Building stock by *teardown coefficient* <span style="float:right;margin-right:10px;" id="buildings_by_teardown_2_value"></span></p>
</div>
</div>


<p>To estimate how many buildings will get torn down and rebuilt in each category we simply multiply each bin with the teardown probability
from the frequency graph above:</p>

<div style="margin:10px 50px;padding:5px;border: 1px solid black;border-radius:5px;">
<div id="graph_teardowns_2" style="height:200px;max-width:640px;" data-url="/data/teardowns_2.json"></div>
<div class="legend no-margin">
  <p><i style="background:steelblue"></i> Estimate of Buildings rebuilt by 2026 <span style="float:right;margin-right:10px;" id="teardowns_2_value"></span></p>
</div>
</div>


<p>Bottom line, we predict around 8,000 buildings to be torn down and rebuilt by 2026. That&rsquo;s significantly more than the
around 5,900 buildings that we identified as going through this process during the prior 10 years.</p>

<h3>Open Question</h3>

<p>There are lots of assumptions that went into this estimate. While we are confident in our analysis
that properties with low <em>teardown coefficient</em> are the ones most likely to be torn down, it is less clear if the number
of properties being torn down grows linearly as the properties with low <em>teardown coefficient</em> grow. In our case the number
of properties with <em>teardown coefficient</em> below 5% grew from 20492 (21% of the 2006 stock) to 32509 (33.5% of the 2016) stock,
which may be out of the range where our simplistic extrapolation holds. One could try to understand this by carefully
analyzing all available tax years, and not just the two extremes of the available spectrum.</p>

<h3>Mapping Teardowns</h3>

<p><a href="https://mountainmath.ca/map/special/17"><img  src="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/images/teardowns.png" style="width:50%;float:right"></a>Now that we
understand how to assign a teardown probability to buildings, let&rsquo;s map them! To keep things as simple as
possible let&rsquo;s focus in on the homes with a <em>teardown coefficient</em> below 5%. They make up the bulk in our prediction and
have the simple interpretation that a little more than 1 in 6 of these will get replaced by something else by 2026. So
<a href="https://mountainmath.ca/map/special/17">here is the interactive map</a> of just these 31301 buildings, where we have
filtered out some parks, marinas and rail lines. And this only accounts
for the 5,700 buildings predicted to be torn down with a <em>teardown coefficient</em> below 5% cutoff and neglects the roughly 2,000 more that
are predicted to be torn down that have a <em>teardown coefficient</em> above 5%.</p>

<h3>Methodology and Data</h3>

<p>Only for people who love getting their hands dirty or who want to reproduce or expand on the analysis.</p>

<p>First thing to note is that there is no way to detect &ldquo;teardowns&rdquo; in the dataset, the only way is to look at what has been
rebuilt and what has &lsquo;dropped off&rsquo;. To be more precise, there data fields to look at is the &ldquo;land coordinate&rdquo;, which links
a taxable property to a physical structure, and the &ldquo;year built&rdquo;. And both fields have problems.</p>

<p>The &ldquo;land coordinate&rdquo;
gets de-commissioned and re-assigned during certain re-develpments. And the city dataset provides no way to link the
old one to the new one. One way to do that is through the polygons that mark the property boundaries, that would allow
tracking of complex re-assemblies of land. But the city does not publish historic records of property polygons.</p>

<p>The &ldquo;year built&rdquo; also has lots of issues. Sometimes it is blank even though it records the value of the building as
greater than zero. Sometimes the &ldquo;year built&rdquo; will be set to a date later than the date of the dataset, for example the
2006 tax dataset has buildings with &ldquo;year built&rdquo; all they way up to 2013.</p>

<p>Then comes the issue of filtering. We decided to filter out parks, rail lines and marinas without structures on them. The
algorithm is somewhat simplistic, it&rsquo;s the same one that was used to filter properties for the maps. Additionally we
filter out properties from the heritage dataset. There is definitely
room for improvement here, but without a clear question of what exactly to measure
(only single family homes, or also condos or apartments, treat commercial separately, &hellip;)
it does not make much sense to invest energy into this. After all, this is just looking for a rough model.</p>

<p>So how do we detect rebuilds? We take the land coordinates from properties identified as park or heritage and sieve through
the 2006 tax data to retrieve all records that don&rsquo;t match these land coordinates and have a &ldquo;year built&rdquo; column set
as 2006 or earlier or don&rsquo;t have a &ldquo;year built&rdquo; set at all but change from zero to non-zero building value from 2006 to 2016.</p>

<p>Pretty messy. We mapped <a href="https://mountainmath.ca/map/special/15">about 6,900 buildings were built after 2006</a>,
but only traced 5,869 buildings in the 2006 tax dataset as
being torn down and rebuilt. That difference is largely explained by different selection criteria. The map only considers
properties with a &ldquo;year built&rdquo; field set, but for the analysis we also added properties that don&rsquo;t have that field set
but go from zero building value in 2006 to non-zero building value in 2016 which gets us to 7,784 &ldquo;rebuilds&rdquo;. On the other hand
in the analysis we don&rsquo;t consder the roughly 140 heritage buildings that would pass our filter of being built after 2006, and
the 2016 tax dataset has 2,422 more buildings than the 2006 dataset, some of which can be seen
<a href="https://mountainmath.ca/map/special/13">on this map</a> and are due to subdivisions being split off of the original
property.</p>

<p>Anyway, if you want to get your hand dirty on this shoot me a message and I will hook you up with my scripts.</p>

<script>


function bar_graph(div,shiftAxis,domainFormatter,rangeFormatter,domainLabelFormatter){
    if (!domainFormatter) domainFormatter=d3.format("d")
    if (!rangeFormatter)
     rangeFormatter = function (y) {
        return y;
     };
     if (!domainLabelFormatter) domainLabelFormatter=domainFormatter;

var margin = {top: 20, right: 20, bottom: 40, left: 70},
    width = parseInt(div.style("width")) - margin.left - margin.right,
    height = parseInt(div.style("height")) - margin.top - margin.bottom;

var x = d3.scale.ordinal()
    .rangeRoundBands([0, width], .1);

var y = d3.scale.linear()
    .range([height, 0]);


var xAxis = d3.svg.axis()
    .scale(x)
    .tickFormat(domainFormatter)
    .orient("bottom");


var yAxis = d3.svg.axis()
    .scale(y)
    .orient("left")
    .tickFormat(rangeFormatter)
    .ticks(5, rangeFormatter);

var svg = div.append("svg")
    .attr("width", width + margin.left + margin.right)
    .attr("height", height + margin.top + margin.bottom)
  .append("g")
    .attr("transform", "translate(" + margin.left + "," + margin.top + ")");

var data_url=div[0][0].dataset.url;

d3.json(data_url, function(error, json) {
  if (error) throw error;
  var graphData=json[0];
  var data=graphData.data;
  x.domain(data.map(function(d) { return d.date }));
  y.domain([0, d3.max(data, function(d) { return d.count; })]);
  
  var domainTickValues=[];
  var skip=Math.round(40/x.rangeBand());
  if (skip<=0) skip=1;
  for (var i=0;i<x.domain().length;i++) {
    if (i % skip==0) domainTickValues.push(x.domain()[i]);
  }
  if (x.domain().length % 5 !=0) domainTickValues.push(x.domain()[x.domain().length-1]);
  xAxis.tickValues(domainTickValues);

  var xShift=shiftAxis ?  x.rangeBand()/2.0 * 1.1 : 0;
  
  svg.append("g")
      .attr("class", "x axis")
      .attr("transform", "translate(" + xShift + "," + height + ")")
      .call(xAxis);

  svg.append("g")
      .attr("class", "y axis")
      .call(yAxis);
//    .append("text")
//      .attr("transform", "rotate(-90)")
//      .attr("y", 6)
//      .attr("dy", ".71em")
//      .style("text-anchor", "end")
//      .text("Probability");

  svg.selectAll(".bar")
      .data(data)
    .enter().append("rect")
      .attr("class", graphData.class + " bar")
      .attr("fill", graphData.color)
      .attr("x", function(d) { return x(d.date); })
      .attr("width", x.rangeBand())
      .attr("y", function(d) { return y(d.count); })
      .attr("height", function(d) { return height - y(d.count); })
      .on('mouseover',function(d){
         d3.select('#'+this.classList[0]+'_value').text(domainLabelFormatter(d.date) + ': ' + rangeFormatter(d.count)) 
      }).on('click',function(d){
       d3.select('#'+this.classList[0]+'_value').text(domainLabelFormatter(d.date) + ': ' + rangeFormatter(d.count)) 
      }).on('touch',function(d){
         d3.select('#'+this.classList[0]+'_value').text(domainLabelFormatter(d.date) + ': ' + rangeFormatter(d.count)) 
      }).on('mouseout',function(){d3.select('#'+this.classList[0]+'_value').text('')});

      
});

}

var percentageFormatter=d3.format(".1%");
var binFormatter=function(d){return percentageFormatter(d-0.025) + ' - ' + percentageFormatter(d);}
//ready_for_graph(d3.select("#graph"));
bar_graph(d3.select("#graph_age"),false);
//ready_for_graph(d3.select("#graph_buildings_by_teardown"),percentageFormatter);
//ready_for_graph(d3.select("#graph_teardowns"),percentageFormatter);
bar_graph(d3.select("#graph_buildings_by_teardown"),true,percentageFormatter,null,binFormatter);
bar_graph(d3.select("#graph_teardowns"),true,percentageFormatter,null,binFormatter);
bar_graph(d3.select("#graph_teardown_probability"),true,percentageFormatter,percentageFormatter,binFormatter);
bar_graph(d3.select("#graph_buildings_by_teardown_2"),true,percentageFormatter,null,binFormatter);
bar_graph(d3.select("#graph_teardowns_2"),true,percentageFormatter,null,binFormatter);
</script>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Updated Vancouver Assessment Data]]></title>
    <link href="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2016/01/17/updated-vancouver-assessment-data/"/>
    <updated>2016-01-17T11:34:09-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2016/01/17/updated-vancouver-assessment-data</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="https://mountainmath.ca/map/assessment?layer=4"><img  src="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/images/relative_land.jpg" style="width:50%;float:right"></a>
The friendly folks at
<a href="http://vancouver.ca/your-government/open-data-catalogue.aspx">Vancouver Open Data</a> just
<a href="https://twitter.com/VanOpenData/status/688060388190097408">updated their property assessment data</a> with the fresh 2016
property tax assessments. Time to run the script to update the <a href="https://mountainmath.ca/map/assessment">Vancouver Assessment Map</a>
with the new data. And for good measure I pasted over some of the thematic map engine from <a href="https://censusmapper.ca">CensusMapper</a>
to improve the mapping performance.</p>

<h4>Maps</h4>

<!-- more -->


<p><img  src="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/images/map_menu.png" style="width:25%;margin-left:5px;float:right">The <a href="https://mountainmath.ca/map/assessment">interactive assessment map</a> offers several views. In the panel on the top
right we can select how to view the data. It offers standard thematic maps for value change, total value, building value
and building age and zoning. And there are some options that warrant more explanation:</p>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://mountainmath.ca/map/assessment?layer=5"><em>Relative Land Value</em>:</a> The colours on the map show each property by the
land value per m&sup2;. We can immediately spot the east-west land gradient, as well as how zoning affects land value.
When zooming in we also see the effect of lot size on land value.</li>
<li><a href="https://mountainmath.ca/map/assessment?layer=10"><em>Tax Density</em>:</a> This map looks at the tax dollars collected
by the city by area. It tells us the relative rate at what each property is contributing to city services. We can again
observe the impact of exclusionary zoning.</li>
<li><a href="https://mountainmath.ca/map/assessment?layer=4"><em>Relative Value of Building</em>:</a>
<a href="https://mountainmath.ca/map/assessment?layer=4"><img  src="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/images/teardown.jpg" style="width:50%;float:right"></a>
This map simply divides the building value
by the total property value. There are many ways to interpret this map, my favourite is to use this as a &ldquo;Teardown Predictor&rdquo;.
Essentially, as the percentage of the building value approaches zero the probability that it will get torn down in the
near future increases. Imagine someone spending $1.5m to buy a property with a house valued at $37k. Many people don&rsquo;t
mind living in a house worth $37k, but someone who is spending $1.5m would probably prefer to buy a different property
with a higher quality house. Or spend more money to upgrade the house. How will it be upgraded? Renovating is in most
cases economically unsound, most people will choose to tear down and rebuild. In fact, the <em>teardown threshold</em> is
likely higher than the 2.5% in the example given. The percentage of properties in Vancouver where the building value is
less than 2.5% of the total value has slightly decreaed in the last year from 17.9% to 17.8%, but the percentage of properties
with building value less than 5% of the total value has increased from 32% to 33.5% during the last year.</li>
</ul>


<h4>The Data</h4>

<p>The data originates with BC Assessment, which estimates land and building values of each property based on recent sales
of comparable properties. The assessment was done in summer 2015 and is based on sales before that, so at this point in
time the data lags the market by about one year. Values for individual properties may well be off, depending how well
renovations and improvements were reported and how well the BC Assessment estimates work for the given property. On
average they should reflect the market about half a year to one year ago.</p>

<p>Sadly, BC Assessment does not give out their data with a license that would allow mapping it the way I do, so we have
to rely on municipalities to release it through their open data portals. The format of the data from each municipality is
different, so lazy me is only importing data from City of Vancouver, although some other nearby municipalities are also releasing
there data.</p>

<p>The motivation behind the map was to understand the building stock. Some effort was made to filter out parks, but the
algorithm is far from perfect and will often includes parks that host building
structures, as well as marinas with structures on them.</p>

<p>The new city dataset does not include the 2016 tax levy, so we still only show the 2015 tax levies until CoV updated their dataset.</p>

<h4>History</h4>

<p>Here is a quick history of the overall land and building values aggregated for Vancouver between 2006 and 2016.</p>

<div style="margin:10px 50px;padding:5px;border: 1px solid black;border-radius:5px;">
<div id="graph" style="height:200px;max-width:640px;" data-lines="/data/vancouver_stats.json"></div>
<div class="legend no-margin">
  <p><i style="background:blue"></i> Land Value <span style="float:right;margin-right:10px;" id="land_value"></span></p>
  <p><i style="background:green"></i> Building Value <span style="float:right;margin-right:10px;" id="building_value"></span></p>
</div>
</div>


<p>When looking at all properties in the city, the increase in land
value year over year was 21.4% ($45.2bn), while overall building values increased by 7.3% ($5bn). Hover, click or touch
the points in the graph to get the values for the corresponding year.</p>

<h4>Neighbourhoods</h4>

<p>Lastly a quick overview over the neighbourhoods. Land and building values have not increased evenly throughout in the year.
I aggregated all tax data by neighbourhood and split it into land value and building value increases.
These numbers should be used as guidance only, they mix lots of different types of properties and include parks.</p>

<p>Here is the breakdown by neighbourhood:</p>

<ul>
<li>Renfrew-Collingwood: Land: 30.6% ($1.2bn), Building: 5.8% ($46.0m)</li>
<li>Sunset: Land: 26.6% ($1.6bn), Building: 5.9% ($74.2m)</li>
<li>Oakridge: Land: 17.6% ($1.2bn), Building: 12.6% ($207.4m)</li>
<li>Downtown: Land: 16.9% ($0.8bn), Building: 3.2% ($91.2m)</li>
<li>Kerrisdale: Land: 18.7% ($1.3bn), Building: 3.3% ($54.1m)</li>
<li>Victoria-Fraserview: Land: 28.0% ($1.5bn), Building: 5.6% ($65.2m)</li>
<li>Grandview-Woodland: Land: 24.9% ($1.7bn), Building: 0.7% ($17.4m)</li>
<li>West End: Land: 22.6% ($2.5bn), Building: 3.5% ($188.4m)</li>
<li>Hastings-Sunrise: Land: 25.1% ($1.1bn), Building: 4.9% ($63.8m)</li>
<li>Killarney: Land: 17.8% ($0.3bn), Building: 14.1% ($241.6m)</li>
<li>Marpole: Land: 17.8% ($0.3bn), Building: 14.1% ($241.6m)</li>
<li>Kitsilano: Land: 21.6% ($3.3bn), Building: 4.3% ($134.5m)</li>
<li>Shaughnessy: Land: 18.6% ($1.7bn), Building: 7.4% ($117.7m)</li>
<li>West Point Grey: Land: 20.2% ($2.3bn), Building: 5.2% ($88.3m)</li>
<li>Fairview: Land: 19.4% ($2.0bn), Building: -1.0% (-$52.4m)</li>
<li>Downtown Eastside: Land: 21.9% ($2.6bn), Building: 4.9% ($194.9m)</li>
<li>Kensington-Cedar Cottage: Land: 24.9% ($1.7bn), Building: 0.7% ($17.4m)</li>
<li>Riley Park: Land: 26.4% ($1.0bn), Building: 4.0% ($40.2m)</li>
<li>Mount Pleasant: Land: 21.9% ($2.6bn), Building: 4.9% ($194.9m)</li>
<li>South Cambie: Land: 20.9% ($1.5bn), Building: 21.4% ($268.1m)</li>
<li>Strathcona: Land: 21.9% ($2.6bn), Building: 4.9% ($194.9m)</li>
<li>Dunbar Southlands: Land: 21.8% ($1.0bn), Building: 11.2% ($126.6m)</li>
<li>Arbutus Ridge: Land: 21.4% ($1.6bn), Building: 1.1% ($17.3m)</li>
</ul>


<p>It becomes immediately clear that the increase in property values is mostly driven by land, note that total value increases
for land and buildings are reported in billions and millions, respectively. The building stock does not
have time to catch up, with the exception of South Cambie. Fairview stands out with declining overall building values.</p>

<script>
var ready_for_graph = function() {
    var d3lines=[];
    var padding = {top: 20, right: 20, bottom: 30, left: 90};
    var prevChartWidth = 0, prevChartHeight = 0;
    var updateTransistionMS = 750; // milliseconds
    var sourceData, lineData, xScale, yScale, line;

    var symbol;
    var prefix;
    var numberFormatter = function (y) {
        return '$' + Math.round(prefix.scale(y*10))/10.0 + symbol;
    };

    var graphs=d3.select("#graph");
    var div=graphs[0][0];
    if (div==null|| div.childElementCount!=0) {return;}
    var data_url=div.dataset.url;

    // create svg and g to contain the chart contents
    var baseSvg = graphs.append("svg");
    var chartSvg=baseSvg
        .append("g")
        .attr("class", "chartContainer")
        .attr("transform", "translate(" + padding.left + "," + padding.top + ")");

    // create the x axis container
    chartSvg.append("g")
        .attr("class", "x axis");

    // create the y axis container
    chartSvg.append("g")
        .attr("class", "y axis");
    var line;
    var largest=null;
    var lineData;
    if (div.dataset.lines) {
        d3.json(div.dataset.lines,function(error,json){
        lineData=json;
        var domain=[null,null];
        var range=[null,null];
        for (var i=0;i<lineData.length;i++){
            lineData[i].data.forEach(function(d) {
                d.date = +d.date;
                d.count = +d.count;
                if (domain[0]==null || domain[0]> d.date) domain[0]= d.date;
                if (domain[1]==null || domain[1]< d.date) domain[1]= d.date;
                if (range[0]==null || range[0]> d.count) range[0]= d.count;
                if (range[1]==null || range[1]< d.count) range[1]= d.count;
            });
        }
        xScale=d3.scale.linear().domain(domain);
        var toAdd=(range[1]-range[0])/10;
        range[0]-=toAdd;
        range[1]+=toAdd;
        yScale=d3.scale.linear()
            .domain(range);

        line = d3.svg.line()
            .x(function(d) { return xScale(d.date); })
            .y(function(d) { return yScale(d.count); })
            .interpolate("linear");

        xAxis = d3.svg.axis()
            .scale(xScale)
            .orient("bottom")
            .tickFormat(d3.format("d"))
            .tickValues(domain);

        yAxis = d3.svg.axis()
            .scale(yScale)
            .orient("left")
            .tickFormat(numberFormatter)
            .ticks(5);

        prefix = d3.formatPrefix(range[1]);
        if (prefix.symbol=='K') {
            symbol='k'
        } else if (prefix.symbol=='M') {
                symbol='m'
        } else if (prefix.symbol=='G') {
            symbol='bn'
        } else if (prefix.symbol=='T') {
            symbol='tn'
        }
        updateChart(true);
        });

    }


    function updateChart(init)
    {
        // get the height and width subtracting the padding
//    var innerHeight = window.innerHeight - 20;
        var innerWidth = window.innerWidth - 20;
        var divWidth=$(div).width();
        if (divWidth==0) divWidth=$(div.parentElement.parentElement).width();
        var maxWidth=parseInt($(div).css('max-width'));
        if (divWidth==0) divWidth=innerWidth*0.8;
        if (divWidth>maxWidth) divWidth=maxWidth;
        var chartWidth = divWidth-padding.left-padding.right;//960 - margin.left - margin.right,
        var chartHeight = $(div).height()-padding.top-padding.bottom;//500 - margin.top - margin.bottom;


        // only update if chart size has changed
        if ((prevChartWidth != chartWidth) ||
            (prevChartHeight != chartHeight)) {
            prevChartWidth = chartWidth;
            prevChartHeight = chartHeight;

            //set the width and height of the SVG element
            chartSvg.attr("width", chartWidth + padding.left + padding.right)
                .attr("height", chartHeight + padding.top + padding.bottom);
            baseSvg.attr("width", chartWidth + padding.left + padding.right)
                .attr("height", chartHeight + padding.top + padding.bottom);

            // ranges are based on the width and height available so reset
            xScale.range([0, chartWidth]);
            yScale.range([chartHeight, 0]);

            if (init) {
                // if first run then just display axis with no transition
                chartSvg.select(".x")
                    .style({ 'stroke': 'grey', 'fill': 'none', 'stroke-width': '1px'})
                    .attr("transform", "translate(0," + chartHeight + ")")
                    .call(xAxis);

                chartSvg.select(".y")
                    .style({ 'stroke': 'grey', 'fill': 'none', 'stroke-width': '1px'})
                    .call(yAxis);
            }
            else {
                // for subsequent updates use a transistion to animate the axis to the new position
                var t = chartSvg.transition().duration(updateTransistionMS);

                t.select(".x")
                    .attr("transform", "translate(0," + chartHeight + ")")
                    .call(xAxis);

                t.select(".y")
                    .call(yAxis);
            }

            for (var i = 0; i < lineData.length; i++) {
                var sourceData=lineData[i].data;
                var color=lineData[i].color;
                var label=lineData[i].label;
                var className=lineData[i].class;

                // bind up the data to the line
                var lines = chartSvg.selectAll("path.line."+className)
                    .data([lineData[i].data]); // needs to be an array (size of 1 for our data) of arrays

                // transistion to new position if already exists
                lines.transition()
                    .duration(updateTransistionMS)
                    .attr("d", line);

                // add line if not already existing
                lines.enter().append("path")
                    .attr("class", "line")
                    .attr("stroke", color)
                    .attr("stroke-width", 2)
                    .attr('fill','none')
                    .attr("d", line);

                // bind up the data to an array of circles
                var circle = chartSvg.selectAll("circle."+className)
                    .data(sourceData);

                // if already existing then transistion each circle to its new position
                circle.transition()
                    .duration(updateTransistionMS)
                    .attr("cx", function (d) {
                        return xScale(d.date);
                    })
                    .attr("cy", function (d) {
                        return yScale(d.count);
                    });

                // if new circle then just display
                circle.enter().append("circle")
                    .attr("cx", function (d) {
                        return xScale(d.date);
                    })
                    .attr("cy", function (d) {
                        return yScale(d.count);
                    })
                    .attr("r", 4)
                    .attr('fill', 'transparent')
                    .style("stroke", color)
                    .style("stroke-width", 8)
                    .attr("class", className)
                    .on('mouseover',function(d){
                       d3.select('#'+this.classList[0]+'_value').text(d.date + ': ' + numberFormatter(d.count)) 
                    }).on('click',function(d){
                     d3.select('#'+this.classList[0]+'_value').text(d.date + ': ' + numberFormatter(d.count)) 
                    }).on('touch',function(d){
                       d3.select('#'+this.classList[0]+'_value').text(d.date + ': ' + numberFormatter(d.count)) 
                    }).on('mouseout',function(){d3.select('#'+this.classList[0]+'_value').text('')});

            }
        }
    }

    // look for resize but use timer to only call the update script when a resize stops
    var resizeTimer;
    window.onresize = function(event) {
        clearTimeout(resizeTimer);
        resizeTimer = setTimeout(function()
        {
            updateChart(false);
        }, 100);
    }


};
ready_for_graph();
</script>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
