<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: d3 | Mountain Doodles]]></title>
  <link href="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/categories/d3/feed.atom" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/"/>
  <updated>2016-01-31T16:30:51-08:00</updated>
  <id>http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[MountainMath]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[On Teardowns]]></title>
    <link href="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2016/01/18/redevelopment/"/>
    <updated>2016-01-18T09:52:33-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2016/01/18/redevelopment</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="https://mountainmath.ca/map/special/17"><img  src="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/images/teardowns.png" style="width:50%;float:left;margin-right:10px;"></a>
On the heels of the <a href="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2016/01/17/updated-vancouver-assessment-data/">new assessment data</a> we
can start to slice the data in different ways to understand various aspects of the real estate landscape in Vancouver. The
fact that <a href="http://vancouver.ca/your-government/open-data-catalogue.aspx">Vancouver Open Data</a> makes historic data available
gives the ability to look for changes over time.</p>

<p><a href="https://mountainmath.ca/map/assessment">Our maps</a> explore this by visualizing some aspects of these changes for all
properties, but it might also be useful to filter the properties we show to focus in on specific criteria.</p>

<p>&ldquo;Teardowns&rdquo; always triggers lots of emotions in Vancouver. Without looking at the emotional side and trying to avoid any
judgement we will
investigate the data to understand what buildings have been torn down recently and predict which buildings will get torn
down next. And map them. Long story short, we predict that
1 in 6 buildings <a href="https://mountainmath.ca/map/special/17?layer=4">on this map</a> (and then some more with lower teardown probability)
will get torn down and rebuilt by 2026.</p>

<h3>Building age temporal distribution</h3>

<!-- more -->


<p>To start understanding teardowns and rebuilds let&rsquo;s look at the <a href="https://mountainmath.ca/map/assessment?layer=7">age of the building stock</a>.</p>

<p>To get a better overview of the building stock through time we can graph the number of buildings by age. We look at buildings, not units. So a stratified
building with 100 units would still count as one building in our graph. And it is not looking at how many buildings were
built in each year, but how many buildings that were built in a given year are still standing today.</p>

<p>We still have 7 buildings in Vancouver that were built before 1900 (the earliest from 1800). Skipping these we graph the
rest to get:</p>

<div style="margin:10px 50px;padding:5px;border: 1px solid black;border-radius:5px;">
<div id="graph_age" style="height:200px;max-width:640px;" data-url="/data/building_age.json"></div>
<div class="legend no-margin">
  <p><i style="background:steelblue"></i> Number of Buildings by Building Age <span style="float:right;margin-right:10px;" id="building_age_value"></span></p>
</div>
</div>


<p>Starting with 1950 the distribution of buildings by age is quite uniform, with a short peak around the early 1990s.</p>

<p>The dip at the end is due to some lag in new buildings showing up in the property dataset. Looking at the more recent history
it is safe to assume that the number of buildings still standing corresponds well to the buildings of units built in that year.
So the pace of new buildings right now seems to fit in quite well with the recent history and is a little lower than the
peak in the early 1990s.</p>

<h3>Recent Building stock (and recent teardowns) spatial distribution</h3>

<p><a href="https://mountainmath.ca/map/special/15"><img  src="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/images/rebuilds.png" style="width:50%;float:right"></a>
The next question is to focus on the spatial distribution of recent redevelopment by filtering out older buildings.
Being too lazy to add a bush for dynamic selection of time ranges I just made a static (in time) view only showing the
<a href="https://mountainmath.ca/map/special/15?zoom=13">6883 properties built after 2006</a>. It is quite safe to assume that most
of those new buildings replaced older ones that were torn down. So this map of new buildings is also a map of locations
of buildings that were torn down in the last 10 years.</p>

<p>What&rsquo;s interesting is when selecting
<a href="https://mountainmath.ca/map/special/15?zoom=16&amp;lat=49.2341&amp;lng=-123.1824&amp;layer=4">relative building value view</a> that
there are some properties that have been recently re-developed with increadibly low building value, like the property
at 5649 Dunbar St. <strike>This gives a window into some of the imperfections of the BC Assessment process where the building
value after re-development is not properly reflected in their dataset.</strike> In this case it seems to be
<a href="https://www.google.ca/maps/@49.2351182,-123.1853038,3a,75y,264.36h,81.1t/data=!3m6!1e1!3m4!1s_weW4bEWpmcKGA-Ppk0d_Q!2e0!7i13312!8i6656">a property whose only &ldquo;improvement&rdquo; seems to be the pavement on it</a>.</p>

<p>It also shows that recent building (or teardown) activity is fairly uniform across the city, with only some areas standing out as having little
development like the West End, parts of Kitsilano and Strathcona.</p>

<h3>What gets torn down and rebuilt next?</h3>

<p>The big question is of course where new buildings get built next. In a built up space like Vancouver there are few sites
left where building a new building does not mean tearing down an old one. So another way to ask that question is: What
gets torn down next?</p>

<h3>Teardown Probability</h3>

<p>Predicting which building will get torn down next is of course impossible. So what we try to do is assign a &ldquo;teardown
probability&rdquo; to each building.</p>

<p>Let&rsquo;s first try to understand why a particular building might get torn down as opposed to the one next door. Typically
buildings get torn down at the time when they change ownership. So if a building is not sold, it is far less likely to
get torn down. So what makes a building more likely to get torn down when it is sold? One hypothesis would be that the
value of the building relative to the land should play an important factor. Let&rsquo;s test this hypothesis using the data.</p>

<p>We take the 2006 tax dataset as a baseline and check how many of the buildings have been torn down by 2016. Refer to the
Methodology and Data section at the botton for the messy details. We only
count buildings, so we count a strata lot with 100 units in the same building as one building. Then we use the 2016 dataset
to check how many of them are still around, identifying them by their tax coordinate and again asking they be marked as
being built no later than 2006.</p>

<p>These criteria capture well what we are looking for, but they are not perfect. As a predictive variable we use the</p>

<div style="padding:5px;border: 1px solid grey;border-radius:4px;width:80%;margin:0 auto;">
<h5 style="text-align:center;">Teardown Coefficient</h5>
The *teardown coefficient* is the percentage of the total assessed value that is attributed to the building. More formally
it&#8217;s the ratio of the building value by the sum of the building and land values.
</div>


<p>So we sort the properties by their <em>teardown coefficient</em> using the
2006 tax assessment data and we check how each group fares.</p>

<p>First up a graph of the distribution of buildigs in 2006 by their <em>teardown coefficient</em>.</p>

<div style="margin:10px 50px;padding:5px;border: 1px solid black;border-radius:5px;">
<div id="graph_buildings_by_teardown" style="height:200px;max-width:640px;" data-url="/data/buildings_by_teardown.json"></div>
<div class="legend no-margin">
  <p><i style="background:steelblue"></i> Number of Buildings by *teardown coefficient* <span style="float:right;margin-right:10px;" id="buildings_by_teardown_value"></span></p>
</div>
</div>


<p>Next up the number of buildings in each category that got torn down and rebuilt by 2016:</p>

<div style="margin:10px 50px;padding:5px;border: 1px solid black;border-radius:5px;">
<div id="graph_teardowns" style="height:200px;max-width:640px;" data-url="/data/teardowns.json"></div>
<div class="legend no-margin">
  <p><i style="background:steelblue"></i> Number of Torn Down Buildings by *teardown coefficient* <span style="float:right;margin-right:10px;" id="teardowns_value"></span></p>
</div>
</div>


<p>We see that our initial hypothesis seems to hold up quite well. The number of buildings that got torn down and rebuilt
decreases as the <em>teardown coefficient</em> increases. Remember that we defined the <em>teardown coefficient</em> to be the percentage
of the building value out of the total value of the property.</p>

<p>Refer to the methodology and data section for further information on how these numbers were extracted.</p>

<p>To explore this further let&rsquo;s graph the frequency with which a building in a given <em>teardown coefficeint</em> range gets torn down.
To keep things cleaner where we only plot up to a <em>teardown coefficient</em> of 50%:</p>

<div style="margin:10px 50px;padding:5px;border: 1px solid black;border-radius:5px;">
<div id="graph_teardown_probability" style="height:200px;max-width:640px;" data-url="/data/teardown_probability.json"></div>
<div class="legend no-margin">
  <p><i style="background:steelblue"></i> Probability of Building being torn down<span style="float:right;margin-right:10px;" id="teardown_probability_value"></span></p>
</div>
</div>


<p>We see that the <em>teardown coefficient</em> has high predictive value for a building to be torn down and
being rebuilt in the following 10 years. Buildings with a <em>teardown coefficient</em> below 5% have about an 18% chance, and the
probability declines exponentially down to zero at a <em>teardown coefficient</em> of about 50%.</p>

<p>If we were more serious about this
we would fit and exponential curve to the data and compute how well it fits the data, repeat the computation for
other time frames, run it on individual neighbourhoods and maybe also on <a href="https://data.surrey.ca">data from other municipalities</a>
to properly validate our model. We could also refine the model by refining our filters, see the methodology and data section for
more details.</p>

<p>And we could add other factors that likely effect the teardown probability, like building age, proximity to arterials and
others. Of course these are not independent factors, so this kind of analysis requires more time.</p>

<h3>Predicting Teardowns</h3>

<p>Now to the main part: Predicting teardowns. How many buildings will get torn down and rebuilt in the next 10 years? Let&rsquo;s
use what we have just learned to extrapolate.</p>

<p>First up the graph of the 2016 building stock by <em>teardown coefficient</em>:</p>

<div style="margin:10px 50px;padding:5px;border: 1px solid black;border-radius:5px;">
<div id="graph_buildings_by_teardown_2" style="height:200px;max-width:640px;" data-url="/data/buildings_by_teardown_2.json"></div>
<div class="legend no-margin">
  <p><i style="background:steelblue"></i> 2016 Building stock by *teardown coefficient* <span style="float:right;margin-right:10px;" id="buildings_by_teardown_2_value"></span></p>
</div>
</div>


<p>To estimate how many buildings will get torn down and rebuilt in each category we simply multiply each bin with the teardown probability
from the frequency graph above:</p>

<div style="margin:10px 50px;padding:5px;border: 1px solid black;border-radius:5px;">
<div id="graph_teardowns_2" style="height:200px;max-width:640px;" data-url="/data/teardowns_2.json"></div>
<div class="legend no-margin">
  <p><i style="background:steelblue"></i> Estimate of Buildings rebuilt by 2026 <span style="float:right;margin-right:10px;" id="teardowns_2_value"></span></p>
</div>
</div>


<p>Bottom line, we predict around 8,000 buildings to be torn down and rebuilt by 2026. That&rsquo;s significantly more than the
around 5,900 buildings that we identified as going through this process during the prior 10 years.</p>

<h3>Open Question</h3>

<p>There are lots of assumptions that went into this estimate. While we are confident in our analysis
that properties with low <em>teardown coefficient</em> are the ones most likely to be torn down, it is less clear if the number
of properties being torn down grows linearly as the properties with low <em>teardown coefficient</em> grow. In our case the number
of properties with <em>teardown coefficient</em> below 5% grew from 20492 (21% of the 2006 stock) to 32509 (33.5% of the 2016) stock,
which may be out of the range where our simplistic extrapolation holds. One could try to understand this by carefully
analyzing all available tax years, and not just the two extremes of the available spectrum.</p>

<h3>Mapping Teardowns</h3>

<p><a href="https://mountainmath.ca/map/special/17"><img  src="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/images/teardowns.png" style="width:50%;float:right"></a>Now that we
understand how to assign a teardown probability to buildings, let&rsquo;s map them! To keep things as simple as
possible let&rsquo;s focus in on the homes with a <em>teardown coefficient</em> below 5%. They make up the bulk in our prediction and
have the simple interpretation that a little more than 1 in 6 of these will get replaced by something else by 2026. So
<a href="https://mountainmath.ca/map/special/17">here is the interactive map</a> of just these 31301 buildings, where we have
filtered out some parks, marinas and rail lines. And this only accounts
for the 5,700 buildings predicted to be torn down with a <em>teardown coefficient</em> below 5% cutoff and neglects the roughly 2,000 more that
are predicted to be torn down that have a <em>teardown coefficient</em> above 5%.</p>

<h3>Methodology and Data</h3>

<p>Only for people who love getting their hands dirty or who want to reproduce or expand on the analysis.</p>

<p>First thing to note is that there is no way to detect &ldquo;teardowns&rdquo; in the dataset, the only way is to look at what has been
rebuilt and what has &lsquo;dropped off&rsquo;. To be more precise, there data fields to look at is the &ldquo;land coordinate&rdquo;, which links
a taxable property to a physical structure, and the &ldquo;year built&rdquo;. And both fields have problems.</p>

<p>The &ldquo;land coordinate&rdquo;
gets de-commissioned and re-assigned during certain re-develpments. And the city dataset provides no way to link the
old one to the new one. One way to do that is through the polygons that mark the property boundaries, that would allow
tracking of complex re-assemblies of land. But the city does not publish historic records of property polygons.</p>

<p>The &ldquo;year built&rdquo; also has lots of issues. Sometimes it is blank even though it records the value of the building as
greater than zero. Sometimes the &ldquo;year built&rdquo; will be set to a date later than the date of the dataset, for example the
2006 tax dataset has buildings with &ldquo;year built&rdquo; all they way up to 2013.</p>

<p>Then comes the issue of filtering. We decided to filter out parks, rail lines and marinas without structures on them. The
algorithm is somewhat simplistic, it&rsquo;s the same one that was used to filter properties for the maps. Additionally we
filter out properties from the heritage dataset. There is definitely
room for improvement here, but without a clear question of what exactly to measure
(only single family homes, or also condos or apartements, treat commercial separately, &hellip;)
it does not make much sense to invest energy into this. After all, this is just looking for a rough model.</p>

<p>So how do we detect rebuilds? We take the land coordinates from properties identified as park or heritage and sieve through
the 2006 tax data to retrieve all records that don&rsquo;t match these land coordinates and have a &ldquo;year built&rdquo; column set
as 2006 or earlier or don&rsquo;t have a &ldquo;year built&rdquo; set at all but change from zero to non-zero building value from 2006 to 2016.</p>

<p>Pretty messy. We mapped <a href="https://mountainmath.ca/map/special/15">about 6,900 buildings were built after 2006</a>,
but only traced 5,869 buildings in the 2006 tax dataset as
being torn down and rebuilt. That difference is largely explained by different selection criteria. The map only considers
properties with a &ldquo;year built&rdquo; field set, but for the analysis we also added properties that don&rsquo;t have that field set
but go from zero building value in 2006 to non-zero building value in 2016 which gets us to 7,784 &ldquo;rebuilds&rdquo;. On the other hand
in the analysis we don&rsquo;t consder the roughly 140 heritage buildings that would pass our filter of being built after 2006, and
the 2016 tax dataset has 2,422 more buildings than the 2006 dataset, some of which can be seen
<a href="https://mountainmath.ca/map/special/13">on this map</a> and are due to subdivisions being split off of the original
property.</p>

<p>Anyway, if you want to get your hand dirty on this shoot me a message and I will hook you up with my scripts.</p>

<script>


function bar_graph(div,shiftAxis,domainFormatter,rangeFormatter,domainLabelFormatter){
    if (!domainFormatter) domainFormatter=d3.format("d")
    if (!rangeFormatter)
     rangeFormatter = function (y) {
        return y;
     };
     if (!domainLabelFormatter) domainLabelFormatter=domainFormatter;

var margin = {top: 20, right: 20, bottom: 40, left: 70},
    width = parseInt(div.style("width")) - margin.left - margin.right,
    height = parseInt(div.style("height")) - margin.top - margin.bottom;

var x = d3.scale.ordinal()
    .rangeRoundBands([0, width], .1);

var y = d3.scale.linear()
    .range([height, 0]);


var xAxis = d3.svg.axis()
    .scale(x)
    .tickFormat(domainFormatter)
    .orient("bottom");


var yAxis = d3.svg.axis()
    .scale(y)
    .orient("left")
    .tickFormat(rangeFormatter)
    .ticks(5, rangeFormatter);

var svg = div.append("svg")
    .attr("width", width + margin.left + margin.right)
    .attr("height", height + margin.top + margin.bottom)
  .append("g")
    .attr("transform", "translate(" + margin.left + "," + margin.top + ")");

var data_url=div[0][0].dataset.url;

d3.json(data_url, function(error, json) {
  if (error) throw error;
  var graphData=json[0];
  var data=graphData.data;
  x.domain(data.map(function(d) { return d.date }));
  y.domain([0, d3.max(data, function(d) { return d.count; })]);
  
  var domainTickValues=[];
  var skip=Math.round(40/x.rangeBand());
  if (skip<=0) skip=1;
  for (var i=0;i<x.domain().length;i++) {
    if (i % skip==0) domainTickValues.push(x.domain()[i]);
  }
  if (x.domain().length % 5 !=0) domainTickValues.push(x.domain()[x.domain().length-1]);
  xAxis.tickValues(domainTickValues);

  var xShift=shiftAxis ?  x.rangeBand()/2.0 * 1.1 : 0;
  
  svg.append("g")
      .attr("class", "x axis")
      .attr("transform", "translate(" + xShift + "," + height + ")")
      .call(xAxis);

  svg.append("g")
      .attr("class", "y axis")
      .call(yAxis);
//    .append("text")
//      .attr("transform", "rotate(-90)")
//      .attr("y", 6)
//      .attr("dy", ".71em")
//      .style("text-anchor", "end")
//      .text("Probability");

  svg.selectAll(".bar")
      .data(data)
    .enter().append("rect")
      .attr("class", graphData.class + " bar")
      .attr("fill", graphData.color)
      .attr("x", function(d) { return x(d.date); })
      .attr("width", x.rangeBand())
      .attr("y", function(d) { return y(d.count); })
      .attr("height", function(d) { return height - y(d.count); })
      .on('mouseover',function(d){
         d3.select('#'+this.classList[0]+'_value').text(domainLabelFormatter(d.date) + ': ' + rangeFormatter(d.count)) 
      }).on('click',function(d){
       d3.select('#'+this.classList[0]+'_value').text(domainLabelFormatter(d.date) + ': ' + rangeFormatter(d.count)) 
      }).on('touch',function(d){
         d3.select('#'+this.classList[0]+'_value').text(domainLabelFormatter(d.date) + ': ' + rangeFormatter(d.count)) 
      }).on('mouseout',function(){d3.select('#'+this.classList[0]+'_value').text('')});

      
});

}

var percentageFormatter=d3.format(".1%");
var binFormatter=function(d){return percentageFormatter(d-0.025) + ' - ' + percentageFormatter(d);}
//ready_for_graph(d3.select("#graph"));
bar_graph(d3.select("#graph_age"),false);
//ready_for_graph(d3.select("#graph_buildings_by_teardown"),percentageFormatter);
//ready_for_graph(d3.select("#graph_teardowns"),percentageFormatter);
bar_graph(d3.select("#graph_buildings_by_teardown"),true,percentageFormatter,null,binFormatter);
bar_graph(d3.select("#graph_teardowns"),true,percentageFormatter,null,binFormatter);
bar_graph(d3.select("#graph_teardown_probability"),true,percentageFormatter,percentageFormatter,binFormatter);
bar_graph(d3.select("#graph_buildings_by_teardown_2"),true,percentageFormatter,null,binFormatter);
bar_graph(d3.select("#graph_teardowns_2"),true,percentageFormatter,null,binFormatter);
</script>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Updated Vancouver Assessment Data]]></title>
    <link href="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2016/01/17/updated-vancouver-assessment-data/"/>
    <updated>2016-01-17T11:34:09-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2016/01/17/updated-vancouver-assessment-data</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="https://mountainmath.ca/map/assessment?layer=4"><img  src="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/images/relative_land.jpg" style="width:50%;float:right"></a>
The friendly folks at
<a href="http://vancouver.ca/your-government/open-data-catalogue.aspx">Vancouver Open Data</a> just
<a href="https://twitter.com/VanOpenData/status/688060388190097408">updated their property assessment data</a> with the fresh 2016
property tax assessments. Time to run the script to update the <a href="https://mountainmath.ca/map/assessment">Vancouver Assessment Map</a>
with the new data. And for good measure I pasted over some of the thematic map engine from <a href="https://censusmapper.ca">CensusMapper</a>
to improve the mapping performance.</p>

<h4>Maps</h4>

<!-- more -->


<p><img  src="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/images/map_menu.png" style="width:25%;margin-left:5px;float:right">The <a href="https://mountainmath.ca/map/assessment">interactive assessment map</a> offers several views. In the panel on the top
right we can select how to view the data. It offers standard thematic maps for value change, total value, building value
and building age and zoning. And there are some options that warrant more explanation:</p>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://mountainmath.ca/map/assessment?layer=5"><em>Relative Land Value</em>:</a> The colours on the map show each property by the
land value per m&sup2;. We can immediately spot the east-west land gradient, as well as how zoning affects land value.
When zooming in we also see the effect of lot size on land value.</li>
<li><a href="https://mountainmath.ca/map/assessment?layer=10"><em>Tax Density</em>:</a> This map looks at the tax dollars collected
by the city by area. It tells us the relative rate at what each property is contributing to city services. We can again
observe the impact of exclusionary zoning.</li>
<li><a href="https://mountainmath.ca/map/assessment?layer=4"><em>Relative Value of Building</em>:</a>
<a href="https://mountainmath.ca/map/assessment?layer=4"><img  src="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/images/teardown.jpg" style="width:50%;float:right"></a>
This map simply divides the building value
by the total property value. There are many ways to interpret this map, my favourite is to use this as a &ldquo;Teardown Predictor&rdquo;.
Essentially, as the percentage of the building value approaches zero the probability that it will get torn down in the
near future increases. Imagine someone spending $1.5m to buy a property with a house valued at $37k. Many people don&rsquo;t
mind living in a house worth $37k, but someone who is spending $1.5m would probably prefer to buy a different property
with a higher quality house. Or spend more money to upgrade the house. How will it be upgraded? Renovating is in most
cases economically unsound, most people will choose to tear down and rebuild. In fact, the <em>teardown threshold</em> is
likely higher than the 2.5% in the example given. The percentage of properties in Vancouver where the building value is
less than 2.5% of the total value has slightly decreaed in the last year from 17.9% to 17.8%, but the percentage of properties
with building value less than 5% of the total value has increased from 32% to 33.5% during the last year.</li>
</ul>


<h4>The Data</h4>

<p>The data originates with BC Assessment, which estimates land and building values of each property based on recent sales
of comparable properties. The assessment was done in summer 2015 and is based on sales before that, so at this point in
time the data lags the market by about one year. Values for individual properties may well be off, depending how well
renovations and improvements were reported and how well the BC Assessment estimates work for the given property. On
average they should reflect the market about half a year to one year ago.</p>

<p>Sadly, BC Assessment does not give out their data with a license that would allow mapping it the way I do, so we have
to rely on municipalities to release it through their open data portals. The format of the data from each municipality is
different, so lazy me is only importing data from City of Vancouver, although some other nearby municipalities are also releasing
there data.</p>

<p>The motivation behind the map was to understand the building stock. Some effort was made to filter out parks, but the
algorithm is far from perfect and will often includes parks that host building
structures, as well as marinas with structures on them.</p>

<p>The new city dataset does not include the 2016 tax levy, so we still only show the 2015 tax levies until CoV updated their dataset.</p>

<h4>History</h4>

<p>Here is a quick history of the overall land and building values aggregated for Vancouver between 2006 and 2016.</p>

<div style="margin:10px 50px;padding:5px;border: 1px solid black;border-radius:5px;">
<div id="graph" style="height:200px;max-width:640px;" data-lines="/data/vancouver_stats.json"></div>
<div class="legend no-margin">
  <p><i style="background:blue"></i> Land Value <span style="float:right;margin-right:10px;" id="land_value"></span></p>
  <p><i style="background:green"></i> Building Value <span style="float:right;margin-right:10px;" id="building_value"></span></p>
</div>
</div>


<p>When looking at all properties in the city, the increase in land
value year over year was 21.4% ($45.2bn), while overall building values increased by 7.3% ($5bn). Hover, click or touch
the points in the graph to get the values for the corresponding year.</p>

<h4>Neighbourhoods</h4>

<p>Lastly a quick overview over the neighbourhoods. Land and building values have not increased evenly throughout in the year.
I aggregated all tax data by neighbourhood and split it into land value and building value increases.
These numbers should be used as guidance only, they mix lots of different types of properties and include parks.</p>

<p>Here is the breakdown by neighbourhood:</p>

<ul>
<li>Renfrew-Collingwood: Land: 30.6% ($1.2bn), Building: 5.8% ($46.0m)</li>
<li>Sunset: Land: 26.6% ($1.6bn), Building: 5.9% ($74.2m)</li>
<li>Oakridge: Land: 17.6% ($1.2bn), Building: 12.6% ($207.4m)</li>
<li>Downtown: Land: 16.9% ($0.8bn), Building: 3.2% ($91.2m)</li>
<li>Kerrisdale: Land: 18.7% ($1.3bn), Building: 3.3% ($54.1m)</li>
<li>Victoria-Fraserview: Land: 28.0% ($1.5bn), Building: 5.6% ($65.2m)</li>
<li>Grandview-Woodland: Land: 24.9% ($1.7bn), Building: 0.7% ($17.4m)</li>
<li>West End: Land: 22.6% ($2.5bn), Building: 3.5% ($188.4m)</li>
<li>Hastings-Sunrise: Land: 25.1% ($1.1bn), Building: 4.9% ($63.8m)</li>
<li>Killarney: Land: 17.8% ($0.3bn), Building: 14.1% ($241.6m)</li>
<li>Marpole: Land: 17.8% ($0.3bn), Building: 14.1% ($241.6m)</li>
<li>Kitsilano: Land: 21.6% ($3.3bn), Building: 4.3% ($134.5m)</li>
<li>Shaughnessy: Land: 18.6% ($1.7bn), Building: 7.4% ($117.7m)</li>
<li>West Point Grey: Land: 20.2% ($2.3bn), Building: 5.2% ($88.3m)</li>
<li>Fairview: Land: 19.4% ($2.0bn), Building: -1.0% (-$52.4m)</li>
<li>Downtown Eastside: Land: 21.9% ($2.6bn), Building: 4.9% ($194.9m)</li>
<li>Kensington-Cedar Cottage: Land: 24.9% ($1.7bn), Building: 0.7% ($17.4m)</li>
<li>Riley Park: Land: 26.4% ($1.0bn), Building: 4.0% ($40.2m)</li>
<li>Mount Pleasant: Land: 21.9% ($2.6bn), Building: 4.9% ($194.9m)</li>
<li>South Cambie: Land: 20.9% ($1.5bn), Building: 21.4% ($268.1m)</li>
<li>Strathcona: Land: 21.9% ($2.6bn), Building: 4.9% ($194.9m)</li>
<li>Dunbar Southlands: Land: 21.8% ($1.0bn), Building: 11.2% ($126.6m)</li>
<li>Arbutus Ridge: Land: 21.4% ($1.6bn), Building: 1.1% ($17.3m)</li>
</ul>


<p>It becomes immediately clear that the increase in property values is mostly driven by land, note that total value increases
for land and buildings are reported in billions and millions, respectively. The building stock does not
have time to catch up, with the exception of South Cambie. Fairview stands out with declining overall building values.</p>

<script>
var ready_for_graph = function() {
    var d3lines=[];
    var padding = {top: 20, right: 20, bottom: 30, left: 90};
    var prevChartWidth = 0, prevChartHeight = 0;
    var updateTransistionMS = 750; // milliseconds
    var sourceData, lineData, xScale, yScale, line;

    var symbol;
    var prefix;
    var numberFormatter = function (y) {
        return '$' + Math.round(prefix.scale(y*10))/10.0 + symbol;
    };

    var graphs=d3.select("#graph");
    var div=graphs[0][0];
    if (div==null|| div.childElementCount!=0) {return;}
    var data_url=div.dataset.url;

    // create svg and g to contain the chart contents
    var baseSvg = graphs.append("svg");
    var chartSvg=baseSvg
        .append("g")
        .attr("class", "chartContainer")
        .attr("transform", "translate(" + padding.left + "," + padding.top + ")");

    // create the x axis container
    chartSvg.append("g")
        .attr("class", "x axis");

    // create the y axis container
    chartSvg.append("g")
        .attr("class", "y axis");
    var line;
    var largest=null;
    var lineData;
    if (div.dataset.lines) {
        d3.json(div.dataset.lines,function(error,json){
        lineData=json;
        var domain=[null,null];
        var range=[null,null];
        for (var i=0;i<lineData.length;i++){
            lineData[i].data.forEach(function(d) {
                d.date = +d.date;
                d.count = +d.count;
                if (domain[0]==null || domain[0]> d.date) domain[0]= d.date;
                if (domain[1]==null || domain[1]< d.date) domain[1]= d.date;
                if (range[0]==null || range[0]> d.count) range[0]= d.count;
                if (range[1]==null || range[1]< d.count) range[1]= d.count;
            });
        }
        xScale=d3.scale.linear().domain(domain);
        var toAdd=(range[1]-range[0])/10;
        range[0]-=toAdd;
        range[1]+=toAdd;
        yScale=d3.scale.linear()
            .domain(range);

        line = d3.svg.line()
            .x(function(d) { return xScale(d.date); })
            .y(function(d) { return yScale(d.count); })
            .interpolate("linear");

        xAxis = d3.svg.axis()
            .scale(xScale)
            .orient("bottom")
            .tickFormat(d3.format("d"))
            .tickValues(domain);

        yAxis = d3.svg.axis()
            .scale(yScale)
            .orient("left")
            .tickFormat(numberFormatter)
            .ticks(5);

        prefix = d3.formatPrefix(range[1]);
        if (prefix.symbol=='K') {
            symbol='k'
        } else if (prefix.symbol=='M') {
                symbol='m'
        } else if (prefix.symbol=='G') {
            symbol='bn'
        } else if (prefix.symbol=='T') {
            symbol='tn'
        }
        updateChart(true);
        });

    }


    function updateChart(init)
    {
        // get the height and width subtracting the padding
//    var innerHeight = window.innerHeight - 20;
        var innerWidth = window.innerWidth - 20;
        var divWidth=$(div).width();
        if (divWidth==0) divWidth=$(div.parentElement.parentElement).width();
        var maxWidth=parseInt($(div).css('max-width'));
        if (divWidth==0) divWidth=innerWidth*0.8;
        if (divWidth>maxWidth) divWidth=maxWidth;
        var chartWidth = divWidth-padding.left-padding.right;//960 - margin.left - margin.right,
        var chartHeight = $(div).height()-padding.top-padding.bottom;//500 - margin.top - margin.bottom;


        // only update if chart size has changed
        if ((prevChartWidth != chartWidth) ||
            (prevChartHeight != chartHeight)) {
            prevChartWidth = chartWidth;
            prevChartHeight = chartHeight;

            //set the width and height of the SVG element
            chartSvg.attr("width", chartWidth + padding.left + padding.right)
                .attr("height", chartHeight + padding.top + padding.bottom);
            baseSvg.attr("width", chartWidth + padding.left + padding.right)
                .attr("height", chartHeight + padding.top + padding.bottom);

            // ranges are based on the width and height available so reset
            xScale.range([0, chartWidth]);
            yScale.range([chartHeight, 0]);

            if (init) {
                // if first run then just display axis with no transition
                chartSvg.select(".x")
                    .style({ 'stroke': 'grey', 'fill': 'none', 'stroke-width': '1px'})
                    .attr("transform", "translate(0," + chartHeight + ")")
                    .call(xAxis);

                chartSvg.select(".y")
                    .style({ 'stroke': 'grey', 'fill': 'none', 'stroke-width': '1px'})
                    .call(yAxis);
            }
            else {
                // for subsequent updates use a transistion to animate the axis to the new position
                var t = chartSvg.transition().duration(updateTransistionMS);

                t.select(".x")
                    .attr("transform", "translate(0," + chartHeight + ")")
                    .call(xAxis);

                t.select(".y")
                    .call(yAxis);
            }

            for (var i = 0; i < lineData.length; i++) {
                var sourceData=lineData[i].data;
                var color=lineData[i].color;
                var label=lineData[i].label;
                var className=lineData[i].class;

                // bind up the data to the line
                var lines = chartSvg.selectAll("path.line."+className)
                    .data([lineData[i].data]); // needs to be an array (size of 1 for our data) of arrays

                // transistion to new position if already exists
                lines.transition()
                    .duration(updateTransistionMS)
                    .attr("d", line);

                // add line if not already existing
                lines.enter().append("path")
                    .attr("class", "line")
                    .attr("stroke", color)
                    .attr("stroke-width", 2)
                    .attr('fill','none')
                    .attr("d", line);

                // bind up the data to an array of circles
                var circle = chartSvg.selectAll("circle."+className)
                    .data(sourceData);

                // if already existing then transistion each circle to its new position
                circle.transition()
                    .duration(updateTransistionMS)
                    .attr("cx", function (d) {
                        return xScale(d.date);
                    })
                    .attr("cy", function (d) {
                        return yScale(d.count);
                    });

                // if new circle then just display
                circle.enter().append("circle")
                    .attr("cx", function (d) {
                        return xScale(d.date);
                    })
                    .attr("cy", function (d) {
                        return yScale(d.count);
                    })
                    .attr("r", 4)
                    .attr('fill', 'transparent')
                    .style("stroke", color)
                    .style("stroke-width", 8)
                    .attr("class", className)
                    .on('mouseover',function(d){
                       d3.select('#'+this.classList[0]+'_value').text(d.date + ': ' + numberFormatter(d.count)) 
                    }).on('click',function(d){
                     d3.select('#'+this.classList[0]+'_value').text(d.date + ': ' + numberFormatter(d.count)) 
                    }).on('touch',function(d){
                       d3.select('#'+this.classList[0]+'_value').text(d.date + ': ' + numberFormatter(d.count)) 
                    }).on('mouseout',function(){d3.select('#'+this.classList[0]+'_value').text('')});

            }
        }
    }

    // look for resize but use timer to only call the update script when a resize stops
    var resizeTimer;
    window.onresize = function(event) {
        clearTimeout(resizeTimer);
        resizeTimer = setTimeout(function()
        {
            updateChart(false);
        }, 100);
    }


};
ready_for_graph();
</script>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Canvas vs SVG]]></title>
    <link href="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2015/12/27/canvas-vs-svg/"/>
    <updated>2015-12-27T15:53:02-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2015/12/27/canvas-vs-svg</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h4>CensusMapper Behind the Scenes</h4>

<p>The idea behind <a href="https://censusmapper.ca">CensusMapper</a> is that it takes away all the technical barriers to dealing with census data. So how does
CensusMapper work behind the scenes?</p>

<h4>CensusMapper Data Workflow</h4>

<!-- more -->


<p>The general setup is quite simple. We use the lean javascript open mapping platform <a href="http://leafletjs.com">leaflet</a>
as the base for mapping information. Leaflet handles the logic of dealing with zoom and pan and keeping track of the
geographic boundaries that should be mapped. That information gets then passed on to the CensusMapper servers.</p>

<p>CensusMapper will then send the appropriate census geographic polygons to the browser for leaflet to display. Once the
geographic data is available for mapping, some custom code checks what kind of information the user wants to display and
requests the census data required to make the map. The census information is then assembled on the server, sent down
and attached to the polygons and drawn
on the browser window within leaflet. This two-tier process allows the highly dynamic mapping in CensusMapper where the
data-heavy geographic polygons are kept separately thus can be cached and re-used.</p>

<h4>Drawing Census Data</h4>

<p>There are a number of ways how we can display census data in the browser. At CensusMapper we have played with three
different technologies to map data that vary in performance and browser support. They all have in common that they
won&rsquo;t run on Internet Explorer 8 or earlier, but we have just about reached the point in time where it is acceptable to
ignore IE8- in products meant for the &ldquo;general internet audience&rdquo;.</p>

<h5>SVG</h5>

<p><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Scalable_Vector_Graphics">SVG</a> is what our maps have been using so far. SVGs are fairly high level, which means it&rsquo;s very little work
to implement and map information. One simply passes a polygon to the browser, tells it how to color it, and the browser
takes care of the rest. SVG elements can easily be styled via CSS, so there is essentially no work involved to deal with
highlight on hover, scaling for retina displays, patterns for census data quality flags, etc. We use
<a href="https://github.com/mbostock/d3">d3.js</a> to attach the geographic and census data right to the SVG elements for easy
manipulation.</p>

<p>While mapping data this way is very easy, for CensusMapper there are two problems.</p>

<ol>
<li>We are restricted in how we can display information by the capabilities of SVG.</li>
<li>SVG rendering is done by the browser, and not all browsers are equal. Most importantly, SVG rendering in Internet
Explorer is excruciatingly slow. So slow, that CensusMapper becomes essentially useless within Internet Explorer. We
felt compelled to add a warning messeage that displayed when people opened CensusMapper with Internet Explorer. And
when you do that, that&rsquo;s a sure sign that your app has a serious problem.
<img src="/images/chrome.png" alt="Browser Warning" />
So how to get around those issues? Enter Canvas.</li>
</ol>


<h5>Canvas</h5>

<p><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Canvas_element">Canvas</a> offers a way to draw images in a browser. Unlike SVG, the drawing has to be done &ldquo;by hand&rdquo;. And the result is just
an image, with no clear way to tell where it came from. There is no way to attach any information to individual
structures drawn on a canvas. All the logic for highlight on hover, figuring out what data is associated with the mouse
position, dealing with retina displays, etc. needs to be added by hand.</p>

<p>On the upside, a good canvas implementation is a lot faster than SVG. And it opens the door to changes in how the data
is handled that bring additional performance improvements. In particular, we can now chop up census polygons and render
the pieces separately, greatly cutting down on the size of the downloaded data, as well as the complexity of the
polygons that get rendered. And the performance improvements are noticeable across all browsers and platforms.</p>

<p>At the end of the day it is actually not that much work and we flipped the switch on this just before the Christmas
break. CensusMapper is now running using canvas instead SVG for
the main maps. We
kept the look and feel the same, so unless you dig into the code you won&rsquo;t notice the difference.
Some parts of CensusMapper still utilized SVGs, like the d3-based
<a href="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2015/10/24/census-drilldown/">Census Wheel</a>.</p>

<h5>WebGL</h5>

<p><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/WebGL">WebGL</a> also draws on a canvas element, but the work is offloaded onto the GPU (graphics processor) giving enormous
speed improvements. Regular canvas rendering is fast enough for our purposes, but with WebGL we can do more complex
renderings that previously we could not even dream of: <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/OpenGL_Shading_Language">Shaders</a>
and Interactive 3D data maps. We had previously
<a href="https://mountainmath.ca/census3">toyed with 3D data visualization</a> to explore Vancouver&rsquo;s household density in 3D using Three.js,
but did not pursue this further because of the complexities of writing code for navigating a Canada-wide map. Then we came
across the super-customizable 3D open mapping platform built by <a href="https://mapzen.com/projects/tangram/">Mapzen</a>, and that
suddenly made it extremely easy to do interactive 3D data mapping live in the browser. A quick test
<a href="https://mountainmath.ca/vancouver_lidar/map">using Vancouver&rsquo;s open LIDAR generated building height data</a> showed how easy Mapzen&rsquo;s
tangram engine is to use.</p>

<p>After digging deeper into tangram, and with help from the friendly people at Mapzen, we figured out a way to fit
CensusMapper&rsquo;s two-stage data workflow into tangram&rsquo;s mapping engine. The result are real-time 3D maps where height
and color of each geographic area can be independently (and dynamically) controlled. Here is an example where mouseover
trigged the area west of Coal Harbor to &lsquo;pop up&rsquo;.
<img src="/images/webGL.jpg" alt="webGL" /></p>

<p>At the same time we gain the ability to easily pull in all kinds of other data and map it. On our canvas or svg maps we
added regular image tiles, either a road and label&rsquo;s overlay or a base map (which then requires opacity to be added to
the census data that is mapped on top of that) as orientation aid. Short of baking our own image tiles we have very
little control over the look and feel of this. With Mapzen&rsquo;s tangram we can very easily pick and style individual
geographic objects from Mapzen&rsquo;s OSM vector tile server, resulting in crisp and clear maps. In the above example we
decide dynamically what level of roads to render, how to style them, what labels to display and we also added bodies of
water, where we filter by size depending on the zoom level.</p>

<p>At this stage it is still an ongoing project to get this production-ready. One obvious obstacle is that WebGL browser
support is still lagging. And on top of that it also requires updated graphics card drivers, which is a big problem on
windows machines that are already a couple of years old. So for now we still need to have a plain canvas or svg fallback.</p>

<p>And then there are the details that need to get worked out. 3D maps sounds great, but it will take us some time to figure
out how to best utilize this in thematic maps. But even without utilizing 3D capabilities, the dynamic shaders and increased
rendering performance are already pushing the boundary of what&rsquo;s possible in web maps.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Census Drilldown]]></title>
    <link href="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2015/10/24/census-drilldown/"/>
    <updated>2015-10-24T20:45:16-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2015/10/24/census-drilldown</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h4>Next steps in CensusMapper</h4>

<p>The <a href="http://censusmapper.ca">Census Mapper Project</a> is moving along slowly, public beta unearthed some bugs and we gathered
feedback (thanks to everyone reporting back!). There are still a couple of steps that need to be taken care of before
we can unleash the full map making power to all users. We feel that the complexity of census data requires more guidance
than the current map making system is providing. Anyone who does not mind getting there hands dirty and having to look
up census variable definitions by themselves when making maps is welcome to contact us and we will hook you up with a
beta mapmaking account.</p>

<p>In the meantime we added one important feature to the CensusMapper.</p>

<h5>Content Drilldown</h5>

<p>CensusMapper is a great way to explore single census variables (or a single function built out of census variables)
across many geographic regions and aggregation levels. But sometimes we would like to do the opposite: Drill down into
a specific census region and explore other census variables. We have now added an easy way to do this. To access it
simply select the &ldquo;more&rdquo; button in the basic popup when you select a census region. This brings up the <em>census wheel</em>,
which is our way to navigate through census data.
<img src="/images/wheel.png" alt="Census Wheel" /></p>

<p>Try it out right away on <a href="http://censusmapper.ca">CensusMapper</a> or read on for details on how this works.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>There are almost 4,000 census variables available, right now we do not offer to split up by gender, which reduces the
available variables to 1,429. To further simplify things we throw out all variables with zero values for the give
geographic area, still leaving a
sizeable number of variables to browse through.
<img src="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/images/mother_tounge.png" alt="Mother Tounge" style="max-width:400px;margin-right:15px;margin-top:10px;" align="left"/>
Each arc in the census wheel represents a variable, or a category of
variables. Selecting an arc will zoom into that arc and turn it into the &ldquo;center&rdquo; of the wheel, collapsing all other
components. That&rsquo;s the content <em>drilldown</em> process. Once it makes sense to display data as proportions, we switch to the
<em>proportional view</em> which shows the data as hierarchical pie chart.</p>

<p>This gives a visual representation of the proportions of each of the variables. Hovering (or touching) an arc will
display more detailed information, selecting one will drill down further. To reverse that process either select the
center or us the <em>content breadcrumbs</em> at the top that were created during the drilldown process.</p>

<h5>Data Problems</h5>

<p>Census data is messy. Now that all census data for each region is generally accessible in CensusMapper we need to
explain some of the inherent data problems.</p>

<h6>Rounding</h6>

<p>Census Canada will <a href="http://www12.statcan.gc.ca/census-recensement/2011/dp-pd/prof/help-aide/N2.cfm?Lang=E">round</a>
(almost) all data to preserve anonymity and don&rsquo;t create false impressions of accuracy that
the data does not achieve. Data is generally reported in increments of 5, rounding includes randomness to preserve
anonymity. The value of the measured value
is <a href="https://www12.statcan.gc.ca/census-recensement/2011/ref/DQ-QD/conf-eng.cfm">within 4</a> of the reported one. And
remember that even the measured variable is only an estimate of the actual value of the variable.
Rounding may lead to situations where, for example, the sum of all people listed
by age bracket will not add up to the total number of people. Generally, this difference will be small and we ignore it
in our visualization.</p>

<h6>Omitted Data</h6>

<p>Census Canada will at times not report data. This could be due to very low return rates or other problems that make data
so unreliable that it is better not reported at all. Or it could be that releasing the information could compromize
the anonymity of the census data for some people in that area. The latter can take
the form of Census Canada not reporting any data for the region, or Census Canada zeroing out specific variables that
&ldquo;are too low to be reported&rdquo;.
<img src="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/images/unaccounted.png" alt="Unaccounted" style="max-width:400px;margin-left:15px;margin-top:10px;" align="right"/>
We have not been able to find clear guidelines how the &ldquo;zeroing&rdquo; works, but often this will leave
detectable traces in the data. Looking at the example in the image, looking at &ldquo;Mode of Transport&rdquo; to work only
&ldquo;Driving&rdquo; has non-zero values, the
other options &ldquo;Passenger&rdquo;, &ldquo;Transit&rdquo;, &ldquo;Bike&rdquo;, &ldquo;Walk&rdquo; and &ldquo;Other&rdquo; are all zero. There were 160 people getting to work,
115 are listed as &ldquo;Driver&rdquo;, leaving 45 unaccounted for. This is outside of the range that could be explained by the
rounding of variables. We alert the user by adding in
a grey area for the missing 45. This also ensures that the visual representation remains accurate.</p>

<h6>Multiple Responses</h6>

<p>Some census questions allow for multiple responses. For exaple &ldquo;Language Spoken Most Often At Home&rdquo;. In this particular
case the census variable breaks out single responses and multiple responses and is very transparent to the user. In
other cases, for example &ldquo;Ethnicity&rdquo;, single and multiple responses are not reported separately but responses are all
added up. This leads to the sum of lower level variables being higher than the base variable. We alert the user to this
by overlaying small white dots on the base variable.
<img src="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/images/multiple_responses.png" alt="Multiple Responses" style="max-width:400px;margin-right:15px;margin-top:10px;" align="left"/>
In this particular case the total for for &ldquo;Ethnic Origin&rdquo; was 12,140 people. But there were 1,430 more responses at the
next level, so up to 1,430 people had given multiple responses to this question listing more than one of the aggregate
(mostly continent level) origins, some possibly listing more than two. The same patter repeats at different ethnic
origin aggregation
levels, for example 2,565 people claimed at least one of the &ldquo;British Island origins&rdquo;, but many listed more than one
resulting in the sum of the individual regions with the British Islands exceeding the British Island count by 1,445.
Again, we alert the user by overlaying dots over the &ldquo;British Island origins&rdquo; arc. Hovering over the arg will display
the exact numbers of the &ldquo;overcounting&rdquo; due to multiple responses.</p>

<p>In these cases where mulitple repsonses are not broken out the dots will aler the user that the proportional
representation in the hierarchical pie chart does not represent proportions out of a total given by the value of the
variable at the centre (or lower level), but as a proportion of all responses which exceeds the value of the
lower level variable.</p>

<h6>Basic Census</h6>

<p>The Basic Census is generally speaking quite reliable, every single person is required to fill it
out and return rates are generally above 95%. Serious problems will only occur if response rates are very low. We alert
the user by shading geographic regions is this has been the case.</p>

<h6>NHS</h6>

<p>The National Household Survey is quite different in nature, it was only
sent out to a smaller portion (~30%) of society and return rates were much lower (~69%). Even with 100% return rates
there are likely to be geographic regions where the results severely misrepresent reality in that region due to sampling
bias. For each region that bias is small, but the probability for bias grows as the number of people in the geographic
region declines. So this is mostly a problem for Dissemination Areas. But even there, the probability of severe sampling
bias in each region is small, but there are many regions and the probability that some of these regions suffer from
sever sampling bias is quite large.</p>

<p>On top of this basic statistical sampling bias, we also have self selection bias due to some deomgraphics being more
likely to return the survey than others. This bias is a product of the decision of scrapping the madatory
&lsquo;long form census&rsquo; and replacing it with the voluntary NHS. The return rates can give some indication of the
likelyhood of self-selection
bias, we shade regions with a non-return rate lower than 50%, the cutoff Census Canada set for reliability of the NHS.
It is especially problematic when trying to detect change in variables (for example poverty) from one census to another
as the differences in the variable over time are often small and similar in magnitude to possible self-selection bias.</p>

<p>The 50% cutoff we highlight in CensusMapper is just a guideline, the exact return rates are displayed on hover or when
selecting regions and should always to be taken into
account when interpreting results,
especially at the Dissemination Area level.</p>

<p>If all this information did not turn you off, head over to <a href="http://censusmapper.ca">CensusMapper</a> and drill down into
some geographic areas.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Census Mapper]]></title>
    <link href="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2015/09/28/census-mapper/"/>
    <updated>2015-09-28T09:23:41-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2015/09/28/census-mapper</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h5>We are excited to announce CensusMapper public beta launch!</h5>

<p>The project on mapping census data for Canada is entering the next stage. We are now mapping 3875 different
variables from the 2011 census, or any combination of them, across 67215 geographic regions covering all of Canada.</p>

<p>We are opening up the <a href="http://censusmapper.ca">Census Mapper</a> to a limited public beta. Limited means that anyone
can view maps created in CensusMapper, but we are only opening up the map creation tools to selected beta users.</p>

<p>Be aware that the web app makes use of modern web technology and renders large amount of data. It will only work on
modern browsers, best viewed in Chrome or Safari. Firefox works ok, Internet Explorer might grind to a halt and should be avoided.</p>

<p><a href="http://censusmapper.ca"><img src="/images/map-tools.jpg" alt="CenusMap Mapmaker" /></a></p>

<p>We are a little restrictive on creating maps right now for the simple reason that census data is somewhat tricky to
understand and at this point we don&rsquo;t have a comprehensive guide explaining all the variables and warning against many
of the pitfalls. We are planning to slowly integrate this and open up the map creation tools to the general public.</p>

<h3>Why CensusMapper?</h3>

<!-- more -->


<p>Census Canada data is extremely rich and useful in many cirumstances, but it is not being widely used. There are many
reasons for this, the somewhat unmanageable amount of data being one of them, the difficulty of accessing and standardizing
the in principle freely available datasets is another.</p>

<p>Census data is inherently geographic in nature, working with the data without proper visualization tools can be challenging
too. And even for people that have good access to the data and that are well-versed in mapping geographic data, it can
still take quite a bit of time to generate maps visualizing the data. CensusMapper greatly speeds up this process by
allowing straightforward mapping of any function derived from census variables through all geographic aggregation levels
Canada wide.</p>

<h3>Storytelling</h3>

<p>Census mapper does more than just mapping census data. It is designed as a storytelling tool. Few maps are so crisp and
clear that they are self-explanatory. A map of population density might fall into that category. But most census variables
are sufficiently complex that maps derived from them warrant narration. We think of CensusMapper as a storytelling tool
that allows &lsquo;readers&rsquo; of the map to interact with it, zoom in, zoom out, pan around, and jump to other maps linked in the
story provided by the mapmaker.</p>

<h3>Directions</h3>

<p>There are many ways to expand on this. On the map creation side we can offer more diverse coloring tools, allowing user
input and user defined map locations to be used in the mapping function, add data from previous census. We could allow
limited upload of user data to be integrated with census data, statistical and spacial analysis tools, custom mapping projects.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
