<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: vancouver | Mountain Doodles]]></title>
  <link href="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/categories/vancouver/feed.atom" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/"/>
  <updated>2016-06-17T19:19:08-07:00</updated>
  <id>http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[MountainMath]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[SDH Zoning and Land Use]]></title>
    <link href="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2016/06/17/sdh-zoning-and-land-use/"/>
    <updated>2016-06-17T09:34:37-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2016/06/17/sdh-zoning-and-land-use</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Recently the question around the amount of space taken up (exclusively) by single detached houses has show up on my
Twitter feed citing that
SFH take up <a href="https://twitter.com/WayneFougere/status/743211599821844481">70%</a>,
<a href="https://twitter.com/MitchellReardon/status/739957295564476416">66%</a>,
and <a href="https://twitter.com/karensawa/status/743235428011020288">57%</a>,
<a href="http://www.cknw.com/2016/06/02/the-lynda-steele-show-bob-rennie-on-supply-and-demand/">56% (timestamp 3:50)</a>.
I personally have thrown in
<a href="https://twitter.com/vb_jens/status/738608945741238272">34%</a> as a contender. And, just for the fun of it, by the end of
this post I will have thrown 33% and 28% and my favorite, 81%, into the mix.</p>

<p>What&rsquo;s going on, how can there be such a large range of estimates for what seems to be a simple question? The answer
lies in the details of what exactly the question is asking, all of the above numbers are correct answers to one particular
version of very similar questions.</p>

<h3>TL;DR</h3>

<p>The takeaway I think is most useful for general purposes:</p>

<pre><code>35% of all households live on single family and duplex properties
making up 81% of Vancouver's residential land, while the     
remaining 65% of households live on 19% of the residential land. 
</code></pre>

<!-- more -->


<p>There are two fundamental ways to attack the question. One is through zoning, that is to look at area where only SDH can
be built. The other is through land use, that is looking at what area is currently occupied by SDH lots.</p>

<h3>Single Detached Houses</h3>

<p>First we need to understand what we mean by single detached house. There are two common, but quite different definitions
out there. One stems from the zoning code and refers to a property that is not stratified and has a single main structure
on it, possibly with one suite, and possibly a laneway house. This is the definition most commonly used. When someone says
they own a single family house, this is what they are talking about. Let&rsquo;s call them <em>single detached properties</em>.
There are around 75,000 of these in the City of Vancouver.</p>

<p>Stats Canada employs a different definition. To them a <em>single detached dwelling</em> is single dwelling unit comprised of a
free-standing (detached) structure. A <em>single detached property</em> may contain exactly one dwelling unit, in which case
Stats Canada would also call it a <em>single detached dwelling</em>. If the house has a secondary suite, Stats Canda would
classify it as a <em>duplex</em>. If it has a laneway house, Stats Canada would classify the laneway house as a separate
<em>single detached dwelling</em>. Stats Canada reports 47,530 <em>single detached dwellings</em> in the City of Vancouver.</p>

<p>Because of this discrepancy, sometimes it is useful to look as single family houses and duplexes combined. Especially
if one wants to mix in census data to for example look at the number of households that live in these dwellings. While
there are about 75,000 <em>single detached properties</em> in Vancouver, it is fair to assume that there are significantly more
than 75,000 households living on these properties once we account for secondary suites and laneway houses.</p>

<h3>Zoning</h3>

<p><a href="http://vancouver.ca/files/cov/Zoning-Map-Vancouver.pdf" target="_blank"><img  src="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/images/zoning_van_pdf.png" style="width:50%;float:right;margin-left:10px;"></a>
Vancouver is divided up into zones that determine what can (and cannot) be legally built on the land.
If one is primarily concerned with the area of land that where only single detached houses can be built, then zoning is
the right metric to look at.</p>

<p>There are two zones that essentially only allow single family houses as residential properties, the RS zones and,
to some extent, First Shaughnessy. Each of these has it&rsquo;s own pitfalls. The first issue is that parks are generally zoned
RS, but one cannot build single family homes in parks. Moreover, while RS does not allow residential land uses other
than single detached houses, it does allow for other land uses, like parks, schools, assisted living and other institutional
uses. So RS zoned land area is a poor proxy for the question of where single family houses could be built. At the very
<a href="https://mountainmath.ca/map/assessment?zoom=13&lat=49.2517&lng=-123.1232&layer=6" target="_blank"><img  src="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/images/zoning_van.png" style="width:50%;float:left;margin-right:10px;"></a>
least we should exclude parks from the equation, but probably also schools and other institutional land uses. After all,
it is delusional to think that even if a school were to close down and the land be sold for development that single
detached dwelling would be built on that land. Next comes the question if we should only include the lots that single
family homes could be built on, or also include the surrounding roads. After all, the roads are needed to serve the lots.
But they also serve the schools and parks, so maybe only a certain portion of the roads should be included? It gets messy,
the second image shows only non-institutional and non-park properties (no roads) coloured by zone, interactive version
<a href="http://mountainmath.ca/map/assessment?zoom=14&amp;lat=49.2517&amp;lng=-123.1232&amp;layer=6">here</a>.</p>

<p>The numbers between 70% and 56% mentioned up top are (probably) derived using some version of zoned area, possibly excluding
parks or schools for some, but including roads within RS zoning. It is easy to underestimate
the space roads take up in the City of Vancouver, overall roads right of ways make up 28% of City of Vancouver land.</p>

<p>At the end of this though process, we are starting to gravitate away from zoning and toward land use.</p>

<h3>Land Use</h3>

<p>We can simplify the discussion by asking how much space currently is taken up by single family properties. The answer
to this is 33%. I have previously written about the
<a href="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2016/02/29/land-use/">land use breakdown</a> for Metro Vancouver municipalities, but
single detached homes were not broken out separately, single detached and duplex properties combined take up 34% of
Vancouver&rsquo;s land. One can play the numbers a little more, maybe only look at single detached properties within RS zoning.
That puts the number at 28%. Throw in Shaugnessy and it rises to 29%. Recall that this excludes roads right of way.</p>

<p><a href="https://mountainmath.ca/land_use/map?zoom=13&lat=49.2544&lng=-123.1268&mu_filter=[%22VA%22]&lu_filter_n=[]" target="_blank"><img  src="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/images/land_use_van.png" style="width:50%;float:right;margin-left:10px;"></a>
Here is an interactive (data-heavy) map that shows the land use for
<a href="https://mountainmath.ca/land_use/map?zoom=13&amp;lat=49.2544&amp;lng=-123.1268&amp;mu_filter=[%22VA%22]&amp;lu_filter_n=[]">just for the City of Vancouver (plus Musqueam 2)</a>.</p>

<h3>Multi-Unit Housing</h3>

<p>One can ask the same question about other housing types, and we can read off the numbers from the
<a href="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2016/02/29/land-use/">land use breakdown</a>. 3.2% of land is taken up with low rise
apartments, 1.9% with townhouses, 1.2% with high rise, 0.3% by non-market housing, 0.9% by mixed use low rise and 0.7%
by mixed use high rise. Adding all of this up we get that 8.2% of land is taken up by housing that is not single detached
or duplex. And it also includes some commercial space in the mixed use developments.</p>

<p>That means that overall in Vancouver 42.2% of the land is used for residential purposes, 81% of which is occupied by
single detached and duplex properties and the remaining 9% is occupied by all other building forms.</p>

<h3>Share of Households in Different Land Uses</h3>

<p>We may be interested in the population density these different land use patterns entail. That&rsquo;s where things get a little
tricky, we will turn to the census for answers. From the standard census releases we can only discern the share of
dwellings that are single detached and duplex properties combined, and that number is 93,370 dwelling units. Overall
there are 264,575 dwelling units, so single family and duplex units make up 35% of all dwelling units in CoV. Glossing
over the issue that some of these may not be occupied we conclude that 35% of all households live on single family and
duplex properties making up 81% of Vancouver&rsquo;s residential land,
while the remaining 75% of households live on 19% of the residential land.</p>

<h3>Fine Print</h3>

<p>There are a number of issues with the data that might change the numbers slightly, but not by much. The first is that
the land use dataset I use lump the City of Vancouver together with Musqueam 2. That slightly changes the land use mix
and areas reported, but the effect on all numbers mentioned here is very small. Next up is the number of dwelling units
on single detached or duplex properties. The census number is likely to under report some secondary suites (although it
captures more than BCAssessment does), and properties with more than one secondary suite (so some illegal suites) will
show up as an apartment building in census data. Moreover, the census data is from 2011, the land use data we used is
about a year old, and we have manually adjusted for some recent upzoning. So there is some give or take in the numbers,
I would not expect more than a one percent move in the numbers I reported as a result.</p>

<h3>Further Questions</h3>

<p>This does not answer the question what percentage of the population lives on single family or duplex properties. To
estimate that one would have to first estimate the number of people per houshold for the different land uses, as we
expect them to differ significantly. One can start exploring how the number of people per dwelling unit varies
<a href="https://censusmapper.ca/maps/391">on CensusMapper</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[FSR]]></title>
    <link href="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2016/05/20/density/"/>
    <updated>2016-05-20T22:51:29-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2016/05/20/density</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="https://mountainmath.ca/map/assessment?layer=16" target="_blank"><img  src="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/images/fsr.png" style="width:50%;float:right;margin-left:10px;"></a>
Ever since I played with the <a href="http://mountainmath.ca/vancouver_lidar/map">LIDAR-generated building height data</a> I thought
that I should use that to map gross floor area (GFA) and floor space ratio (FSR). Gross floor area is the total floor area
inside the building envelope. So for a three storey building, it is the area of the footprint times three.
Floor space ratio is the GFA divided by the area of the parcel it sits on. There are several reasons why this may be
interesting.</p>

<p>GFA is the currency of the developer. Especially once we enter the world of apartment or commercial buildings,
gross floor area is directly proportional to the amount of money a developer can charge for a property, either when stratified
and sold or when rented out.</p>

<p>FSR on the other hand is a measure of density, and it is the currency of the zoning code. Height and site coverage are
also regulated in the zoning code and there is an obvious relationship to FSR. But because GFA is so important to the
developer, FSR usually receives more attention in public discussions.</p>

<p>Read on or <a href="https://mountainmath.ca/map/assessment?layer=16" target="_blank" class='btn btn-default'>head straight for the interactive map</a> to browse
Vancouver by FSR. Read the disclaimer at the bottom before using any data for purposes other than general reference.</p>

<!-- more -->


<h3>Maximum Allowable FSR and Spot Zoning.</h3>

<p>The maximum allowable FSR is set by the zoning code. Because land is so valuable in Vancouver, most people will try
to maximize GFA when building a new building, so they typically go right up to the maximum allowable FSR. Previously we have
<a href="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2016/03/05/physical-sfh-form-over-time/">examined the effects of various related metrics like height and site coverage</a>
for single family homes.</p>

<p><a href="https://mountainmath.ca/map/assessment?zoom=15&lat=49.2599&lng=-123.1583&layer=6" target="_blank"><img  src="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/images/spot-zoning.png" style="width:30%;float:right;margin-left:10px;"></a>
At least this is how it works for RS/RT zones. If you are looking to develop a different property, say a mixed use or
an apartment building or commercial building you will probably be looking to up-zone. That is, you will try to convince
the city (and the local population) to allow you to build more GFA than zoning would allow. If successful the city will
create a new zone just for your property and ask for some compensation in form of CACs (aiming to recoup about 80% of the
uplift in value the up-zoning creates) in return. That process is called
spot zoning and it can be seen in form of the little &ldquo;Comprehensive Development&rdquo; zones that are visible as yellow
sprinkles in the otherwise quite uniform zones on the map.</p>

<p>In reality the process of up-zoning a property is a lot more complex, arduous and time consuming, which favours larger
developers with deep pockets that can take the risk and sit out the long process of eventually obtaining higher GFA. One
of the many reasons why the &ldquo;missing middle&rdquo; is missing.</p>

<h3>Mapping Density</h3>

<p><a href="https://censusmapper.ca/maps/302#16/49.2375/-123.1573" target="_blank"><img  src="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/images/kerrisdale_people.png" style="width:30%;float:left;margin-right:10px;"></a>
From Census data we know the <a href="https://censusmapper.ca/maps/302">nighttime density</a>, that is where people live and sleep.
But we don&rsquo;t know where they are
during the daytime.</p>

<p><a href="https://mountainmath.ca/map/assessment?zoom=16&lat=49.238&lng=-123.154&layer=16" target="_blank"><img  src="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/images/kerrisdale_fsr.png" style="width:30%;float:right;margin-left:10px;"></a>
FSR is also often seen as such a measure of density, although it only focuses on density on property parcels and neglects
all the space between parcels, like roads right of ways and parks.</p>

<p>In mostly residential neighbourhoods the two densities correspond quite closely, but in areas with large commercial buildings
(nighttime) population density can be quite low while FSR is very high as can easily be seen by comparing the two maps.</p>

<p><a href="https://mountainmath.ca/assessment_gl/map?zoom=16&lat=49.2384&lng=-123.1567" target="_blank"><img  src="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/images/kerrisdale_tax.png" style="width:30%;float:left;margin-right:10px;"></a>
<a href="https://mountainmath.ca/assessment_gl/map">Tax density</a>, that is property taxes collected per area, give another view of
&ldquo;density&rdquo; in the city that highlights relative property values and emphasises commercial land use that pays five times
the residential tax rate.</p>

<p>There are lots of other measures of density that are important for different purposes, for example <a href="http://mountainmath.ca/census3">household density</a>
(in full 3D, requires modern computer),
<a href="https://censusmapper.ca/maps/359">the density of private dwelling units</a> or <a href="https://censusmapper.ca/maps/35">toddler density</a> just to name a few.</p>

<h3>Next Steps</h3>

<p>There are several directions I want to take this. Now that FSR is available for all properties, I can
compare purpose built rental buildings to strata buildings. For example, in my
<a href="http://mountainmath.ca/assessment/split_map">Buildings and Dirt map</a> I can&rsquo;t integrate purpose
built rentals because I don&rsquo;t know how many rental units they have. The assessment data from the Vancouver Open Data portal,
does not have that information, and BC Assessment won&rsquo;t share it (in a hassle-free way). But I can make a similar map based on GFA instead of
number of units and examine
how GFA effect land and building values across different land uses. And in many ways GFA may be a better unit for comparisons
than number of suites.</p>

<p><a href="https://mountainmath.ca/map/assessment?zoom=13&lat=49.2488&lng=-123.1211&layer=17&filter=res" target="_blank"><img  src="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/images/value_per_gfa.png" style="width:50%;float:right;margin-left:10px;"></a>
Or I can just make a <a href="https://mountainmath.ca/map/assessment?zoom=14&amp;lat=49.2684&amp;lng=-123.1354&amp;layer=17">straight-up map of total assessed value per GFA</a>.
And maybe add a filter to only show this for <a href="https://mountainmath.ca/map/assessment?zoom=13&amp;lat=49.2488&amp;lng=-123.1211&amp;layer=17&amp;filter=res">residential and mixed use units</a>
like in the image if that&rsquo;s what we are interested in.</p>

<p>Another interesting application is to use this data to do something along the lines of this
<a href="http://www.nytimes.com/interactive/2016/05/19/upshot/forty-percent-of-manhattans-buildings-could-not-be-built-today.html?_r=0">excellent analysis the New York Times published</a>
for Vancouver. FSR, next to building heights and lot coverage that I
<a href="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2016/03/05/physical-sfh-form-over-time/">have already analysed from a different angle</a>,
is an important metric to detect buildings that could not be rebuilt under regular zoning.</p>

<p>Lastly, having data on building GFA, together with assessment open data, allows for reverse-engineering of the GFA of individual
strata units. That makes the analysis of condo assessment data more meaningful as we can analyse assessed condo values by
unit size. One of the reasons why we are only talking about single family homes (or in some cases RS zoned homes) and
not condos is that it is very easy to compare single family homes. But comparing condos doesn&rsquo;t make much sense unless
one also has data on the size of each condo. And this has probably focused the public debate too much on single family
homes when we should be paying a lot more attention to condos. And purpose built rental units.</p>

<h3>Disclaimer</h3>

<p>The FSR was estimated using coarse building data extracted from LIDAR data. The motivation was to use the FSR for aggregate
analysis and not for getting accurate estimates of individual buildings.</p>

<p>Secondary buildings like garages or laneway houses are only inconsistently detected and mapped. The data is from 2009,
buildings built after that are greyed out.</p>

<p>The algorithm to compute FSR
from this building data is rather crude and only makes rudimentary attempts to adjust for varying floor heights of buildings
different for land uses, overhangs and eyebrows and dealing with pitched roofs or mechanical units.</p>

<p>Building data was clipped to property polygons to deal with cases of buildings spanning several legal lots or not properly
separated.</p>

<p>The FSR computed only roughly resembles the FSR defined in building codes. In particular our model with grossly
overestimate the FSR for buildings with overhanging features like
the Lookout on the Harbour Centre.</p>

<p>Block level aggregates will underestimate FSR in the presence of properties excluded from the FSR calculation.</p>

<p>Do not be use the FSR estimates as an authoritative source for any individual building FSR.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[TOD Mode Share]]></title>
    <link href="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2016/04/20/tod-mode-share/"/>
    <updated>2016-04-20T23:26:35-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2016/04/20/tod-mode-share</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/skytrain_mode_map.html" target="_blank"><img  src="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/images/mode_share.png"  style="width:50%;float:right;margin-left:10px;"></a>
Just saw a <a href="https://pricetags.wordpress.com/2016/04/20/surprising-densities-at-some-skytrain-stations/">comment on the Pricetags blog</a>
pointing to a nice <a href="http://summit.sfu.ca/system/files/iritems1/9819/ETD4936.pdf">master&rsquo;s thesis</a>
investigating various TOD metrics around skytrain stations. I got curious how the 2011 transit mode share compares to the earlier
census years listed in the thesis. And how the mode share varies spatially.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>With <a href="http://censusmapper.ca/maps/316">CensusMapper</a> at my finger tips and building on the
<a href="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2016/04/06/tod/">visuals from the previous post</a> this is an easy exercise.</p>

<p>We again simply map our concentric circles around the stations, but this time we turn them into pie charts to show the
commute to work mode share. And we show the values for the inner 400m circle and the 400m to 800m annulus separately. I
also added some basic land use data, green for parks, pink for instututional and light blue for commercial or industrial
to provide more context.</p>

<p>What we would expect to see is that the transit mode share is larger in the 400m buffer, but curiously this is not always the case.</p>

<p>Click, touch or hover to get the exact values. And sorry again, only new computers will get a meaningful result. Most
smart phones and tablets will have no problems.</p>

<iframe src="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/skytrain_mode_map.html" width="80%" height="500", style="margin:5px 10%;"></iframe>


<p><a href="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/skytrain_mode_map.html#11/49.2430/-123.0350" class="btn btn-primary">Full screen view</a></p>

<p>The City of Vancouver average transit mode share is 30%, for Metro it&rsquo;s 20%. Head over to <a href="http://censusmapper.ca/maps/316">CensusMapper</a>
to explore transit mode share in the region (or anywhere else in Canada) in more detail.</p>

<h3>What I missed</h3>

<p>The master&rsquo;s thesis was careful enough to exclude areas across the river from the analysis. That&rsquo;s good thinking, I only
took circular buffers around the stations to do this. As indicated in the <a href="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2016/04/06/tod/">previous post</a>,
in the future we will add the capability to automatically generate isochrones, so areas
within 5 or 10 minutes walking distance, and use these
as regions, instead of using circular 400m and 800m buffers around the stations.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[TOD]]></title>
    <link href="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2016/04/06/tod/"/>
    <updated>2016-04-06T16:22:36-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2016/04/06/tod</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/skytrain_tod_map.html" target="_blank"><img  src="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/images/skytrain_tod.png"  style="width:50%;float:right;margin-left:10px;"></a>
Just saw <a href="http://michaelmortensenblog.com/2016/04/05/transit-oriented-development-room-for-smart-growth-in-greater-vancouver/">this excellent post looking at density around transit stations</a>
today and though I should pull out some numbers
to go with the pretty visuals. And with CensusMapper&rsquo;s new capabilities of populating custom geometries with census data
estimates it&rsquo;s super-easy to do.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>Population density is only one measure of interest here, job density or amenities density would be others. But for now let&rsquo;s
focus on population, so how many people live near the rapid transit stations. To keep things simple we checked for a 400m
and an 800m radius circle around the stations. At least roughly, if you need to know the details check the bottom.</p>

<p>To visualize this we simply map our concentric circles around the stations and use the population density as height.
Click, touch or hover to get the exact values. And sorry again, only new computers will get a meaningful result. Most
smart phones and tablets will have no problems.</p>

<iframe src="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/skytrain_tod_map.html" width="80%" height="500", style="margin:5px 10%;"></iframe>


<p><a href="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/skytrain_tod_map.html#11/49.2430/-123.0350" class="btn btn-primary">Full screen view</a></p>

<p>What immediately stands out is that for some stations inner orange circle is lower than the outer yellow circle. That means
the 400m radius area is less dense than the 800m radius area. It&rsquo;s as if
there was an inverse-TOD development. That&rsquo;s where local knowlege becomes important to see how exectly things are like
around the stations. Maybe the station primarily servers jobs or amenities, which we did not map. This definitely deserves
more scrutiny.</p>

<p><a href="http://censusmapper.ca/maps/302" target="_blank"><img  src="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/images/population_density.png"  style="width:50%;float:left;margin-right:10px;"></a>
Of course we can also view this on the <a href="http://censusmapper.ca/maps/302?zoom=12&amp;lat=49.2545&amp;lng=-123.0433">CensusMapper population density map</a>
comes in handy, if we zoom in it breaks it down to the census block level. And CensusMapper will also function on your
old computer if that&rsquo;s what you are using.</p>

<h3>Next steps</h3>

<p>One clear drawback of the analysis is that it uses 2011 numbers, which are quite old by now. So it&rsquo;s probably worthwhile to
re-visit this once 2016 population numbers become available. In the meantime I should run the same analysis on the 2006
data to see how density around transit stations changed. Some other day.</p>

<h3>Details</h3>

<p>This section is only interesting for people who want to know how exactly the numbers were derived. Conveniently
<a href="https://twitter.com/dshkol/status/717768801664651264">Dmitry had the station data handy</a>, which I took and then threw out
the duplicates data for each station platform.</p>

<p>Getting exact number
of people in a given circle radius around a station would require a getting custom tabulation for Stats Canada. This
is clearly overkill for the application we are looking at, and if we really wanted to be more precise we should probably start
by using an isochrone, that is an area that is at a 10 minute walking distance from the station, instead of using a circle.</p>

<p>In the future we will bake the ability to compute isochrones right into CensusMapper. Right now CensusMapper
estimates population data for arbitrary regions, including circular ones, by checking which census blocks intersect
each circle and add up the populations. Actually, we have three differnt ways to do this</p>

<ol type="a">
<li>by just taking all dissemination blocks that intersect</li>
<li>by just taking all dissemination blocks with the majority of its area in the intersection with the region</li>
<li>by scaling all properties of the dissemination block according to the proportion of its area in the overlap with our region.</li>
</ol>


<p>Each has its own advantages and disadvantages, we felt that option 2 is best suited for our purposes.</p>

<p>So we end up with a slightly different areas from the circle, the area given by the
census blocks we included, and we compute population densities based on that area. Since we visualize the circles instead
of the union of the census blocks used the visualization is a little bit misleading, but there is some value in the simplicity
of sticking with circles.</p>

<p>Since we are only interested in population data
we are done. In the more general case, when we are interested in estimating other census variables, for example the average rent in the
area, CensusMapper would now go through the census geographies and match up appropriate geographies with the census blocks
to derive the appropriate estimates. The actual algorithm gets quite complex here. Extra weights, like the proportion of
households that rent (and not own), come into play, as well as data quality estimates. And yes, if we did opt to use area overlap
weights in the block level computation, we would base them on households instead of population. If I am vague here it&rsquo;s
because the algorithm is quite complex and not really fit for a blog post.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[On Houses and Dirt]]></title>
    <link href="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2016/04/01/on-dirt-and-houses/"/>
    <updated>2016-04-01T22:30:43-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2016/04/01/on-dirt-and-houses</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The story of Vancouver real estate is mostly a story of dirt. After spending a bit of time to collect relevant data I
am now wondering how to make better visualizations to make that data more accessible.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p><a href="http://mountainmath.ca/map/assessment?zoom=13&lat=49.2483&lng=-123.1139&layer=9" target="_blank"><img  src="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/images/sfh.png"  style="width:50%;float:right;margin-left:10px;"></a>
Looking at my <a href="http://www.mountainmath.ca/map/assessment">old maps based around assessment data</a>, there are a couple of things that bother me. They are not very
good at showing changes over time. And they are not very good at highlighting the different role of dirt and the
houses on top. Yes, they do have separate views for building value, land value and various changes over time.
But the visuals aren&rsquo;t catchy and intuitive. When mapping building values I show the properties the buildings sit
on, instead of the building footprint. When mapping value increases I just map a some kind of ratio of values between
specific years. I use colours to visualize values, highlighting large differences but losing the smaller differences
within the colour brackets.</p>

<p>What would a better visual look like? I want to better explain the different roles played by dirt and houses. But
retain interactivity and the ability to zoom and pan around.</p>

<h3>Better Visualizations</h3>

<p>The idea is to map buildings and properties on the same map. Using 3D mapping we can uses height as an intuitive
representation for value, adding colour brackets for additional reference as values push through emotionally relevant
brackets, like the $1m barrier. To show change over time we just add a time slider and animate the whole thing.
To keep things simple and comparable we will focus on single family homes for now.
<a href="http://www.mountainmath.ca/assessment/split_map" target="_blank"><img  src="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/images/vanre.gif" style="margin:10px;"></a></p>

<p>We build three maps, one showing land and buildings on the same map, one just showing land values and one just showing building
values. All three can be animated over time.</p>

<p>We normalized all dollar amounts to 2015 by adjusting for inflation. There are good reasons for going either
way, adjusting for inflation or keeping it in original dollar amounts. For this animation we felt the it was better to show
real (inflation adjusted) value growth. Keep in mind that this means is that if a property cost $1,000,000 in 2005 dollars we will
show the value for 2005 to be $1,175,686 in 2015 dollars.</p>

<h3>The Rub</h3>

<p>I find these maps much more intuitive and instructive than earlier maps I did. But it comes at a price &ndash; these maps
will give your GPU a run for it&rsquo;s money. And they are only visible on modern computers and browsers. They can be viewed
on mobile too, but don&rsquo;t try to zoom out. They eat up quite a bit of memory and may crash your mobile browser.</p>

<p>Go test how &ldquo;modern&rdquo; your computer is. It&rsquo;s kind of fun to view the houses in different areas evolve over time. Try out
the <a href="http://www.mountainmath.ca/assessment/split_map">interactive animations</a> with just the houses or with both, houses and land.</p>

<h3>Local Stories</h3>

<p><a href="http://mountainmath.ca/assessment/split_map?zoom=17&lat=49.2362&lng=-123.1365&type=1&use3D=1&year=2015" target="_blank"><img  src="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/images/s_vanre.gif" loop="0" style="width:50%;float:left;margin-right:10px;"></a>
Zooming into these maps we can start to see the local stories of the Vancouver single family homes during the last 11 years.
Over time one sees where the land value is doing almost all of the lifting, but occasionally one sees re-development or
extensive re-modeling activity that pushes up the building value as buildings try to catch up with the sharp rise in land
value.</p>

<p>And this is really the essence of the Vancouver real estate story when viewing dirt vs buildings. The land values are rising
so fast that the building values don&rsquo;t have time to catch up. In fact, during the last year alone the aggregate land values of all single family
homes <a href="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2016/01/24/work-vs-twiddling-thumbs/">exceeded the combined pre-tax income of all Vancouverites</a>.</p>

<p>The speed of the rise in land values is also driving the rapid re-development
of buildings as explained <a href="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2016/01/18/redevelopment/">in an earlier post</a>.</p>

<h3>Unaffordable Dirt</h3>

<p><a href="http://mountainmath.ca/assessment/split_map?zoom=17&lat=49.2362&lng=-123.1365&type=3&use3D=1&year=2006" target="_blank"><img  src="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/images/b_vanre.gif" loop="0" style="width:50%;float:right;margin-left:10px;"></a>
The visualizations show that Vancouver&rsquo;s &ldquo;unaffordable housing&rdquo; is really all about &ldquo;unaffordable dirt&rdquo; and not &ldquo;unaffordable houses&rdquo;.
Looking at only the houses, we see that while there are some multi-million dollar houses, most houses are very affordable. It&rsquo;s just the
dirt they sit on that is really expensive.</p>

<p>This distinction does not matter much if one is buying a house. But it does matter when making policy decisions. One way
to make housing more affordable is to reduce the impact of the land value. Converting a single detached house into a
duplex immediately cuts the land value in half. If we replace it with a 4-plex, land values go down to a quarter for each
housing unit.</p>

<h3>Dividing Dirt (Update)</h3>

<p>We added stratified residential units into the visualization so we can take a closer look what happens when we <em>divide dirt</em>,
that is when we allow more housing units on a single property. In the RT zones
the city allows duplexes or coach houses, so two stratified units on a single property. In other zones, like RM, some CD and
some commercial (mixed use) the city allows for more strata units per property. We added a unit slider that allows to
filter residential properties by how many strata units they house. If upper and lower cutoffs are set to 1, we just get single
detached properties. If both are set to 2, we get duplexes. If the slider range is 4-20 then we see all buildings with somewhere
between 4 and 20 units. Note that we did not map any purpose built rental buildings, that is residential buildings that
have more than 2 units but are not stratified.</p>

<p><a href="http://mountainmath.ca/assessment/split_map?zoom=15&lat=49.2665&lng=-123.1496&type=1&use3D=1&year=2015&units=[1,700]" target="_blank"><img  src="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/images/m_vanre.gif" loop="0" style="width:50%;float:left;margin-right:10px;"></a>
We then use the <em>average</em> value of the land and the building per unit to map colour and height. Starting out mapping
only buildings with at least 40 units we see that the average price of a unit is solidly in the bottom color bracket for most properties.
As we slowly add in buildings with fewer units we see that only once we get down to 3 and 4-plexes do we see a clear increase
in more expensive properties on our colour scale. Adding in duplexes then leaves a clear mark with, in genreal, twice the
value of 4-plexes on a comparably sized property, and then another jump by a factor of two as we add in the single detached
properties.</p>

<p>Looking at the general condo picture, we generally see savings on a per-unit basis as we increase the number of units per property.
Those savings are most pronounced for lower unit counts and seem to flatten out once we hit around 20 units as building values
per unit stabilize and land values also rise proportionally to the unit number.</p>

<p>Some luxury developments stand out, but even there land values dominate. There are very few strata buildings where
building values exceed land values. I would be curious to hear what economists think about this, to me it looks like a sign
that land values of condo buildings are inflated because of the artificial sparsity of available land for such developments
through restrictive zoning code.</p>

<h3>Data (only if you need to know)</h3>

<p>The data used for this consist of merging four datasets. The Vancouver property boundary data set, the Vancouver
tax assessment dataset (for tax years 2006 and 2016, estimating values on July 1st of each previous year),
the Vancouver building footprint dataset (based on 2009 LIDAR data)
and the Metro Vancouver land use dataset to help identify single family homes, especially the 15% outside of RS zoned areas.
The tax assessment dataset gives an estimate of the values on July 1st of the year indicated in the visualization.</p>

<p>The datasets all have their issues and are a little out of sync. The property dataset is for a fixed point in time and
may not properly reflect the legal state of properties for all years (when for example properties were joined or split).
The tax dataset is not in all cases properly linked to the properties, in particular if the tax code changed which happens
in some but not all cases when the building gets redeveloped. There are 854 such single family home properties in Vancouver
that we can&rsquo;t trace for the whole time period. On
the map they will be visible as greyed out properties for earlier years that in later years spring to life as we can trace them.</p>

<p>Especially in the earlier years the dataset will not properly identify all single detached homes if they have been converted
to duplexes or other multi-family units in the meantime.</p>

<p>The building dataset represents a snapshot in time around
2009. We don&rsquo;t show properties that did not have a building in 2009 (767 properties, 562 of which are single detached),
and if properties have been re-built since 2009 we show the old building.
The Land Use dataset is lagging behind a bit and has for example not caught up with recent re-developments along
the Cambie corridor.</p>

<p>We also dropped 296 residential properties that did not have a land value for 2016, most lightly because they are
being re-developed and linking the assessment to the property failed.</p>

<p>The land and building value data is estimated by BC Assessment and is based on sales of comparable properties in the time before and after July 1 and
takes into account information from building permits and other evaluations. On an individual building level, especially for older buildings that
have not been sold for a long time, the data can be somewhat inaccurate at times. But in aggregate it provides a fairly
accurate snapshot of the property and building values.</p>

<p>Neither the zoning information, not the land use have been updated to catch some of these freshly developed land assemblies.
I have manually removed a good dozen obvious ones from the dataset, there are probably some more hidden in there.</p>

<p>Most of the problems stem from the fact that BCAssessment data, which has much more comprehensive and cleaner data,
is not directly accessible.</p>

<script>
function resetImages(){
    $('img').each(function(img){
        imgsrc = $(img).attr('src');
        if (imgsrc.slice(imgsrc.length-4)=='.gif') {
            $(img).attr('src', '');
            $(img).attr('src', imgsrc);
            
        }
    });
    setTimeout(function(){
        resetImages();
    },25000);
}
setTimeout(function(){
    resetImages();
},25000);
</script>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
