<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: vancouver | Mountain Doodles]]></title>
  <link href="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/categories/vancouver/feed.atom" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/"/>
  <updated>2016-04-02T17:26:36-07:00</updated>
  <id>http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[MountainMath]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[On Houses and Dirt]]></title>
    <link href="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2016/04/01/on-dirt-and-houses/"/>
    <updated>2016-04-01T22:30:43-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2016/04/01/on-dirt-and-houses</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The story of Vancouver real estate is mostly a story of dirt. After spending a bit of time to collect relevant data I
am now wondering how to make better visualizations to make that data more accessible.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>Looking at my <a href="http://www.mountainmath.ca/map/assessment">old maps based around assessment data</a>, there are a couple of things that bother me. They are not very
good at showing changes over time. And they are not very good at highlighting the different role of dirt and the
houses on top. Yes, they do have separate views for building value, land value and various changes over time.
But the visuals aren&rsquo;t catchy and intuitive. When mapping building values I show the properties the buildings sit
on, instead of the building footprint. When mapping value increases I just map a some kind of ratio of values between
specific years. I use colours to visualize values, highlighting large differences but losing the smaller differences
within the colour brackets.</p>

<p>What would a better visual look like? I want to better explain the different roles played by dirt and houses. But
retain interactivity and the ability to zoom and pan around.</p>

<h3>Better Visualizations</h3>

<p>The idea is to map buildings and properties on the same map. Using 3D mapping we can uses height as an intuitive
representation for value, adding colour brackets for additional reference as values push through emotionally relevant
brackets, like the $1m barrier. To show change over time we just add a time slider and animate the whole thing.
To keep things simple and comparable we will focus on single family homes for now.
<a href="http://www.mountainmath.ca/assessment/split_map" target="_blank"><img  src="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/images/vanre.gif" style="margin:10px;"></a></p>

<p>We build three maps, one showing land and buildings on the same map, one just showing land values and one just showing building
values. All three can be animated over time.</p>

<p>We normalized all dollar amounts to 2015 by adjusting for inflation. There are good reasons for going either
way, adjusting for inflation or keeping it in original dollar amounts. For this animation we felt the it was better to show
real (inflation adjusted) value growth. Keep in mind that this means is that if a property cost $1,000,000 in 2005 dollars we will
show the value for 2005 to be $1,175,686 in 2015 dollars.</p>

<h3>The Rub</h3>

<p>I find these maps much more intuitive and instructive than earlier maps I did. But it comes at a price &ndash; these maps
will give your GPU a run for it&rsquo;s money. And they are only visible on modern computers and browsers. They can be viewed
on mobile too, but don&rsquo;t try to zoom out. They eat up quite a bit of memory and may crash your mobile browser.</p>

<p>Go test how &ldquo;modern&rdquo; your computer is. It&rsquo;s kind of fun to view the houses in different areas evolve over time. Try out
the <a href="http://www.mountainmath.ca/assessment/split_map">interactive animations</a> with just the houses or with both, houses and land.</p>

<h3>Local Stories</h3>

<p><a href="http://mountainmath.ca/assessment/split_map?zoom=17&lat=49.2362&lng=-123.1365&type=1&use3D=1&year=2015" target="_blank"><img  src="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/images/s_vanre.gif" style="width:50%;float:left;margin-right:10px;"></a>
Zooming into these maps we can start to see the local stories of the Vancouver single family homes during the last 11 years.
Over time one sees where the land value is doing almost all of the lifting, but occasionally one sees re-development or
extensive re-modeling activity that pushes up the building value as buildings try to catch up with the sharp rise in land
value.</p>

<p>And this is really the essence of the Vancouver real estate story when viewing dirt vs buildings. The land values are rising
so fast that the building values don&rsquo;t have time to catch up. In fact, during the last year alone the aggregate land values of all single family
homes <a href="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2016/01/24/work-vs-twiddling-thumbs/">exceeded the combined pre-tax income of all Vancouverites</a>.</p>

<p>The speed of the rise in land values is also driving the rapid re-development
of buildings as explained <a href="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2016/01/18/redevelopment/">in an earlier post</a>.</p>

<h3>Unoffordable Dirt</h3>

<p><a href="http://mountainmath.ca/assessment/split_map?zoom=17&lat=49.2362&lng=-123.1365&type=3&use3D=1&year=2006" target="_blank"><img  src="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/images/b_vanre.gif" style="width:50%;float:right;margin-left:10px;"></a>
The visualizations show that Vancouver&rsquo;s &ldquo;unaffordable housing&rdquo; is really all about &ldquo;unaffordable dirt&rdquo; and not &ldquo;unaffordable houses&rdquo;.
Looking at only the houses, we see that while there are some multi-million dollar houses, most houses are very affordable. It&rsquo;s just the
dirt they sit on that is really expensive.</p>

<p>This distinction does not matter much if one is buying a house. But it does matter when making policy decisions. One way
to make housing more affordable is to reduce the impact of the land value. Converting a single detached house into a
duplex immediately cuts the land value in half. If we replace it with a 4-plex, land values go down by a quarter for each
housing unit.</p>

<h3>Next Steps</h3>

<p>This points us toward investigating how the evolution of the single detached property value compares to that of duplexes,
4-plexes or, more generally, the &ldquo;missing middle&rdquo;. We should add stratified units into the visualization and see how
they fair (taking the average over all units in each building) in terms of affordability and how this compares to
single detached.</p>

<h3>Data</h3>

<p>The data used for this consist of merging four datasets. The Vancouver property boundary data set, the Vancouver
tax assessment dataset (for years 2006 and 2016), the Vancouver building footprint dataset (based on 2009 LIDAR data)
and the Metro Vancouver land use dataset to help identify single family homes, especially the 15% outside of RS zoned areas.
The tax assessment dataset gives an estimate of the values on July 1st of the year indicated in the visualization.</p>

<p>The datasets all have their issues and are a little out of sync. The property dataset is for a fixed point in time and
may not properly reflect the legal state of properties for all years (when for example properties were joined or split).
The tax dataset is not in all cases properly linked to the properties, in particular if the tax code changed which happens
in some but not all cases when the building gets redeveloped. There are 854 such single family home properties in Vancouver
that we can&rsquo;t trace for the whole time period. On
the map they will be visible as greyed out properties for earlier years that in later years spring to life as we can trace them.</p>

<p>The building dataset represents a snapshot in time around
2009. The Land Use dataset is lagging behind a bit and has for example not caught up with recent re-developments along
the Cambie corridor.</p>

<p>The land and building value data is estimated by BC Assessment and is based on sales of comparable properties in the time before and after July 1 and
takes into account information from building permits and other evaluations. On an individual building level, especially for older buildings that
have not been sold for a long time, the data can be somewhat inaccurate at times. But in aggregate it provides a fairly
accurate snapshot of the property and building values.</p>

<p>Neither the zoning information, not the land use have been updated to catch some of these freshly developed land assemblies.
I have manually removed a good dozen obvious ones from the dataset, there are probably some more hidden in there.</p>

<p>Most of the problems stem from the fact that BCAssessment data, which has much more comprehensive and cleaner data,
is not directly accessible.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[On Mixed Use]]></title>
    <link href="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2016/03/28/on-mixed-use%20(1)/"/>
    <updated>2016-03-28T23:37:16-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2016/03/28/on-mixed-use (1)</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Redeveloping single storey commercial properties into mixed use is taking off in Vancouver right now. It&rsquo;s a little frustrating
to see how pretty much every story I have seen on this get the effect this has on property taxes wrong, including one on the generally quite good
<a href="https://pricetags.wordpress.com/2016/01/25/guest-on-retail-and-an-evolving-environment-with-a-short-historic-note/">Price Tags blog</a>.
Property taxes are an important piece of the puzzle in Vancouver, so I decided to go into a little detail on this.</p>

<p>Long story short, re-developing single story commercial into mixed use lowers the commercial property taxes. Dramatically.</p>

<!-- more -->


<h3>Commercial Property Taxes</h3>

<p>In Vancouver, the commercial property tax rate is five times the residential rate. Toronto also has higher property tax
rates for commercial, 3x in their case, I don&rsquo;t know how this plays out more broadly. Nor do I know when and why these
decisions were made. Generally cities have a hard time to keep space for residential areas in or close to the central
business district, and higher property taxes may help to uphold the zoning restrictions in place and keep residential
properties in close proximity to commercial.</p>

<p>The effect of the unequal tax rates is quite stark
<a href="http://www.mountainmath.ca/assessment_gl/map">when visualizing taxes collected per area</a>. And this keeps residential
property taxes low.</p>

<p>If Vancouver were isolated from everyone else it would not make much of a difference. Stores pass the
higher property taxes on to residents by charging higher prices, and offices pass them on to employees through lower wages.
Things get more complex when Vancouver is seen as part of metro, or Canada or in the world. But that discussion goes into
a different direction.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.mountainmath.ca/assessment_gl/map" target="_blank"><img  src="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/images/tax_density_mixed_use.png" style="width:50%;float:right;margin-left:10px;"></a>
On the <a href="http://www.mountainmath.ca/assessment_gl/map">interactive 3D tax density map</a> we can clearly see that the some mixed use properties (in darker red) generate lower total property
taxes than comparable pure commercial properties nearby. We will explore this in more detail in the next section.</p>

<p>For Vancouver it is also important to note that commercial leases are generally trip net, in particular the tenant pays
the property taxes. And they are quite substantial. The important number is the gross rent, which is the sum of rent, taxes,
utilities and other costs borne by tenants. That number is determined by the willingness of a tenant to lease the commercial
space, which in turn determines the rent a commercial landlord can charge for the space. In theory at least, in practice
some commercial landlords develop a relationship with their tenants and don&rsquo;t increase rents for old tenants as much as
the market would bear.</p>

<h3>Taxes for Commercial vs Mixed Use</h3>

<p><img  src="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/images/w_broadway.png" style="width:50%;float:left;margin-right:10px;">
Let&rsquo;s look at and example, the adjacent properties at
3071 and 3063 W Broadway. The first is single story commercial, the latter two story mixed use. They have almost identical
lot sizes and assessed land and building values, with the mixed use property having slightly higher overall assessed value.</p>

<p>How about the property taxes? In 2015, the 2016 taxes aren&rsquo;t out yet, the single story generated $47,797 in taxes, the mixed
use only $32,031. The reason is simple. The single story property
simply pays 5x the residential rate. For mixed use, the value gets divided up between two stories, so half the value pays
5x residential rate, the other half gets taxes at 1x residential rate. So the effective tax rate for the mixed use is 3x
residential rate. Well, the actual effective rate is 3.35x residential, probably because the first floor carries a little
higher value than the second floor.</p>

<p>The net effect is that the mixed use commercial tenant pays just over half of the property taxes as the pure commercial
tenant next door. So the mixed use commercial landlord will charge exactly that much more rent, so that the gross rent
for both commercial tenants is about the same.</p>

<p>Feel free to play with the <a href="http://mountainmath.ca/map/assessment?zoom=14&amp;layer=10">tax density</a> and
<a href="http://mountainmath.ca/map/assessment?zoom=14&amp;layer=14">land use</a> map and click into properties to see a more detailed break-down of
taxes. Be warned that the land use dataset is not perfect in identifying every commercial vs mixed use place.</p>

<h3>A Re-Developmet Example</h3>

<p><img  src="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/images/main1.png" style="width:50%;float:right;margin-left:10px;">
Let&rsquo;s see how this works when a property gets re-developed. To keep things simple, let&rsquo;s look at something that went
from single story commercial to two story mixed use. 6621 Main Street got re-developed around 2009/2010 and now spans
addresses 6615, 6621 and 6623.</p>

<p>Behind the original 6621 are now three stratified residential units, the other two addresses are the front doors for the
two commercial units that replace the two commercial units behind the original 6621 address.</p>

<p><img  src="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/images/main2.png" style="width:50%;float:left;margin-right:10px;">
So what happened to property taxes from 2009 to 2010? In 2009 the combined tax levy was $22,102,
in 2010 it was $16,859, of which $2,994 was payed by residential stratas and $13,865 by the two commercial.</p>

<p>For comparison,
the commercial property next door saw their property tax climb lightly from $20,754 in 2009 to $20,794 in 2010. So the
decrease in property taxes we see is really due to the re-development to mixed use.</p>

<h3>Bottom Line</h3>

<p>So what&rsquo;s the bottom line for mixed use re-development? Depends for who, but overall it looks pretty good.</p>

<h5>City bottom line</h5>

<p>For conversion to two story mixed use, the city collects less
property taxes than before and the overall mill rate goes up a tiny amount. Conversion to three stories or higher and
total tax revenue for the property goes up and the overall mill rate goes down a tiny amount.</p>

<h5>Commercial tenant bottom line</h5>

<p>The property tax rate goes down substantially, but rent will go up as the gross rent is determined by the market. So not
much changed assuming the form factor of the stores stay the same. In theory at least. If the commercial land lord was
giving a long time tenant a break on their rent before re-development, the tenant will have a hard time to find a different
commercial location with comparable gross rent.</p>

<h5>Residential tenant bottom line</h5>

<p>Added supply can only help. In some cases units will get stratified and sold off, in other cases the property owner keeps
the residential units as rental.</p>

<h5>Property owner bottom line</h5>

<p>Especially with the recent change in lending practices that focus on cache flow, mixed use re-development becomes very attractive.
After re-development, landlords can charge higher rents because commercial property taxes go down. And they can rent out
the residential units for added cash flow. That way, when they take that property to the bank to get a loan for their
next project they can show a large cache flow and get a bigger loan. And the re-development cycle keeps going. And with
almost everyone re-financing their properties a couple of years ago at roughly the same time, when interest rates hit rock-bottom, everyone is
now gearing up at the same time to re-develop.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[On Mixed Use]]></title>
    <link href="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2016/03/28/on-mixed-use/"/>
    <updated>2016-03-28T23:37:16-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2016/03/28/on-mixed-use</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Redeveloping single storey commercial properties into mixed use is taking off in Vancouver right now. It&rsquo;s a little frustrating
to see how pretty much every story I have seen on this get the effect this has on property taxes wrong, including one on the generally quite good
<a href="https://pricetags.wordpress.com/2016/01/25/guest-on-retail-and-an-evolving-environment-with-a-short-historic-note/">Price Tags blog</a>. People
claim that converting single story commercial to mixed use pushes up the property taxes for the commercial tenants.
Property taxes are an important piece of the puzzle in Vancouver, so I decided to go into a little detail on this.</p>

<p>Long story short, re-developing single story commercial into mixed use lowers the commercial property taxes. Dramatically.</p>

<!-- more -->


<h3>Commercial Property Taxes</h3>

<p>In Vancouver, the commercial property tax rate is five times the residential rate. Toronto also has higher property tax
rates for commercial, 3x in their case, I don&rsquo;t know how this plays out more broadly. Nor do I know when and why these
decisions were made. Generally cities have a hard time to keep space for residential areas in or close to the central
business district, and higher property taxes may help to uphold the zoning restrictions in place and keep residential
properties in close proximity to commercial.</p>

<p>The effect of the unequal tax rates is quite stark
<a href="http://www.mountainmath.ca/assessment_gl/map">when visualizing taxes collected per area</a>. And this keeps residential
property taxes low.</p>

<p>If Vancouver were isolated from everyone else it would not make much of a difference. Stores pass the
higher property taxes on to residents by charging higher prices, and offices pass them on to employees through lower wages.
Things get more complex when Vancouver is seen as part of metro, or Canada or in the world. But that discussion goes into
a different direction.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.mountainmath.ca/assessment_gl/map" target="_blank"><img  src="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/images/tax_density_mixed_use.png" style="width:50%;float:right;margin-left:10px;"></a>
On the <a href="http://www.mountainmath.ca/assessment_gl/map">interactive 3D tax density map</a> we can clearly see that the some mixed use properties (in darker red) generate lower total property
taxes than comparable pure commercial properties nearby. We will explore this in more detail in the next section.</p>

<p>For Vancouver it is also important to note that commercial leases are generally trip net, in particular the tenant pays
the property taxes. And they are quite substantial. The important number is the gross rent, which is the sum of rent, taxes,
utilities and other costs borne by tenants. That number is determined by the willingness of a tenant to lease the commercial
space, which in turn determines the rent a commercial landlord can charge for the space. In theory at least, in practice
some commercial landlords develop a relationship with their tenants and don&rsquo;t increase rents for old tenants as much as
the market would bear.</p>

<h3>Taxes for Commercial vs Mixed Use</h3>

<p><img  src="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/images/w_broadway.png" style="width:50%;float:left;margin-right:10px;">
Let&rsquo;s look at and example, the adjacent properties at
3071 and 3063 W Broadway. The first is single story commercial, the latter two story mixed use. They have almost identical
lot sizes and assessed land and building values, with the mixed use property having slightly higher overall assessed value.</p>

<p>How about the property taxes? In 2015, the 2016 taxes aren&rsquo;t out yet, the single story generated $47,797 in taxes, the mixed
use only $32,031. The reason is simple. The single story property
simply pays 5x the residential rate. For mixed use, the value gets divided up between two stories, so half the value pays
5x residential rate, the other half gets taxes at 1x residential rate. So the effective tax rate for the mixed use is 3x
residential rate. Well, the actual effective rate is 3.35x residential, probably because the first floor carries a little
higher value than the second floor.</p>

<p>The net effect is that the mixed use commercial tenant pays just over half of the property taxes as the pure commercial
tenant next door. So the mixed use commercial landlord will charge exactly that much more rent, so that the gross rent
for both commercial tenants is about the same.</p>

<p>Feel free to play with the <a href="http://mountainmath.ca/map/assessment?zoom=14&amp;layer=10">tax density</a> and
<a href="http://mountainmath.ca/map/assessment?zoom=14&amp;layer=14">land use</a> map and click into properties to see a more detailed break-down of
taxes. Be warned that the land use dataset is not perfect in identifying every commercial vs mixed use place.</p>

<h3>A Re-Developmet Example</h3>

<p><img  src="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/images/main1.png" style="width:50%;float:right;margin-left:10px;">
Let&rsquo;s see how this works when a property gets re-developed. To keep things simple, let&rsquo;s look at something that went
from single story commercial to two story mixed use. 6621 Main Street got re-developed around 2009/2010 and now spans
addresses 6615, 6621 and 6623.</p>

<p>Behind the original 6621 are now three stratified residential units, the other two addresses are the front doors for the
two commercial units that replace the two commercial units behind the original 6621 address.</p>

<p><img  src="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/images/main2.png" style="width:50%;float:left;margin-right:10px;">
So what happened to property taxes from 2009 to 2010? In 2009 the combined tax levy was $22,102,
in 2010 it was $16,859, of which $2,994 was payed by residential stratas and $13,865 by the two commercial.</p>

<p>For comparison,
the commercial property next door saw their property tax climb lightly from $20,754 in 2009 to $20,794 in 2010. So the
decrease in property taxes we see is really due to the re-development to mixed use.</p>

<h3>Bottom Line</h3>

<p>So what&rsquo;s the bottom line for mixed use re-development? Overall it looks pretty good, let&rsquo;s go down the list of all
parties involved.</p>

<h5>City bottom line</h5>

<p>For conversion to two story mixed use, the city collects less
property taxes than before and the overall mill rate goes up a tiny amount. Conversion to three stories or higher and
total tax revenue for the property goes up and the overall mill rate goes down a tiny amount.</p>

<h5>Commercial tenant bottom line</h5>

<p>The property tax rate goes down substantially, but rent will go up as the gross rent is determined by the market. So not
much changed assuming the form factor of the stores stay the same. In theory at least. If the commercial land lord was
giving a long time tenant a break on their rent before re-development, the tenant will have a hard time to find a different
commercial location with comparable gross rent.</p>

<h5>Residential tenant bottom line</h5>

<p>Added supply can only help. In some cases units will get stratified and sold off, in other cases the property owner keeps
the residential units as rental.</p>

<h5>Property owner bottom line</h5>

<p>Especially with the recent change in lending practices that focus on cache flow, mixed use re-development becomes very attractive.
After re-development, landlords can charge higher rents because commercial property taxes go down. And they can rent out
the residential units for added cash flow. That way, when they take that property to the bank to get a loan for their
next project they can show a large cache flow and get a bigger loan. And the re-development cycle keeps going. And with
almost everyone re-financing their properties a couple of years ago at roughly the same time, when interest rates hit rock-bottom, everyone is
now gearing up at the same time to re-develop.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Unoccupied Dwellings]]></title>
    <link href="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2016/03/08/unoccupied-dwellings/"/>
    <updated>2016-03-08T14:07:47-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2016/03/08/unoccupied-dwellings</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Today the City of Vancouver <a href="http://council.vancouver.ca/20160308/documents/rr1presentation.pdf">released their report</a>
on unoccupied dwelling units in the city. I watched part of the presentation and read through the report, and from all
that I can see the methodology used is very solid.</p>

<p>I have seen some confusion and even some incorrect reporting on this, so I thought it would be worthwhile to look into
the report in detail.</p>

<!-- more -->


<h3>The Data</h3>

<p>Smart meter data can be used to determine very accurately which units
are occupied and which ones are not. In theory at least, in practice this is quite difficult because of the sheer magnitude
of the data. That&rsquo;s why this is best left to companies who specialize in this kind of analysis, which is exactly what the
city has done.</p>

<p>The only problem is that not all units have smart meters. I don&rsquo;t know how far BCHydro has come with their rollout, but
most condo units should have smart meters by now, as do newer single family units. So what to do about the housing that
does not have smart meters? That&rsquo;s where things get tricky. Some studies I have seen use cutoffs for monthly electricity
consumption to determine which are unoccupied. The problem is to find the right cutoff. Typically these studies report
rates computed using several cutoffs to address that uncertainty. The problem is that different cutoffs give very different
results. For example, <a href="http://www.btaworks.com/wp-content/uploads/2009/12/btaworks_condo_study_report_final2.pdf">this study</a>
looked at 75kWh and 100kWh as monthly consumption cutoffs and reported 5.5% and 8.5% unoccupancy rate, respectively. I checked my condo unit
when it was unoccupied for two months one summer, my two fridges pushed me well above the 100kWh threshold. So my unoccupied
unit would have been counted as occupied in this study.</p>

<p>So how did the new study deal with this problem. We did not hear technical details, but during the presentation it was
explained that smart meter data was used to &ldquo;train&rdquo; a model to use dumb meter data. That&rsquo;s exactly the right approach. Going
by the fact that everything was done right I am reasonably comfortable to assume that this part was also done in a way to
give accurate aggregate numbers.</p>

<p>I am hoping that the technical report will still come out so we can be confident that the details were taken care of
properly. In particular I would like to know how the model dealt with different housing types, and how the housing type
was tied to the electricity bill. What ratio of dwellings of each housing type had smart meter data available? And most
importantly, what are the uncertainty estimates on the numbers presented?</p>

<p>Bottom line on data: Solid.</p>

<h3>Results</h3>

<p>The big takeaway is this one graph:</p>

<p><img  src="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/images/unoccupied-trends.png" style="width:50%;float:left;margin-right:10px;">
It shows that no matter what timeframe is used to define &ldquo;unoccupied&rdquo;, the rate stayed flat over time. In context of
the current affordability discussion this means that this is unlikely a driving factor of Vancouver&rsquo;s skyrocketing
real estate prices. But the absolute numbers are still quite large and there is a lot of untapped potential. While some people
have argued that supply has not been the main part of the cause of the price hike in Vancouver, it is clear that it must
be a big part of any solution. Finding effective ways to get this untapped supply online should be a priority, it is easier
and more efficient than building new housing in NIMBY-zoned Vancouver.</p>

<p>The other takeaway is that unoccupied units are dominated by condos.</p>

<p><img  src="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/images/unoccupied-apartment.png" style="width:50%;float:right;margin-left:10px;">
The graph shows the rate for apartments, which also includes purpose built rentals. As the report points out, if we
take out the purpose-built rentals, which have vacancy rates well below 1% at any given time and are extremely unlikely
to stay vacant for two or more months, we arrive at a rate of about 12.5% of condos that are unoccupied in the City of
Vancouver. As should be expected, that&rsquo;s significantly higher than what the non-smart meter studies picked up.</p>

<h3>Are rates in Vancouver higher than elsewhere?</h3>

<p>That depends exactly on what the question asks. And this is where, in my opinion, the city report fails to give a good
answer.</p>

<p><img  src="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/images/unoccupied-apartment-comparison.png" style="width:50%;float:left;margin-right:10px;">
The City implied, <a href="http://www.theglobeandmail.com/news/british-columbia/vancouvers-vacant-homes-in-line-with-other-cities-but-condos-most-likely-empty/article29072573/">and newspapers now report</a>
that Vancouver numbers are &ldquo;in line&rdquo; with other comparable cities. That claim is based on this graphic,
which is included in the report and stems from a <a href="http://www.urbanfutures.com/foreign-unoccupied/">study by Urban Futures</a>.
The study shows that the Metro Vancouver&rsquo;s rate of unoccupied <em>apartments</em> is not much different from other Metro regions.</p>

<p>The problem is that this study is read as giving the <em>overall</em> occupancy rates are similar across metro regions, which is not
the case. This is a fine point and a little technical, let&rsquo;s take a look at the actual rates of unoccupied dwellings in
the larges metro areas.</p>

<div id="unoccupied_cma" class="land_use" style="width:300px;float:right"></div>


<p>We took these numbers from a <a href="http://www.cmhc-schl.gc.ca/odpub/pdf/68323.pdf?lang=en">CMHC report</a> that looked into this
question and used the same data and methodology as Urban Futures, except they based it on all dwelling units instead of
just apartments. This difference is quite stunning, and it can be explained by the fact that e.g. Metro Vancouver&rsquo;s
housing units are to 41% apartments, vs 20% for Metro Calgary. And that various reports showed that the
rate of unoccupied units is much higher in condos, so we can&rsquo;t substitute comparisons for unoccupied apartments for comparisons
of unoccupied dwellings overall.</p>

<p>So what do the numbers look like when comparing the City of Vancouver to other cities in the region and across Canada.
In short, I do not know. Without going into too much details, the number of unoccupied dwelling units is derived by taking the number of
units that are &ldquo;not occupied by usual residents&rdquo;, which is part of the standard release of the census data, and subtracting
the &ldquo;unusual residents&rdquo;, that is foreign or temporary residents. So residents that have a permanent address abroad or
elsewhere in Canada and on Census day occupied in a dwelling unit that is not their primary residents. Think students
in a dorm room. Or someone in his vacation home. Or someone that works far from home and has a second unit close to work.</p>

<p>And to get the number of foreign or temporary residents requires a custom tabulation, which costs some time and money. But
overall not that much compared to the scope of the study the city just undertook, so it is not clear why they did not do this
and settle this question properly.</p>

<h3>Why do I see so many different unoccupancy rates?</h3>

<p>Again, that depends exactly on the question asked. The report offers a variety of different rates, using the definition
of unoccupied for 2 months, 6 months or 12 months. Each one gives a different rate. Then there is also the definitions
used by Stats Canada, the building being unoccupied on census day (and the questionnaire was not returned).
Again resulting in a differnt number. Then we can throw in the &ldquo;unusual residents&rdquo;, getting yet another number. Confused?
You should be! Difficult questions often don&rsquo;t have an easy answer.</p>

<p>The most important thing is to be consistent when comparing these numbers. Has the problem gotten worse? Use numbers that
were derived using the same methodology at different times. Is is worse here than elsewhere? Use numbers derived using
the same methodology across geographies.</p>

<h3>Geographic distribution</h3>

<p><a href="https://censusmapper.ca/maps/104" target="_blank"><img  src="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/images/unoccupied.png" style="width:50%;float:left;margin-right:10px;"></a>
In absence of the data on the foreign and temporary residents, we can take a closer look at the publicly released census
data on &ldquo;dwellings not occupied by usual residents&rdquo;. The percentage of dwellings occupied by foreign or temporary residents
are quite low, in the 0.4% to 0.2% range for these metro areas we looked at above. They tend to cluster around universities,
but may also accumulate in some other areas. Keeping that in mind we can <a href="http://censusmapper.ca/maps/104">head over to CensusMapper</a>
and zoom, pan around and use the search bar to explore the geographic distribution. The city data has shown that there
was not much change in the number of unoccupied dwellings over time, no matter how the data was sliced. That gives us
some confidence that the geographic distribution has also been somewhat stable over that time frame.</p>

<p>At CensusMapper we are working on adding previous censuses, so this will be a good test case to see how the 2006 and 2001
geographic distribution of unoccupied dwellings stacks up. For City of Vancouver the corresponding numbers are 7.5% and
5.1%, respectively. The 2006 number is nicely in line with Vancouver&rsquo;s 2011 rate of 7.7%. <strike>It is not immediately clear how the significantly
lower 2001 rate squares with the city report showing a flat trendline, but could well be due to shifting definitions from
one census to another.</strike> The 2001 Census used slightly different definitions, it requires more
work to compare these numbers. The devil is in the details.</p>

<h3>Next Steps</h3>

<p>The city study settles an important questions. The rates of unoccupied homes have not gone up. Perceptions often don&rsquo;t
match facts. And there are lots of little things to poke at of course. What about people having a cleaning person stop
by every other week? How about homes awaiting renovation or demolition permits? How about AirBnB?</p>

<p>Now all these are valid questions. But before using this to discount the study do some estimates to see how large of an effect
your porposed hole actually has. How does it compare to the number of units that were found unoccupied and how would it
change that rate? In all these cases it is quite small. Then ask yourself how likely it is that the problem would be growing.</p>

<p>Then you find that AirBnB probably needs more scrutiny. Best current estimates that I have seen
<a href="https://twitter.com/karensawa/status/707288630444699650">peg entire units rented fulltime at AirBnB at 1200 in Vancouver</a>.
Counting those would bring the rates of units taken out of the rental market by being unoccupied for a year or rented out
full time via AirBnB from 4.8% to 5.3%. Noticeable, but doesn&rsquo;t make that much of a difference. Yet. That number is
very likely to grow if left unchecked and should probably be taken seriously and regulated properly right now.</p>

<h3>Update</h3>

<p>A <a href="http://vancouver.ca/files/cov/stability-in-vancouver-housing-unit-occupancy-empty-homes-report.pdf">more detailed report</a>
is now available to give more insight into the methodology. Nothing unexpected there, although the claim that the 12.5%
rate of unoccupied condos is consistent with earlier claims of 5.5% to 8.5% is hard to follow.</p>

<p>Still waiting for the technical report to get an idea of the error estimates (by housing type). Seeing the graphs for
the 2-month and 4-month cutoffs by housing type would be nice too, as well as the respective ones using the 15 day
criterion.</p>

<div><script src="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/javascripts/unoccupied-graph.js"></script></div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Physical SFH Form Over Time]]></title>
    <link href="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2016/03/05/physical-sfh-form-over-time/"/>
    <updated>2016-03-05T22:58:06-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2016/03/05/physical-sfh-form-over-time</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I was curious how the physical parameters of Single Family Houses changed over time.</p>

<p>Using the <a href="https://mountainmath.ca/map/assessment">assessment dataset</a> merged with the <a href="https://mountainmath.ca/land_use/map">land use dataset</a>
allows to fairly accurately pick out single family houses, and also holds the age of most properies. Together with
the City of Vancouver LIDAR-generated building dataset <a href="https://mountainmath.ca/vancouver_lidar/map">that I have played with before</a>
we can look at physical building parameters.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>The city dataset is a little coarse, it only contains the main building and does not map things like garages. It&rsquo;s a little
rough and should probably be interpreted cautiously on an individual building level. One could spend the time and derive the
building data directly from the raw LIDAR dataset optimized for this purpose, but for some overview statistics the building
dataset that was derived by the city is just fine. The LIDAR was taken in 2009, so we only consider houses built before that time.</p>

<h3>Site coverage</h3>

<p>One question is how the site coverage of the buildings have changed over time. We simply line up the buildings by the year
they were built, compute the site coverage of the main building relative to the parcel size and graph the quintiles for
each year. For good measure, we throw in the 10 and 90 percentile whiskers.</p>

<div style="margin:10px 50px;padding:5px;border: 1px solid black;border-radius:5px;" class="whiskers">
<div id="sfh_coverage" style="height:200px;max-width:640px;" data-url="/data/sfh_coverage.json"></div>
<div class="legend no-margin" style="padding-bottom:2em;">
</div>
</div>


<p>What jumps out immediately is that around 1988 there apparently was a change in zoning law that reduced site coverage
of the main building. <strike>I don&rsquo;t know anything about the history of building codes, maybe someone that does could shed some
light onto this.</strike> <a href="https://twitter.com/BrendanDawe/status/706737206484795392">Twitter was fast to provide the answer</a>
it appears that changes in building code were implemented to counteract the growing footprint of houses at the time, details
can be found in <a href="https://open.library.ubc.ca/cIRcle/collections/ubctheses/831/items/1.0086386">Barbara Pettit&rsquo;s Ph.D. thesis</a>.</p>

<h3>Building Height</h3>

<p>The next obvious point of analysis is how building height, in meters, changed over time.</p>

<div style="margin:10px 50px;padding:5px;border: 1px solid black;border-radius:5px;" class="whiskers">
<div id="sfh_height" style="height:200px;max-width:640px;" data-url="/data/sfh_height.json"></div>
<div class="legend no-margin" style="padding-bottom:2em;">
</div>
</div>


<p>We observe a similar jump in the data around 1988, with building height jumping up as site coverage decreases.</p>

<h3>Building Volumes</h3>

<p>Now let&rsquo;s look at how &ldquo;massive&rdquo; the buildings are, measured by volume in cubic metres.</p>

<div style="margin:10px 50px;padding:5px;border: 1px solid black;border-radius:5px;" class="whiskers">
<div id="sfh_volume" style="height:200px;max-width:640px;" data-url="/data/sfh_volume.json"></div>
<div class="legend no-margin" style="padding-bottom:2em;">
</div>
</div>


<p>The graph does show that in general houses have gotten more massive starting in the late 80s, but after that have more or less
maintained the same volume. It shows that the combined effect of the regulation change in the late 80s that resulted in
smaller building footprints and taller buildings was that buildings overall got bulkier.</p>

<h3>Roof Type</h3>

<p>Lastly we see how the roof type changes over time, plotting the number of buildings with given roof type for each year.</p>

<div style="margin:10px 50px;padding:5px;border: 1px solid black;border-radius:5px;" class="whiskers">
<div id="sfh_roof" style="height:200px;max-width:640px;" data-url="/data/sfh_roof.json"></div>
<div class="legend no-margin" style="padding-bottom:2em;">
</div>
</div>


<p>Flat roofs seem to have been quite popular between the mid 60s to mid 80s.</p>

<h3>Length to Width Ratio (Update)</h3>

<p>A question about a regulation change in 1938 <a href="https://twitter.com/GRIDSVancouver/status/706879555550613504">came up on Twitter</a>,
so I thought I should check into the length-to-width ratio to see if anything can be seen there. A ratio of 1
would mean a square footprint, a ratio of 2 means the house is twice as long as wide.</p>

<div style="margin:10px 50px;padding:5px;border: 1px solid black;border-radius:5px;" class="whiskers">
<div id="sfh_square" style="height:200px;max-width:640px;" data-url="/data/sfh_square.json"></div>
<div class="legend no-margin" style="padding-bottom:2em;">
</div>
</div>


<p>No obvious changes around 1938, but our houses became a lot more square after the late 80s zoning changes.</p>

<h3>Next Steps</h3>

<p>After starting to see what kind of data can be derived from LIDAR data we can start to explore different questions. The
graphs open a small window into the physical parameters of single family homes over time and are only of limited general
interest.</p>

<p>For
more serious analysis we would most likely have to start from the raw LIDAR data, which takes a little bit of effort.</p>

<div><script src="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/javascripts/box.js"></script></div>




<script>

function stacked_bar_graph(div,shiftAxis,domainFormatter,rangeFormatter,domainLabelFormatter){
    if (!domainFormatter) domainFormatter=d3.format("d")
    if (!rangeFormatter)
     rangeFormatter = function (y) {
        return y;
     };
     if (!domainLabelFormatter) domainLabelFormatter=domainFormatter;

var margin = {top: 20, right: 20, bottom: 40, left: 70},
    width = parseInt(div.style("width")) - margin.left - margin.right,
    height = parseInt(div.style("height")) - margin.top - margin.bottom;

var x = d3.scale.ordinal()
    .rangeRoundBands([0, width], .1);

var y = d3.scale.linear()
    .range([height, 0]);


var xAxis = d3.svg.axis()
    .scale(x)
    .tickFormat(domainFormatter)
    .orient("bottom");


var yAxis = d3.svg.axis()
    .scale(y)
    .orient("left")
    .tickFormat(rangeFormatter)
    .ticks(5, rangeFormatter);

var svg = div.append("svg")
    .attr("width", width + margin.left + margin.right)
    .attr("height", height + margin.top + margin.bottom)
  .append("g")
    .attr("transform", "translate(" + margin.left + "," + margin.top + ")");

var data_url=div[0][0].dataset.url;
var legend=d3.select(div.node().parentNode).select('.legend');


d3.json(data_url, function(error, json) {
  if (error) throw error;
  var graphData=json[0];
  var data=graphData.data;
  var color = d3.scale.ordinal().domain(graphData.colors.map(function(d,i){return i}))
  .range(graphData.colors);
  var domain=data.map(function(d){return d.date;});
  x.domain(domain);

  function graphValueId(i){
      return graphData.class + '_' + i + '_value'
  }

  graphData.labels.forEach(function(text,i){
    var color=graphData.colors[i];
    var html='<i style="background:' + color + '"></i> ' + text + ' <span style="float:right;margin-right:10px;" id="' + graphValueId(i) + '"></span>'
    legend.append('p').html(html);
  });
  
  data.forEach(function(d) {
      var y0 = 0;
      d.values = color.domain().map(function(i) { return {date: d.date, y0: y0, y1: y0 += +d.count[i]}; });
      d.total = d.values[d.values.length - 1].y1;
  });
  y.domain([0, d3.max(data, function(d) { return d.total; })]);

  var domainTickValues=[];
  var skip=Math.round(40/x.rangeBand());
  if (skip<=0) skip=1;
  for (var i=0;i<x.domain().length;i++) {
    if (i % skip==0) domainTickValues.push(x.domain()[i]);
  }
  if (x.domain().length % 5 !=0) domainTickValues.push(x.domain()[x.domain().length-1]);
  xAxis.tickValues(domainTickValues);

  var xShift=shiftAxis ?  x.rangeBand()/2.0 * 1.1 : 0;
  
  svg.append("g")
      .attr("class", "x axis")
      .attr("transform", "translate(" + xShift + "," + height + ")")
      .call(xAxis);

  svg.append("g")
      .attr("class", "y axis")
      .call(yAxis);
//    .append("text")
//      .attr("transform", "rotate(-90)")
//      .attr("y", 6)
//      .attr("dy", ".71em")
//      .style("text-anchor", "end")
//      .text("Probability");

    function updateTooltip(d,i){
       color.domain().forEach(function(j){
             var value=d && i==j ? (domainLabelFormatter(d.date) + ': ' +rangeFormatter(d.y1-d.y0)) : '';
             d3.select('#'+graphValueId(j)).text( value);
       });
    }

  var year=svg.selectAll(".year")
    .data(data)
        .enter().append("g")
          .attr("class", "g");
  year.selectAll(".color-bar")
      .data(function(d) { return d.values; })
    .enter().append("rect")
      .attr("class", graphData.class + " color-bar")
      .attr("fill", graphData.color)
      .attr("x", function(d) { return x(d.date); })
      .attr("width", x.rangeBand())
      .attr("y", function(d) { return y(d.y1); })
      .attr("height", function(d) { return Math.max(0, y(d.y0) - y(d.y1)); })
      .attr("fill",function(d,i) {return color(i);})
      .on('mouseover',updateTooltip)
      .on('click',updateTooltip)
      .on('touch',updateTooltip) 
      .on('mouseout',function(){updateTooltip(null,i)});

      
});

}

var yearFormatter=d3.format();
stacked_bar_graph(d3.select("#sfh_roof"),true,yearFormatter,null,yearFormatter);
</script>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
