<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: vancouver | Mountain Doodles]]></title>
  <link href="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/categories/vancouver/feed.atom" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/"/>
  <updated>2015-02-03T22:04:55-08:00</updated>
  <id>http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[MountainMath]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Mapping CACs]]></title>
    <link href="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2014/11/05/mapping-cacs/"/>
    <updated>2014-11-05T12:03:25-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2014/11/05/mapping-cacs</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>After reading the <a href="http://pricetags.wordpress.com/2014/11/04/the-daily-durning-back-and-forth-on-cacs/">post on Price Tags</a>,
originally from <a href="http://karensawatzky.ca/2014/10/29/7868/">Karen Sawatzky&rsquo;s blog</a>, I got curious about getting a
geographic overview over the CACs in Vancouver in 2010, 2011 and 2012.</p>

<p>As opposed to the <a href="/blog/2014/09/05/vancouver-teardown-map/">teardown map</a> the dataset is quite small, so there should
be no problems viewing this on a mobile device. As always, map is below the fold.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>Some of the property addresses did not match any address in the CoV open data property database, probably because the
developments are quite new and new addresses got assigned. In these cases I mapped the CAC property to a nearby property
and added the &lsquo;Mapped Address&rsquo; field in the info pane. Enjoy.</p>

<iframe src="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/cac_map.html" width="100%" height="500"></iframe>


<p><a href="/cac_map.html">Full screen view</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Vancouver High Value Improvements Map]]></title>
    <link href="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2014/09/07/vancouver-high-value-improvements-map/"/>
    <updated>2014-09-07T22:11:08-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2014/09/07/vancouver-high-value-improvements-map</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>After the <a href="/blog/2014/09/05/vancouver-teardown-map/">teardown map</a> that looked at the low end of Vancouver&rsquo;s building
stock, a natural question is to look at the high end. Just as before, we are focusing on the (assessed) value of the
building relative to the total (assessed) value of land and improvements. We defined &ldquo;highly improved&rdquo; properties to
be properties where the ratio is at least 50%, so the building is worth at least as much as the land it is built on.</p>

<p>That&rsquo;s actually a pretty high bar in Vancouver, less than 1500 buildings pass that muster. And in concordance with the
teardown map, the &ldquo;high value improvements&rdquo; seem to concentrate in downtown. See the map below the fold
to explore for yourself.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>When browsing the map it becomes clear that some properties have &ldquo;high value improvements&rdquo; because of an abnormally low
land value, rather than an abnormally high improvement value. This is probably due to intricacies of zoning in Vancouver
that maybe someone else can shed some light on.</p>

<iframe src="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/improvement_map.html" width="100%" height="500"></iframe>


<p><a href="/improvement_map.html">Full screen view</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Vancouver Teardown Map]]></title>
    <link href="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2014/09/05/vancouver-teardown-map/"/>
    <updated>2014-09-05T13:27:18-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2014/09/05/vancouver-teardown-map</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>There has been lots of talk about old homes being torn down and replaced in Vancouver. The likeliest targets are houses
of relatively low value sitting on expensive land. So how many teardown candidates are there in Vancouver, and where
in Vancouver are they located?</p>

<p>To answer this we use data from <a href="http://vancouver.ca/your-government/open-data-catalogue.aspx">Vancouver&rsquo;s open data catalogue</a>
to build an interactive map to explore the low end of the building stock. More specifically, we set a somewhat arbitrary
ratio of (assessed) house value to total (assessed) property value (house + land) of 5% and label everything below that
a &ldquo;teardown candidate&rdquo;.</p>

<p>The short answer is that almost one in three properties in Vancouver fall into this category. And they are distributed
quite evenly across all of Vancouver with some areas like downtown looking a little better.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>On the level of the individual property the &ldquo;teardown candidate&rdquo; designation might be unfair and somewhat inflammatory.
By our above definition, a million dollar house sitting on a 20 million dollar property is a &ldquo;teardown candidate&rdquo;. In
some cases BC Assessment may have failed to properly account for recent renovations resulting in the building being
undervalued and more likely to show up as a &ldquo;teardown candidate&rdquo;. And of course not every &ldquo;teardown candidate&rdquo; will be
torn down, other options may be preferable. Depending on circumstance extensive renovations may be the better option,
and the pervasiveness of &ldquo;teardown candidates&rdquo; suggest that many people in Vancouver are happy living in a house that
is worth less than 5% of the overall assessed value of the property.</p>

<p>To aid a more individualized look at properties we included the address, the assessed land and improvement values, the
tax levy (CoV just added this information a couple of days ago), zoning information, the land area and the relative land
value. To display this information just hover your mouse over a property (or touch it on your mobile device). Opening a
second browser with a map with satellite imagery (or Apple maps) can provide additional context.</p>

<p>Take a look at the map and explore for yourself. You will need a reasonably fast computer and modern
browser to enjoy the map, it contains lots of data and may feel quite slow on mobile devices.</p>

<iframe src="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/teardown_map.html" width="100%" height="500"></iframe>


<p><a href="/teardown_map.html">Full screen view</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
