<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: zoning | Mountain Doodles]]></title>
  <link href="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/categories/zoning/feed.atom" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/"/>
  <updated>2017-06-16T13:46:26-07:00</updated>
  <id>http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[MountainMath]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[RS Population Change]]></title>
    <link href="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2017/03/06/rs-population-change/"/>
    <updated>2017-03-06T11:06:57-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2017/03/06/rs-population-change</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="https://censusmapper.ca/maps/583"><img src="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/images/pop_change_ct.png" style="width:50%;float:right;margin-left:10px;"></a>
With reporting on the new census numbers gaining traction, and now
Mayor Robertson
<a href="http://www.cbc.ca/news/canada/british-columbia/gregor-robertson-statement-vancouver-character-homes-review-1.4011100">picking up on single family neighbourhoods losing population</a>
we thought it is time to crunch some numbers.</p>

<p>Why does it need number crunching? All the reporting so far is based on looking at CT (Census Tract) aggregates, like e.g. in the
map shown and linked to the right. But there is actually no
single CT in the City of Vancouver that only contains RS zoning. Deducing results by just looking on CT aggregates can lead
to misleading reporting, like we have seen with unoccupied dwellings in the &ldquo;Marine Gateway Neighbourhood&rdquo;. Given how prominent
this topic has become it is high time to dig into the details.</p>

<h3>TL;DR</h3>

<p>In summary, we can confirm that RS (single family), RT (duplex) and FSD neighbourhoods have been dropping population.
Slightly. Looking separately at the
east and the west side, we notice that population in these neighbourhoods dropped by about 1% on the west side and increased
slightly on the east side.</p>

<p>In all groupings that we looked at the household size dropped and the rate of unoccupied dwellings increased. This was counter-acted
by a growth in dwelling units, mostly confined to RS zones where laneway houses and suites were added (or newly discovered
in the 2016 census).</p>

<p>We split the analysis into <em>core</em> regions, blocks that lie completely within RS, RT and FSD zoning, and <em>fringe</em> regions,
blocks that have RS, RT or FSD zoning as well as other zoning. Fringe regions grew in population and had overall lower rates
of unoccupied units when compared to core regions.</p>

<!-- more -->


<h3>Comparing Censuses</h3>

<p>Comparing data across censuses is hard. For one, definitions change from one census to the next
and thus variables aren&rsquo;t always comparable. Four our immediate goal of comparing
population, private dwellings, and private households between the 2011 and 2016 censuses
that is not a concern.</p>

<p>Comparing data is relatively easy when census geographies are large (i.e. CT, CSD level or higher)
and the census geography matches exactly the area that we are interested in. For CSDs (Municipalities)
this is often the case, but at the sub-municipal level, the CTs (Census Tracts) or other sub-municipal
aggregation levels rarely line up with the regions one is interested in.</p>

<p>For example, if one is interested in changes in population in RS (single family zoned) neighbourhoods in
Vancouver, looking at selected CTs will only give some initial indication. The reason is that
there is actually no CT in the City of Vancouver that is entirely RS zoned. There are several that
come close (the closest one is CT 9330015.01 around 41st and Thyne, which actually
increased population from 5,364 in 2011 to 5,485 in 2016) but it shows how tricky
it is to answer the really simple question how the population changed in RS neighbourhoods.</p>

<p>So how to deal with this issue? The cleanest way is a custom tabulation from StatCan, but that takes
time, costs money, and may still
<a href="https://twitter.com/vb_jens/status/838561779970011136">result in problems when data was not geocoded correctly</a>,
which is next to impossible to detect in custom tabulations.</p>

<p>An alternative way is to compare censuses at finer aggregation levels, that is at DAs (Dissemination Areas) or
DBs (Dissemination Blocks).</p>

<h3>Comparing Censuses at DA or DB levels</h3>

<p>For our concrete example, that means we look for DBs within RS zoning and work with these.</p>

<p>There are several difficulties with this approach. The most important is that the finer data we look at,
the more likely we pick up problems with Census data (yes, there are problems) and mistake them for real world data.
For our case through, we can avoid some of that by aggregating over all DBs within RS zoning to even out some
of these issues. Morever, we can visually inspect the data to look for any particular DB that seems to be problematic
and do some ground-truthing to see if the issues are only in the data or actually on the ground.</p>

<p>The next difficulty is technical in nature. Census geographies, including DBs and DAs, can change from one census to
another and thus may not be comparable. In order to get reliable results we need to make sure that we work with
a common set of geographies for both the 2011 and 2016 censuses. Luckily this is only a technical problem that can be
overcome as census geographies don&rsquo;t just change randomly but still retain some basic comparability.</p>

<p>And it&rsquo;s perfect timing, since we just created a &ldquo;least common denominator&rdquo; tiling derived from 2011 and 2016 DBs and DAs. At
CensusMapper we work with &ldquo;cartographic&rdquo; DBs (so we clip our major bodies of water), which leads to a minor issue where
between 2011 and 2016 things were clipped slightly differently which yielded two DBs in 2011 (with 16 and 17 people in it)
being clipped out (and having no people in it) in 2017, likely a combination of adjusting some tolerances in the StatCan
algorithms as well as some minor changes in geocoding that moved the population into an adjacent DB
(like e.g. happened with 59150971009 and 59150971008 south of King Edward split along Carnarvon). Apart from that, the
result is a tiling of Canada by DB and DA-based geographies that allow for consistent comparisons across the two censuses.</p>

<p>In numbers there were 493,192 cartographic DBs in 2016, 489,676 in 2016, and these resulted in a least common denominator tiling
by 445,953 DB-based geographies.</p>

<h3>RS, RT and FSD Zones and Population Change</h3>

<p><img src="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/images/filter_all.png" style="width:50%;float:right;margin-left:10px;">
Back to our original question, how did population change in RS zoning. Before we go there, we think it makes more sense to expand
the question to ask for RS, RT (duplex) and FSD (First Shaughnessy) combined as these are about equally restrictive in what
we allow there.</p>

<p>Grabbing the <a href="http://data.vancouver.ca/datacatalogue/zoning.htm">latest available zoning data</a> and uploading it to
CensusMapper makes it easy to download the 2011 and 2016 dissemination blocks that intersect RS, RT and FSD zoning. We removed the RS part
that snakes along the downtown beaches and covers Stanley Park, as well as the sliver creeping up False Creek and covering the marinas there.</p>

<p>When we intersect the census data with the zones, we also compute the overlap each DB has with the zoning and disregard any region
with less than 10% overlap. Moreover we divide the dissemination blocks into <em>core</em> blocks where
the overlap is greater than 99% and <em>fringe</em> blocks, where the overlap is less than 99%.</p>

<p>One should remember that a significant
portion (a majority actually) of RS, RT and FSD dwellings are contained in &ldquo;fringe&rdquo; areas.
So it is best to focus on the rates of change, we would expect the total number of population decline
of all RS, RT and FSD zoned properties to be higher.</p>

<p>Here are the results:</p>

<pre><code>RS, RT, FSD
core: 236 DB, fringe: 475 DB
Population 2011 - 2016
core pop change: -69, fringe pop change: 6673, core total pop: 124916, fringe total pop: 284231
Dwellings 2011 - 2016
core dw change: 2812, fringe dw change: 7142, core total dw: 47008, fringe total dw: 121488
Households 2011 - 2016
core hh change: 1194, fringe hh change: 5127, core total hh: 42298, fringe total hh: 111801
</code></pre>

<p><img src="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/images/filter_core.png" style="width:50%;float:right;margin-left:10px;">
What we see is that the population in the &ldquo;core&rdquo; DBs did drop. Slightly. At the same time the number of dwellings
increased quite noticeably by 6.3% in the core, with essentially all of the dwelling growth located within RS zones
(as opposed to RT and FSD). So most of that dwelling
growth is due to suites and laneway houses. Note that we only capture 47008 dwellings in the &ldquo;core&rdquo; RS, RT, FSD areas,
which is less
than half of the dwelling units in RS, RT and FSD with the remaining dwellings are located within the &ldquo;fringe&rdquo; regions.</p>

<p><a href="https://censusmapper.ca/maps/596"><img src="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/images/van_pop_comp.png" style="width:50%;float:left;margin-right:10px;"></a>
Interestingly, the number of households grew much slower than the number of dwellings in the &ldquo;core&rdquo; regions, increasing the rate
of unoccupied units from 7% to 10%. Following our decomposition of population growth <a href="https://censusmapper.ca/maps/596">mapped here</a>
and <a href="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2017/02/10/2016-census-data/">explained in more detail in a previous post</a>, we see
that the population growth of -69 in the &ldquo;core&rdquo; regions can be decomposed into:</p>

<ul>
<li>-3,699 due to declining household size,</li>
<li>-4,321 due to increase in unoccupied dwellings, and</li>
<li>7,952 due to increase in dwelling units.</li>
</ul>


<p><img src="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/images/filter_fringe.png" style="width:50%;float:right;margin-left:10px;">
We can do the same analysis for the &ldquo;fringe&rdquo; areas, where RS, RT and FSD zoning mixes with other zones. Here we get a population
increase by 2.4%, driven by an increase
in dwelling units by 6.2%, and dampened by shrinking household size and a
more modest increase in the rate of unoccupied units from 6.7% in 2011 to 8% in 2016. We note that
the rate of unoccupied units increased significantly less on the fringe when compared to the core.</p>

<p>Breaking up the population growth of 6,673 people as before we have:</p>

<ul>
<li>-6,667 due to declining household size,</li>
<li>-3,996 due to increase in unoccupied dwellings, and</li>
<li>17,336 due to increase in dwelling units.</li>
</ul>


<h4>The West Side</h4>

<p>Lastly, we probably can&rsquo;t talk about this without running a separate analysis for the west side. So here we go.</p>

<pre><code>RS, RT, FSD
core: 88 DB, fringe: 184 DB
Population 2011 - 2016
core pop change: -510, fringe pop change: 1631, core total pop: 42878, fringe total pop: 105309
Dwellings 2011 - 2016
core dw change: 572, fringe dw change: 2426, core total dw: 16735, fringe total dw: 49210
Households 2011 - 2016
core hh change: -18, fringe hh change: 1226, core total hh: 15066, fringe total hh: 44907
</code></pre>

<p>We see that this confirms conventional wisdom that the population decline in the core areas of RS, RT, FSD is stronger
on the west side (and in fact population did increase overall in the core areas on the east side). The rate of unoccupied (by usual residents)
units was quite similar to the overall RS, RT, FSD, climbing from 6.7% in 2011 to 10% in 2016.</p>

<p>Again splitting up the population change of -510 people in the &ldquo;core&rdquo; area into components we get:</p>

<ul>
<li>-458 due to declining household size,</li>
<li>-1,587 due to increase in unoccupied dwellings, and</li>
<li>1,535 due to increase in dwelling units.</li>
</ul>


<p>For the &ldquo;fringe&rdquo; west side areas we again observe that population increased at 1.5%, dwellings by 5.1% and
the rate of unoccupied units grew slower from 6.6% to 8.7%. Splitting up the population change of 1,631 people:</p>

<ul>
<li>-1,278 due to declining household size,</li>
<li>-2,466 due to increase in unoccupied dwellings, and</li>
<li>5,376 due to increase in dwelling units.</li>
</ul>


<h3>Glossary</h3>

<p>We are a little loose with our use of language. In this post &ldquo;unoccupied&rdquo; is always short for &ldquo;not occupied by usual residents&rdquo;,
so in simpler terms &ldquo;not used as primary residence&rdquo;. &ldquo;Occupied&rdquo; refers to &ldquo;used as primary residence&rdquo;.</p>

<p>West side and east side were divided along the longitude for Ontario road.</p>

<p>Core regions are Dissemination Blocks that have at least 99% overlap with RS, RT or FSD zoning.</p>

<p>Fringe regions are Dissemination Blocks that have between 10% and 99% overlap with RS, RT or FSD zoning.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[SDH Zoning and Land Use]]></title>
    <link href="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2016/06/17/sdh-zoning-and-land-use/"/>
    <updated>2016-06-17T09:34:37-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2016/06/17/sdh-zoning-and-land-use</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Recently the question around the amount of space taken up (exclusively) by single detached houses has show up on my
Twitter feed citing that
SFH take up <a href="https://twitter.com/WayneFougere/status/743211599821844481">70%</a>,
<a href="https://twitter.com/MitchellReardon/status/739957295564476416">66%</a>,
and <a href="https://twitter.com/karensawa/status/743235428011020288">57%</a>,
<a href="http://www.cknw.com/2016/06/02/the-lynda-steele-show-bob-rennie-on-supply-and-demand/">56% (timestamp 3:50)</a>.
I personally have thrown in
<a href="https://twitter.com/vb_jens/status/738608945741238272">34%</a> as a contender. And, just for the fun of it, by the end of
this post I will have thrown 33% and 28% and my favorite, 81%, into the mix.</p>

<p>What&rsquo;s going on, how can there be such a large range of estimates for what seems to be a simple question? The answer
lies in the details of what exactly the question is asking, all of the above numbers are correct answers to one particular
version of very similar questions.</p>

<h3>TL;DR</h3>

<p>The takeaway I think is most useful for general purposes:</p>

<pre><code>35% of all households live on single family and duplex properties
making up 81% of Vancouver's residential land, while the     
remaining 65% of households live on 19% of the residential land. 
</code></pre>

<!-- more -->


<p>There are two fundamental ways to attack the question. One is through zoning, that is to look at area where only SDH can
be built. The other is through land use, that is looking at what area is currently occupied by SDH lots.</p>

<h3>Single Detached Houses</h3>

<p>First we need to understand what we mean by single detached house. There are two common, but quite different definitions
out there. One stems from the zoning code and refers to a property that is not stratified and has a single main structure
on it, possibly with one suite, and possibly a laneway house. This is the definition most commonly used. When someone says
they own a single family house, this is what they are talking about. Let&rsquo;s call them <em>single detached properties</em>.
There are around 75,000 of these in the City of Vancouver.</p>

<p>Stats Canada employs a different definition. To them a <em>single detached dwelling</em> is single dwelling unit comprised of a
free-standing (detached) structure. A <em>single detached property</em> may contain exactly one dwelling unit, in which case
Stats Canada would also call it a <em>single detached dwelling</em>. If the house has a secondary suite, Stats Canda would
classify it as a <em>duplex</em>. If it has a laneway house, Stats Canada would classify the laneway house as a separate
<em>single detached dwelling</em>. Stats Canada reports 47,530 <em>single detached dwellings</em> in the City of Vancouver.</p>

<p>Because of this discrepancy, sometimes it is useful to look as single family houses and duplexes combined. Especially
if one wants to mix in census data to for example look at the number of households that live in these dwellings. While
there are about 75,000 <em>single detached properties</em> in Vancouver, it is fair to assume that there are significantly more
than 75,000 households living on these properties once we account for secondary suites and laneway houses.</p>

<h3>Zoning</h3>

<p><a href="http://vancouver.ca/files/cov/Zoning-Map-Vancouver.pdf" target="_blank"><img  src="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/images/zoning_van_pdf.png" style="width:50%;float:right;margin-left:10px;"></a>
Vancouver is divided up into zones that determine what can (and cannot) be legally built on the land.
If one is primarily concerned with the area of land that where only single detached houses can be built, then zoning is
the right metric to look at.</p>

<p>There are two zones that essentially only allow single family houses as residential properties, the RS zones and,
to some extent, First Shaughnessy. Each of these has it&rsquo;s own pitfalls. The first issue is that parks are generally zoned
RS, but one cannot build single family homes in parks. Moreover, while RS does not allow residential land uses other
than single detached houses, it does allow for other land uses, like parks, schools, assisted living and other institutional
uses. So RS zoned land area is a poor proxy for the question of where single family houses could be built. At the very
<a href="https://mountainmath.ca/map/assessment?zoom=13&lat=49.2517&lng=-123.1232&layer=6" target="_blank"><img  src="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/images/zoning_van.png" style="width:50%;float:left;margin-right:10px;"></a>
least we should exclude parks from the equation, but probably also schools and other institutional land uses. After all,
it is delusional to think that even if a school were to close down and the land be sold for development that single
detached dwelling would be built on that land. Next comes the question if we should only include the lots that single
family homes could be built on, or also include the surrounding roads. After all, the roads are needed to serve the lots.
But they also serve the schools and parks, so maybe only a certain portion of the roads should be included? It gets messy,
the second image shows only non-institutional and non-park properties (no roads) coloured by zone, interactive version
<a href="http://mountainmath.ca/map/assessment?zoom=14&amp;lat=49.2517&amp;lng=-123.1232&amp;layer=6">here</a>.</p>

<p>The numbers between 70% and 56% mentioned up top are (probably) derived using some version of zoned area, possibly excluding
parks or schools for some, but including roads within RS zoning. It is easy to underestimate
the space roads take up in the City of Vancouver, overall roads right of ways make up 28% of City of Vancouver land.</p>

<p>At the end of this though process, we are starting to gravitate away from zoning and toward land use.</p>

<h3>Land Use</h3>

<p>We can simplify the discussion by asking how much space currently is taken up by single family properties. The answer
to this is 33%. I have previously written about the
<a href="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2016/02/29/land-use/">land use breakdown</a> for Metro Vancouver municipalities, but
single detached homes were not broken out separately, single detached and duplex properties combined take up 34% of
Vancouver&rsquo;s land. One can play the numbers a little more, maybe only look at single detached properties within RS zoning.
That puts the number at 28%. Throw in Shaugnessy and it rises to 29%. Recall that this excludes roads right of way.</p>

<p><a href="https://mountainmath.ca/land_use/map?zoom=13&lat=49.2544&lng=-123.1268&mu_filter=[%22VA%22]&lu_filter_n=[]" target="_blank"><img  src="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/images/land_use_van.png" style="width:50%;float:right;margin-left:10px;"></a>
Here is an interactive (data-heavy) map that shows the land use for
<a href="https://mountainmath.ca/land_use/map?zoom=13&amp;lat=49.2544&amp;lng=-123.1268&amp;mu_filter=[%22VA%22]&amp;lu_filter_n=[]">just for the City of Vancouver (plus Musqueam 2)</a>.</p>

<h3>Multi-Unit Housing</h3>

<p>One can ask the same question about other housing types, and we can read off the numbers from the
<a href="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2016/02/29/land-use/">land use breakdown</a>. 3.2% of land is taken up with low rise
apartments, 1.9% with townhouses, 1.2% with high rise, 0.3% by non-market housing, 0.9% by mixed use low rise and 0.7%
by mixed use high rise. Adding all of this up we get that 8.2% of land is taken up by housing that is not single detached
or duplex. And it also includes some commercial space in the mixed use developments.</p>

<p>That means that overall in Vancouver 42.2% of the land is used for residential purposes, 81% of which is occupied by
single detached and duplex properties and the remaining 19% is occupied by all other building forms.</p>

<h3>Share of Households in Different Land Uses</h3>

<p>We may be interested in the population density these different land use patterns entail. That&rsquo;s where things get a little
tricky, we will turn to the census for answers. From the standard census releases we can only discern the share of
dwellings that are single detached and duplex properties combined, and that number is 93,370 dwelling units. Overall
there are 264,575 dwelling units, so single family and duplex units make up 35% of all dwelling units in CoV. Glossing
over the issue that some of these may not be occupied we conclude that 35% of all households live on single family and
duplex properties making up 81% of Vancouver&rsquo;s residential land,
while the remaining 65% of households live on 19% of the residential land.</p>

<h3>Fine Print</h3>

<p>There are a number of issues with the data that might change the numbers slightly, but not by much. The first is that
the land use dataset I use lump the City of Vancouver together with Musqueam 2. That slightly changes the land use mix
and areas reported, but the effect on all numbers mentioned here is very small. Next up is the number of dwelling units
on single detached or duplex properties. The census number is likely to under report some secondary suites (although it
captures more than BCAssessment does), and properties with more than one secondary suite (so some illegal suites) will
show up as an apartment building in census data. Moreover, the census data is from 2011, the land use data we used is
about a year old, and we have manually adjusted for some recent upzoning. So there is some give or take in the numbers,
I would not expect more than a one percent move in the numbers I reported as a result.</p>

<h3>Further Questions</h3>

<p>This does not answer the question what percentage of the population lives on single family or duplex properties. To
estimate that one would have to first estimate the number of people per houshold for the different land uses, as we
expect them to differ significantly. One can start exploring how the number of people per dwelling unit varies
<a href="https://censusmapper.ca/maps/391">on CensusMapper</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
