<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: density | Mountain Doodles]]></title>
  <link href="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/categories/density/feed.atom" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/"/>
  <updated>2017-08-26T15:34:57-07:00</updated>
  <id>http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[MountainMath]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Density]]></title>
    <link href="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2017/08/23/density/"/>
    <updated>2017-08-23T10:15:29-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2017/08/23/density</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Density in Vancouver has been one of the recurring themese on this blog, and there are many
different ways to come at it. We have <a href="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2016/02/29/land-use/">looked at density in terms of land use</a>
to understand how much land is devoted to what purpose in Metro Vancouver and it&rsquo;s municipalities. We have looked
at density in terms of <a href="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2016/03/02/property-taxes-and-land-use/">tax density</a> to
understand how property tax revenue depends on land use and zoning. We have looked at
<a href="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2016/05/20/density/">density in terms of built floor space ratio</a>.</p>

<p>And of course we have looked at <a href="https://censusmapper.ca/maps/591">population density through CensusMapper</a>,
and this time we want to do a quick variation on that theme.</p>

<!-- more -->


<h2>Population Density</h2>

<p>Recently I have heard renewed chatter about how dense Vancouver is or is not. Before diving deepr into this it is
important to distinguish two types of density that often get mixed up.</p>

<h3>Gross Density</h3>

<p>Gross (population) density simply looks
at the total population divided by (land) area. Ignoring census undercounts, we can simply look at the 2016 census numbers
to compute these.</p>

<h3>Net Density</h3>

<p><em>Net density</em> takes residential land (instead of all land)
as it&rsquo;s base. One measure of net density is the <em>floor space ratio</em> (FSR), which we have
<a href="https://mountainmath.ca/map/assessment?zoom=13&amp;lat=49.25&amp;lng=-123.1182&amp;layer=16&amp;mapBase=2">approximated and mapped in the past</a>
and that also includes commercial space next to residential living space. More details on this are in
<a href="(http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2016/05/20/density/">this older blog post</a>).</p>

<p>Net density is typically what people refer to in the countext of building developments. Sadly it&rsquo;s hard to
get a hold of good data sources that would allow for meaningful comparisons across the country. The
provincial assessment authorities have that data, but in Canada this data only shared after significant financial
commitments.</p>

<h2>How Dense is Vancouver?</h2>

<p>How does Vancouver stack up against the rest of Canada? That, as always, depends on the details.
In particular, on whether we are talking about Metro Vancouver or the City of Vancouver, and on
what good comparables are. With the new <a href="https://github.com/mountainMath/cancensus">cancensus R package</a>
it&rsquo;s straight forward to start hacking away
at this question. Let&rsquo;s start simple by looking at the 10 census metropolitan
areas and 10 census subdivisions (cities) with the largest gross density. And to keep things
somewhat in check, let&rsquo;s only look at census subdivisions with at least 50,000 people. (If we
drop the population restriction we get the cities of Westmount, Côte-Saint-Luc, Hampstead,
and White Rock gate-crash our top 10 list.)</p>

<p><img  src="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/images/densest_CMAs.png" style="width:49%;"><img  src="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/images/densest_CSDs.png" style="width:49%;"></p>

<p>We see that the City of Vancouver takes the top spot among the cities, Metro Vancouver comes in
behind Toronto, Red Deer and Montréal. Great for a game of trivia, but it&rsquo;s hard to learn
much of significance from this.</p>

<p>The reason is that we don&rsquo;t know how these densities come about. Metro Vancouver contains the North Shore mountains,
a very large swath of land where nobody lives. Yet this counts to our area (or at least the horizontal projection of it).
Toronto has the green belt. How does one compare these things?</p>

<h2>Distribution of Density</h2>

<p>A good first step is to look at the distribution of density within the cities. Again <em>cancensus</em> makes it easy
to map dissemination block level density. We change gears a tiny pit and simply focus Canada&rsquo;s 9 largest (by population) cities.</p>

<p><img  src="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/images/density_map.png" style="width:99%;margin:5px auto;"></p>

<p>The large grey areas, with fewer than 1 person per hectare, jump out immediately. As the colour gradient suggest, there
are some denser areas around the centres, but the exact extent of these are hard to grasp. A better way to get a grip on
the proportion is to abandon the geographic coordinates and show the data as a tree map.</p>

<p><img  src="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/images/density_area.png" style="width:99%;margin:5px auto;"></p>

<p>Now we much more clearly how the density in the different cities is made up, the proportion of low and high density areas.
The grey areas, with less than 1 person per hectare, are the parks, industrial and commercial land base of the city. Areas with
fewer than 25 people per hectare are densities usually found in broad suburban sprawl. In Vancouver, Shaughnessey, Southlands, or the Drummond Drive
area of West Point Grey are examples.</p>

<p>We can see that only Toronto, Montreal and Vancouver have significant portions of land beyond the 100 people per hectare density, with
Montréal devoting a larger portion of it&rsquo;s land to that density than any other of the cities.
In Vancouver the 50 to 100 people per hectare density dominates, althoguh the cutoffs are quite arbitrary to this should not be
over-interpreted, whereas in Toronto the  1-50 and 50-100 areas are larger.</p>

<p>Instead of asking how much area is devoted to what density, we can also ask what share of the population lives in what density.</p>

<p><img  src="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/images/density_population.png" style="width:99%;margin:5px auto;"></p>

<p>This visualizes the density as felt by the population that lives in it. Comparing Montréal and Vancouver we see that about half of Montréal&rsquo;s citizens
live in 50 ro 150 people per hectare density, whereas in Vancouver half live in 25 to 100 people per hectare density. To make up for that, Vancouver has
a much higher portion of the population living in over 300 people per hectare density than Montréal.</p>

<h2>Next Steps</h2>

<p>There are several obvious ways to expand on this. One would be to take better comparables, so instead of comparing cities one could compare
areas with similar population centred around census metropolitan area centres. Comparing Vancouver to Toronto as cities is tricky, Toronto has
a comparable population to the whole of Metro Vancouver. So a better comparison could be to take the old City of Toronto boundaries and compare
these against Toronto. Or throw Burnaby, Richmond, New Westminster and North Vancouver into the mix with the City of Vancouver.</p>

<p>With the <a href="https://github.com/mountainMath/cancensus">cancensus R package</a> this is quite easy to do. And totally reproducible,
as I have <a href="https://github.com/mountainMath/density-explorations">uploaded the R notebook I used to create all the included images to github</a>.</p>

<p>Feel free to clone or fork it and adapt it for your own purposes.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[FSR]]></title>
    <link href="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2016/05/20/density/"/>
    <updated>2016-05-20T22:51:29-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2016/05/20/density</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="https://mountainmath.ca/map/assessment?layer=16" target="_blank"><img  src="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/images/fsr.png" style="width:50%;float:right;margin-left:10px;"></a>
Ever since I played with the <a href="http://mountainmath.ca/vancouver_lidar/map">LIDAR-generated building height data</a> I thought
that I should use that to map gross floor area (GFA) and floor space ratio (FSR). Gross floor area is the total floor area
inside the building envelope. So for a three storey building, it is the area of the footprint times three.
Floor space ratio is the GFA divided by the area of the parcel it sits on. There are several reasons why this may be
interesting.</p>

<p>GFA is the currency of the developer. Especially once we enter the world of apartment or commercial buildings,
gross floor area is directly proportional to the amount of money a developer can charge for a property, either when stratified
and sold or when rented out.</p>

<p>FSR on the other hand is a measure of density, and it is the currency of the zoning code. Height and site coverage are
also regulated in the zoning code and there is an obvious relationship to FSR. But because GFA is so important to the
developer, FSR usually receives more attention in public discussions.</p>

<p>Read on or <a href="https://mountainmath.ca/map/assessment?layer=16" target="_blank" class='btn btn-default'>head straight for the interactive map</a> to browse
Vancouver by FSR. Read the disclaimer at the bottom before using any data for purposes other than general reference.</p>

<!-- more -->


<h3>Maximum Allowable FSR and Spot Zoning.</h3>

<p>The maximum allowable FSR is set by the zoning code. Because land is so valuable in Vancouver, most people will try
to maximize GFA when building a new building, so they typically go right up to the maximum allowable FSR. Previously we have
<a href="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2016/03/05/physical-sfh-form-over-time/">examined the effects of various related metrics like height and site coverage</a>
for single family homes.</p>

<p><a href="https://mountainmath.ca/map/assessment?zoom=15&lat=49.2599&lng=-123.1583&layer=6" target="_blank"><img  src="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/images/spot-zoning.png" style="width:30%;float:right;margin-left:10px;"></a>
At least this is how it works for RS/RT zones. If you are looking to develop a different property, say a mixed use or
an apartment building or commercial building you will probably be looking to up-zone. That is, you will try to convince
the city (and the local population) to allow you to build more GFA than zoning would allow. If successful the city will
create a new zone just for your property and ask for some compensation in form of CACs (aiming to recoup about 80% of the
uplift in value the up-zoning creates) in return. That process is called
spot zoning and it can be seen in form of the little &ldquo;Comprehensive Development&rdquo; zones that are visible as yellow
sprinkles in the otherwise quite uniform zones on the map.</p>

<p>In reality the process of up-zoning a property is a lot more complex, arduous and time consuming, which favours larger
developers with deep pockets that can take the risk and sit out the long process of eventually obtaining higher GFA. One
of the many reasons why the &ldquo;missing middle&rdquo; is missing.</p>

<h3>Mapping Density</h3>

<p><a href="https://censusmapper.ca/maps/302#16/49.2375/-123.1573" target="_blank"><img  src="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/images/kerrisdale_people.png" style="width:30%;float:left;margin-right:10px;"></a>
From Census data we know the <a href="https://censusmapper.ca/maps/302">nighttime density</a>, that is where people live and sleep.
But we don&rsquo;t know where they are
during the daytime.</p>

<p><a href="https://mountainmath.ca/map/assessment?zoom=16&lat=49.238&lng=-123.154&layer=16" target="_blank"><img  src="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/images/kerrisdale_fsr.png" style="width:30%;float:right;margin-left:10px;"></a>
FSR is also often seen as such a measure of density, although it only focuses on density on property parcels and neglects
all the space between parcels, like roads right of ways and parks.</p>

<p>In mostly residential neighbourhoods the two densities correspond quite closely, but in areas with large commercial buildings
(nighttime) population density can be quite low while FSR is very high as can easily be seen by comparing the two maps.</p>

<p><a href="https://mountainmath.ca/assessment_gl/map?zoom=16&lat=49.2384&lng=-123.1567" target="_blank"><img  src="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/images/kerrisdale_tax.png" style="width:30%;float:left;margin-right:10px;"></a>
<a href="https://mountainmath.ca/assessment_gl/map">Tax density</a>, that is property taxes collected per area, give another view of
&ldquo;density&rdquo; in the city that highlights relative property values and emphasises commercial land use that pays five times
the residential tax rate.</p>

<p>There are lots of other measures of density that are important for different purposes, for example <a href="http://mountainmath.ca/census3">household density</a>
(in full 3D, requires modern computer),
<a href="https://censusmapper.ca/maps/359">the density of private dwelling units</a> or <a href="https://censusmapper.ca/maps/35">toddler density</a> just to name a few.</p>

<h3>Next Steps</h3>

<p>There are several directions I want to take this. Now that FSR is available for all properties, I can
compare purpose built rental buildings to strata buildings. For example, in my
<a href="http://mountainmath.ca/assessment/split_map">Buildings and Dirt map</a> I can&rsquo;t integrate purpose
built rentals because I don&rsquo;t know how many rental units they have. The assessment data from the Vancouver Open Data portal,
does not have that information, and BC Assessment won&rsquo;t share it (in a hassle-free way). But I can make a similar map based on GFA instead of
number of units and examine
how GFA effect land and building values across different land uses. And in many ways GFA may be a better unit for comparisons
than number of suites.</p>

<p><a href="https://mountainmath.ca/map/assessment?zoom=13&lat=49.2488&lng=-123.1211&layer=17&filter=res" target="_blank"><img  src="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/images/value_per_gfa.png" style="width:50%;float:right;margin-left:10px;"></a>
Or I can just make a <a href="https://mountainmath.ca/map/assessment?zoom=14&amp;lat=49.2684&amp;lng=-123.1354&amp;layer=17">straight-up map of total assessed value per GFA</a>.
And maybe add a filter to only show this for <a href="https://mountainmath.ca/map/assessment?zoom=13&amp;lat=49.2488&amp;lng=-123.1211&amp;layer=17&amp;filter=res">residential and mixed use units</a>
like in the image if that&rsquo;s what we are interested in.</p>

<p>Another interesting application is to use this data to do something along the lines of this
<a href="http://www.nytimes.com/interactive/2016/05/19/upshot/forty-percent-of-manhattans-buildings-could-not-be-built-today.html?_r=0">excellent analysis the New York Times published</a>
for Vancouver. FSR, next to building heights and lot coverage that I
<a href="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2016/03/05/physical-sfh-form-over-time/">have already analysed from a different angle</a>,
is an important metric to detect buildings that could not be rebuilt under regular zoning.</p>

<p>Lastly, having data on building GFA, together with assessment open data, allows for reverse-engineering of the GFA of individual
strata units. That makes the analysis of condo assessment data more meaningful as we can analyse assessed condo values by
unit size. One of the reasons why we are only talking about single family homes (or in some cases RS zoned homes) and
not condos is that it is very easy to compare single family homes. But comparing condos doesn&rsquo;t make much sense unless
one also has data on the size of each condo. And this has probably focused the public debate too much on single family
homes when we should be paying a lot more attention to condos. And purpose built rental units.</p>

<h3>Disclaimer</h3>

<p>The FSR was estimated using coarse building data extracted from LIDAR data. The motivation was to use the FSR for aggregate
analysis and not for getting accurate estimates of individual buildings.</p>

<p>Secondary buildings like garages or laneway houses are only inconsistently detected and mapped. The data is from 2009,
buildings built after that are greyed out.</p>

<p>The algorithm to compute FSR
from this building data is rather crude and only makes rudimentary attempts to adjust for varying floor heights of buildings
different for land uses, overhangs and eyebrows and dealing with pitched roofs or mechanical units.</p>

<p>Building data was clipped to property polygons to deal with cases of buildings spanning several legal lots or not properly
separated.</p>

<p>The FSR computed only roughly resembles the FSR defined in building codes. In particular our model with grossly
overestimate the FSR for buildings with overhanging features like
the Lookout on the Harbour Centre.</p>

<p>Block level aggregates will underestimate FSR in the presence of properties excluded from the FSR calculation.</p>

<p>Do not be use the FSR estimates as an authoritative source for any individual building FSR.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
