<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Mountain Doodles]]></title>
  <link href="http://mountainmath.github.io/mountaindoodles/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://mountainmath.github.io/mountaindoodles/"/>
  <updated>2014-08-29T14:32:56-07:00</updated>
  <id>http://mountainmath.github.io/mountaindoodles/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Jens von Bergmann]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Vancouver Teardown Map]]></title>
    <link href="http://mountainmath.github.io/mountaindoodles/blog/2014/08/29/vancouver-teardown-map/"/>
    <updated>2014-08-29T13:27:18-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://mountainmath.github.io/mountaindoodles/blog/2014/08/29/vancouver-teardown-map</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>There has been lots of talk about old homes being torn down and replaced in Vancouver. In the past decades land prices
have risen sharply and the building stock has not had time to catch up. A significant portion of Vancouver consists of
land that is by an order of magnitude more valuable than the building on top of it.</p>

<p>For example, a buyer spending $1.3M for a single family house worth $50k will have to tear down and rebuild, renovate
extensively or make some small upgrades. From as investment perspective, the economically most sound solution usually
is to tear down and rebuild. Money invested in small upgrades will probably see zero returns if resold, and extensive
 renovations face many hurdles to convert an old house with small rooms into more of an open living environment that
  the market values. And the &ldquo;investment perspective&rdquo; usually takes over in decision making since in most cases their
  property is by far their largest investment.</p>

<p>So how many &ldquo;teardowns&rdquo; are there in Vancouver where the house is less than, say, 5% of the total value? And where in
the city are these houses? We turned to <a href="http://vancouver.ca/your-government/open-data-catalogue.aspx">Vancouver&rsquo;s open data</a>
to build an interactive map to explore the low end of the building stock.</p>

<p>The short answer is that almost one in three properties in Vancouver fall into this category. And they are distributed
quite evenly across all of Vancouver with some areas like downtown looking a little better.</p>

<iframe src="http://0.0.0.0:4000/mountaindoodles/teardown_map.html" width="100%" height="500"></iframe>


<p>xxx</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
