<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: canvas | Mountain Doodles]]></title>
  <link href="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/categories/canvas/feed.atom" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/"/>
  <updated>2016-01-05T05:10:26-08:00</updated>
  <id>http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[MountainMath]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[dot-density]]></title>
    <link href="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2015/12/29/dot-density/"/>
    <updated>2015-12-29T21:28:40-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2015/12/29/dot-density</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h4>One person at a time</h4>

<p><img  src="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/images/bike-dot.png" style="width:25%;float:right">Dot-density maps look pretty cool.
They have been <a href="https://www.google.com/search?q=dot-density+map+images&amp;client=safari&amp;rls=en&amp;tbm=isch&amp;tbo=u&amp;source=univ&amp;sa=X&amp;ved=0ahUKEwjuy9Ch6PjJAhUivXIKHWcvDb4QsAQIHA&amp;biw=1253&amp;bih=812">flying around the itnernet</a>
lately, so we have been thinking about how to offer them in CensusMapper. They are great because they are so simple to
interpret. One dot = one person. And we can color the dots by category. And they look cool.</p>

<p>But once one looks closer there are lots of issues that need to be dealt with.</p>

<!-- more -->


<h4>The devil is in the details</h4>

<p>As simple as the the basic dot-density promise of <em>one dot = one person</em> is, it must fundamentally remain a lie for
census maps. We simply don&rsquo;t have the level of detail that the maps suggest. We don&rsquo;t know the location of people with
the accuracy depicted in the maps, and we certainly don&rsquo;t know the categories that give the color with the accuracy
suggested in the maps.</p>

<p>So what is going on here, and is the use of dot-density maps justified in light of the lying? Let&rsquo;s start by looking at
the alternative.</p>

<h4><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Choropleth_map">Choropleth Maps</a></h4>

<p>Choropleth maps is what CensusMapper is based on. We color each geographic region based on some property from our data
that we are interested in. The greatest advantage is that the representation is truthful to the data. But at the same
time it suffers from low population bias.</p>

<p>As an example, let&rsquo;s map child poverty. Child poverty is a serious problem and we would like to map it. Right away we
can think of two ways of mapping this. We could map the <a href="http://censusmapper.ca/maps/132">child poverty rate</a>,
so the percentage of children in each region
that live in poverty, or we could map the
<a href="http://censusmapper.ca/maps/134">number of children in each region living in poverty</a>.</p>

<p>Each map has it&rsquo;s advantages and disadvantages. The poverty rate map tells the chance that a child in the given region
lives in poverty. But we have no idea how many children live in each region, so it is difficult to gauge how sever the
problem is. Similarly, the map of the number of children living in poverty makes it easy to see the absolute scope of
the problem. But this number masks the relative prevalence of child poverty. And for our maps it does not adapt well
when zooming. As we zoom past census aggregation levels the total population in each region undergoes sudden jumps, and
so will the total number of children in poverty, forcing the user to &lsquo;rebalance&rsquo; the scales when zooming to get a
meaningful coloring.</p>

<p>We really need a way to blend the two maps into one. <a href="http://andywoodruff.com/blog/value-by-alpha-maps/">Value by Alpha</a>
is one way to do this. Dot-density maps is another.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
