<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: censusmapper | Mountain Doodles]]></title>
  <link href="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/categories/censusmapper/feed.atom" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/"/>
  <updated>2016-04-07T01:10:00-07:00</updated>
  <id>http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[MountainMath]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[TOD]]></title>
    <link href="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2016/04/06/tod/"/>
    <updated>2016-04-06T16:22:36-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2016/04/06/tod</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/skytrain_tod_map.html" target="_blank"><img  src="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/images/skytrain_tod.png"  style="width:50%;float:right;margin-left:10px;"></a>
Just saw <a href="http://michaelmortensenblog.com/2016/04/05/transit-oriented-development-room-for-smart-growth-in-greater-vancouver/">this excellent post looking at density around transit stations</a>
today and though I should pull out some numbers
to go with the pretty visuals. And with CensusMapper&rsquo;s new capabilities of populating custom geometries with census data
estimates it&rsquo;s super-easy to do.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>Population density is only one measure of interest here, job density or retail density would be others. But for now let&rsquo;s
focus on population, so how many people live near the rapid transit stations. To keep things simple we checked for a 400m
and an 800m radius circle around the stations. At least roughly, if you need to know the details check the bottom.</p>

<p>To visualize this we simply map our concentric circles around the stations and use the population density as height.
Click, touch or hover to get the exact values. And sorry again, only new computers will get a meaningful result. Most
smart phones and tablets will have no problems.</p>

<iframe src="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/skytrain_tod_map.html" width="80%" height="500", style="margin:5px 10%;"></iframe>


<p><a href="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/skytrain_tod_map.html#11/49.2430/-123.0350" class="btn btn-primary">Full screen view</a></p>

<p>What immediately stands out is that for some stations inner orange circle is lower than the outer yellow circle. That means
the 400m radius area is less dense than the 800m radius area. It&rsquo;s as if
there was an inverse-TOD development. That&rsquo;s where local knowlege becomes important to see how exectly things are like
around the stations. Maybe the station primarily servers jobs or retail, which we did not map. This definitely deserves
more scrutiny.</p>

<p><a href="http://censusmapper.ca/maps/302" target="_blank"><img  src="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/images/population_density.png"  style="width:50%;float:left;margin-right:10px;"></a>
Of course we can also view this on the <a href="http://censusmapper.ca/maps/302?zoom=12&amp;lat=49.2545&amp;lng=-123.0433">CensusMapper population density map</a>
comes in handy, if we zoom in it breaks it down to the census block level. And CensusMapper will also function on your
old computer if that&rsquo;s what you are using.</p>

<h3>Next steps</h3>

<p>I should run the same analysis on the 2006 data to see how density around transit stations changed. Some other day.</p>

<h3>Details</h3>

<p>This section is only interesting for people who want to know how exactly the numbers were derived. Conveniently
<a href="https://twitter.com/dshkol/status/717768801664651264">Dmitry had the station data handy</a>, which I took and then threw out
the duplicates data for each station platform.</p>

<p>Getting exact number
of people in a given circle radius around a station would require a getting custom tabulation for Stats Canada. This
is clearly overkill for the application we are looking at, and if we really wanted to be more precise we should probably start
by using an isochrone, that is an area that is at a 10 minute walking distance from the station, instead of using a circle.</p>

<p>In the future we will bake the ability to compute isochrones right into CensusMapper. Right now CensusMapper
estimates population data for arbitrary regions, including circular ones, by checking which census blocks intersect
each circle and add up the populations. Actually, we have three differnt ways to do this</p>

<ol type="a">
<li>by just taking all dissemination blocks that intersect</li>
<li>by just taking all dissemination blocks with the majority of it&rsquo;s area in the intersection with the region</li>
<li>by scaling all properties of the dissemination block according to the proportion of it&rsquo;s area in the overlap with our region.</li>
</ol>


<p>Each has it&rsquo;s own advantages and disadvantages, we felt that option 2 is best suited for our purposes.</p>

<p>So we end up with a slightly different areas from the circle, the area given by the
census blocks we included, and we compute population densities based on that area. Since we visualize the circles instead
of the union of the census blocks used the visualization is a little bit misleading, but there is some value in the simplicity
of sticking with circles.</p>

<p>Since we are only interested in population data
we are done. In the more general case, when we are interested in estimating other census variables, for example the average rent in the
area, CensusMapper would now go through the census geographies and match up appropriate geographies with the census blocks
to derive the appropriate estimates. The actual algorithm gets quite complex here. Extra weights, like the proportion of
households that rent (and not own), come into play, as well as data quality estimates. And yes, if we did opt to use area overlap
weights in the block level computation, we would base them on households instead of population. If I am vague here it&rsquo;s
because the algorithm is quite complex and not really fit for a blog post.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Unoccupied Dwellings]]></title>
    <link href="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2016/03/08/unoccupied-dwellings/"/>
    <updated>2016-03-08T14:07:47-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2016/03/08/unoccupied-dwellings</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Today the City of Vancouver <a href="http://council.vancouver.ca/20160308/documents/rr1presentation.pdf">released their report</a>
on unoccupied dwelling units in the city. I watched part of the presentation and read through the report, and from all
that I can see the methodology used is very solid.</p>

<p>I have seen some confusion and even some incorrect reporting on this, so I thought it would be worthwhile to look into
the report in detail.</p>

<!-- more -->


<h3>The Data</h3>

<p>Smart meter data can be used to determine very accurately which units
are occupied and which ones are not. In theory at least, in practice this is quite difficult because of the sheer magnitude
of the data. That&rsquo;s why this is best left to companies who specialize in this kind of analysis, which is exactly what the
city has done.</p>

<p>The only problem is that not all units have smart meters. I don&rsquo;t know how far BCHydro has come with their rollout, but
most condo units should have smart meters by now, as do newer single family units. So what to do about the housing that
does not have smart meters? That&rsquo;s where things get tricky. Some studies I have seen use cutoffs for monthly electricity
consumption to determine which are unoccupied. The problem is to find the right cutoff. Typically these studies report
rates computed using several cutoffs to address that uncertainty. The problem is that different cutoffs give very different
results. For example, <a href="http://www.btaworks.com/wp-content/uploads/2009/12/btaworks_condo_study_report_final2.pdf">this study</a>
looked at 75kWh and 100kWh as monthly consumption cutoffs and reported 5.5% and 8.5% unoccupancy rate, respectively. I checked my condo unit
when it was unoccupied for two months one summer, my two fridges pushed me well above the 100kWh threshold. So my unoccupied
unit would have been counted as occupied in this study.</p>

<p>So how did the new study deal with this problem. We did not hear technical details, but during the presentation it was
explained that smart meter data was used to &ldquo;train&rdquo; a model to use dumb meter data. That&rsquo;s exactly the right approach. Going
by the fact that everything was done right I am reasonably comfortable to assume that this part was also done in a way to
give accurate aggregate numbers.</p>

<p>I am hoping that the technical report will still come out so we can be confident that the details were taken care of
properly. In particular I would like to know how the model dealt with different housing types, and how the housing type
was tied to the electricity bill. What ratio of dwellings of each housing type had smart meter data available? And most
importantly, what are the uncertainty estimates on the numbers presented?</p>

<p>Bottom line on data: Solid.</p>

<h3>Results</h3>

<p>The big takeaway is this one graph:</p>

<p><img  src="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/images/unoccupied-trends.png" style="width:50%;float:left;margin-right:10px;">
It shows that no matter what timeframe is used to define &ldquo;unoccupied&rdquo;, the rate stayed flat over time. In context of
the current affordability discussion this means that this is unlikely a driving factor of Vancouver&rsquo;s skyrocketing
real estate prices. But the absolute numbers are still quite large and there is a lot of untapped potential. While some people
have argued that supply has not been the main part of the cause of the price hike in Vancouver, it is clear that it must
be a big part of any solution. Finding effective ways to get this untapped supply online should be a priority, it is easier
and more efficient than building new housing in NIMBY-zoned Vancouver.</p>

<p>The other takeaway is that unoccupied units are dominated by condos.</p>

<p><img  src="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/images/unoccupied-apartment.png" style="width:50%;float:right;margin-left:10px;">
The graph shows the rate for apartments, which also includes purpose built rentals. As the report points out, if we
take out the purpose-built rentals, which have vacancy rates well below 1% at any given time and are extremely unlikely
to stay vacant for two or more months, we arrive at a rate of about 12.5% of condos that are unoccupied in the City of
Vancouver. As should be expected, that&rsquo;s significantly higher than what the non-smart meter studies picked up.</p>

<h3>Are rates in Vancouver higher than elsewhere?</h3>

<p>That depends exactly on what the question asks. And this is where, in my opinion, the city report fails to give a good
answer.</p>

<p><img  src="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/images/unoccupied-apartment-comparison.png" style="width:50%;float:left;margin-right:10px;">
The City implied, <a href="http://www.theglobeandmail.com/news/british-columbia/vancouvers-vacant-homes-in-line-with-other-cities-but-condos-most-likely-empty/article29072573/">and newspapers now report</a>
that Vancouver numbers are &ldquo;in line&rdquo; with other comparable cities. That claim is based on this graphic,
which is included in the report and stems from a <a href="http://www.urbanfutures.com/foreign-unoccupied/">study by Urban Futures</a>.
The study shows that the Metro Vancouver&rsquo;s rate of unoccupied <em>apartments</em> is not much different from other Metro regions.</p>

<p>The problem is that this study is read as giving the <em>overall</em> occupancy rates are similar across metro regions, which is not
the case. This is a fine point and a little technical, let&rsquo;s take a look at the actual rates of unoccupied dwellings in
the larges metro areas.</p>

<div id="unoccupied_cma" class="land_use" style="width:300px;float:right"></div>


<p>We took these numbers from a <a href="http://www.cmhc-schl.gc.ca/odpub/pdf/68323.pdf?lang=en">CMHC report</a> that looked into this
question and used the same data and methodology as Urban Futures, except they based it on all dwelling units instead of
just apartments. This difference is quite stunning, and it can be explained by the fact that e.g. Metro Vancouver&rsquo;s
housing units are to 41% apartments, vs 20% for Metro Calgary. And that various reports showed that the
rate of unoccupied units is much higher in condos, so we can&rsquo;t substitute comparisons for unoccupied apartments for comparisons
of unoccupied dwellings overall.</p>

<p>So what do the numbers look like when comparing the City of Vancouver to other cities in the region and across Canada.
In short, I do not know. Without going into too much details, the number of unoccupied dwelling units is derived by taking the number of
units that are &ldquo;not occupied by usual residents&rdquo;, which is part of the standard release of the census data, and subtracting
the &ldquo;unusual residents&rdquo;, that is foreign or temporary residents. So residents that have a permanent address abroad or
elsewhere in Canada and on Census day occupied in a dwelling unit that is not their primary residents. Think students
in a dorm room. Or someone in his vacation home. Or someone that works far from home and has a second unit close to work.</p>

<p>And to get the number of foreign or temporary residents requires a custom tabulation, which costs some time and money. But
overall not that much compared to the scope of the study the city just undertook, so it is not clear why they did not do this
and settle this question properly.</p>

<h3>Why do I see so many different unoccupancy rates?</h3>

<p>Again, that depends exactly on the question asked. The report offers a variety of different rates, using the definition
of unoccupied for 2 months, 6 months or 12 months. Each one gives a different rate. Then there is also the definitions
used by Stats Canada, the building being unoccupied on census day (and the questionnaire was not returned).
Again resulting in a differnt number. Then we can throw in the &ldquo;unusual residents&rdquo;, getting yet another number. Confused?
You should be! Difficult questions often don&rsquo;t have an easy answer.</p>

<p>The most important thing is to be consistent when comparing these numbers. Has the problem gotten worse? Use numbers that
were derived using the same methodology at different times. Is is worse here than elsewhere? Use numbers derived using
the same methodology across geographies.</p>

<h3>Geographic distribution</h3>

<p><a href="https://censusmapper.ca/maps/104" target="_blank"><img  src="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/images/unoccupied.png" style="width:50%;float:left;margin-right:10px;"></a>
In absence of the data on the foreign and temporary residents, we can take a closer look at the publicly released census
data on &ldquo;dwellings not occupied by usual residents&rdquo;. The percentage of dwellings occupied by foreign or temporary residents
are quite low, in the 0.4% to 0.2% range for these metro areas we looked at above. They tend to cluster around universities,
but may also accumulate in some other areas. Keeping that in mind we can <a href="http://censusmapper.ca/maps/104">head over to CensusMapper</a>
and zoom, pan around and use the search bar to explore the geographic distribution. The city data has shown that there
was not much change in the number of unoccupied dwellings over time, no matter how the data was sliced. That gives us
some confidence that the geographic distribution has also been somewhat stable over that time frame.</p>

<p>At CensusMapper we are working on adding previous censuses, so this will be a good test case to see how the 2006 and 2001
geographic distribution of unoccupied dwellings stacks up. For City of Vancouver the corresponding numbers are 7.5% and
5.1%, respectively. The 2006 number is nicely in line with Vancouver&rsquo;s 2011 rate of 7.7%. <strike>It is not immediately clear how the significantly
lower 2001 rate squares with the city report showing a flat trendline, but could well be due to shifting definitions from
one census to another.</strike> The 2001 Census used slightly different definitions, it requires more
work to compare these numbers. The devil is in the details.</p>

<h3>Next Steps</h3>

<p>The city study settles an important questions. The rates of unoccupied homes have not gone up. Perceptions often don&rsquo;t
match facts. And there are lots of little things to poke at of course. What about people having a cleaning person stop
by every other week? How about homes awaiting renovation or demolition permits? How about AirBnB?</p>

<p>Now all these are valid questions. But before using this to discount the study do some estimates to see how large of an effect
your porposed hole actually has. How does it compare to the number of units that were found unoccupied and how would it
change that rate? In all these cases it is quite small. Then ask yourself how likely it is that the problem would be growing.</p>

<p>Then you find that AirBnB probably needs more scrutiny. Best current estimates that I have seen
<a href="https://twitter.com/karensawa/status/707288630444699650">peg entire units rented fulltime at AirBnB at 1200 in Vancouver</a>.
Counting those would bring the rates of units taken out of the rental market by being unoccupied for a year or rented out
full time via AirBnB from 4.8% to 5.3%. Noticeable, but doesn&rsquo;t make that much of a difference. Yet. That number is
very likely to grow if left unchecked and should probably be taken seriously and regulated properly right now.</p>

<h3>Update</h3>

<p>A <a href="http://vancouver.ca/files/cov/stability-in-vancouver-housing-unit-occupancy-empty-homes-report.pdf">more detailed report</a>
is now available to give more insight into the methodology. Nothing unexpected there, although the claim that the 12.5%
rate of unoccupied condos is consistent with earlier claims of 5.5% to 8.5% is hard to follow.</p>

<p>Still waiting for the technical report to get an idea of the error estimates (by housing type). Seeing the graphs for
the 2-month and 4-month cutoffs by housing type would be nice too, as well as the respective ones using the 15 day
criterion.</p>

<div><script src="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/javascripts/unoccupied-graph.js"></script></div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
