<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: open data | Mountain Doodles]]></title>
  <link href="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/categories/open-data/feed.atom" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/"/>
  <updated>2016-07-26T15:48:14-07:00</updated>
  <id>http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[MountainMath]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Mixing Data]]></title>
    <link href="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2016/07/06/mixing-data/"/>
    <updated>2016-07-06T09:19:04-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2016/07/06/mixing-data</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Census data is very rich and with <a href="https://censusmapper.ca">CensusMapper</a> we now have about 1 billion data points right at
our fingertips. And we have managed to open up some of our interfaces for everyone to <a href="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2016/05/04/census-mapping-for-everyone/">explore data and make their own maps
and freely share them</a>.</p>

<p>Things really get interesting when one mixes custom data with census data. While, at this point, these are not part of
the freely available CensusMapper functionality we still wanted to share what can be done.</p>

<p>At CensusMapper we have developed three basic ways to rapidly mix custom data with census data. So this is really three
blog posts in one.</p>

<!-- more -->


<h3>1. Overlay Mapping</h3>

<p>First up, advanced users can upload custom datasets and map them on top of census data.
<a href="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/images/restaurants_2.png"><img  src="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/images/restaurants_2.png" style="width:50%;float:right;margin-left:10px;"></a>
For example, we took a
<a href="http://data.vancouver.ca/datacatalogue/businessLicence.htm">business license dataset</a> from the City of Vancouver open
data catalogue, filtered it by the <em>BusinessType</em> field to only include businesses starting with &ldquo;Restaurant&rdquo; or
&ldquo;Liquor Establishment&rdquo; and uploaded them to CensusMapper to map it on top of census data. We have used a map
for <em>median age</em> that was <a href="https://twitter.com/jofu_/status/750564269796823041">recently created using CensusMapper&rsquo;s free public interface</a>
(have you made <a href="https://censusmapper.ca/maps/new">your own CensusMapper map</a> yet?), we have faded out areas outside of
Vancouver and coloured <em>Liquor Establishments</em> in red and <em>Restaurants</em> in blue.</p>

<p>Giving a visual impression of your own dataset in relation to census data is the first step to location analysis.</p>

<h3>2. Populate Custom Data with Census Data</h3>

<p>Next
up is to populate your own dataset with census data for further analysis. For the restaurants, we may be interested in
attaching population estimates in 5 minute walking distance from each location. We might also be interested in specific
age brackets, or numbers of recent immigrants
from specific countries that we may want to target with a new restaurant, or maybe even     income data.</p>

<p>This can be a time consuming and painful process,
but we have automated this at CensusMapper.</p>

<p>To showcase how this works we will show an example using elementary school catchment areas in the City of Vancouver. The
areas we have (from the <a href="http://data.vancouver.ca/datacatalogue/publicPlaces.htm">Vancouver Open Data Catalogue</a>) are
quite out of date, but for the purpose of this example they work as we will compare them to 2011 census data. We will look at the
<a href="https://censusmapper.ca/maps/419">school aged population</a> in each catchment.</p>

<!--
The general census release data does not fit our task perfectly, the census splits by age in early May 2011 and not by
year born and it does not have fine enough age brackets to estimating accurate school catchment numbers.
[BC Stats](http://www.bcstats.gov.bc.ca/StatisticsBySubject/Demography/PopulationEstimates.aspx) has finer age brackets
computed to school district (not catchment) boundaries, but their estimates are ridiculously far off of census numbers
when using matching age brackets and years that their usefulness is highly questionable. 
-->


<p><a href="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/images/e-schools.png"><img  src="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/images/e-schools.png" style="width:50%;float:left;margin-right:10px;"></a>
Using the visual overlay we notice that the catchment areas do fit boundaries of Dissemination Areas shown on the map
reasonably well, with some exceptions. The same cannot be said for Census Tracts, we can be reasonably confident that
Dissemination Area data is fairly accurate.</p>

<p>Next we use the built-in CensusMapper functionality to automatically populate the catchment areas with the census
data we are interested
in. When Dissemination Areas don&rsquo;t line up with the catchment boundaries we go down to Dissemination Blocks to estimate
how many children live on what side of the catchment boundary. We
<a href="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2016/04/06/tod/">previously explained this process in more detail</a>, the result is
a spreadsheet with the population data by age for each catchment area.</p>

<div id='schools'></div>


<div><script src="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/javascripts/colorbrewer.js" charset="utf-8"></script></div>


<div><script src="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/javascripts/school_bar_graph.js" charset="utf-8"></script></div>


<p>Here we show the results by school, the select element can be used to select any school of interest. The whole process
of populating the school data with census data just required uploading the catchment boundaries and selecting which
variables to attach.</p>

<h3>3. Custom Census Data Mapping</h3>

<p>Sometimes it is not practical to map custom data on CensusMapper. Maybe the custom data is too sensitive to be uploaded
to CensusMapper servers. Or it is quite complex and is better mapped separately. So we created an API to pull in
census data from CensusMapper to easily show census data on custom maps. And dynamically mix in your own data. As an
example we mix census data with data from BCAssessment, again obtained through the
<a href="http://vancouver.ca/your-government/open-data-catalogue.aspx">Vancouver Open Data Catalogue</a> (and enriched with
<a href="http://www.metrovancouver.org/data">open data from Metro Vancouver</a>).
For demonstration purposes take Dissemination Area
geographies and Dwelling Characteristic data from CensusMapper and mash it up with our
<a href="http://mountainmath.ca/map/assessment?zoom=14&amp;lat=49.2604&amp;lng=-123.1417&amp;layer=14&amp;mapBase=2">processed assessment data</a>
to explore the <a href="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2016/06/17/sdh-zoning-and-land-use/">differences in how single family properties are classified</a>.</p>

<p><a href="https://mountainmath.ca/census_mix/map?mapBase=2&layer=0" target="_blank"><img  src="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/images/sfh_unit_count.png" style="width:50%;float:right;margin-left:10px;"></a>
For example we can <a href="https://mountainmath.ca/census_mix/map?mapBase=2&amp;layer=0">compare BC Assessment single family lot count to Stats Canada unit count</a>
in the dissemination areas
that are exclusively made up of single family lots. This gives an indication of how many suites and laneway houses there
are in those areas. The census is prone to undercount units, but still does a better job at estimating them than other data sources,
like the city or BC Assessment.</p>

<p>One of the reasons why census unit counts come up higher than other methods is that the census also counts illegal units,
which naturally are not part of other official government counts. There are different reasons why a suite may be illegal:
<a href="https://mountainmath.ca/census_mix/map?mapBase=2&layer=5" target="_blank"><img  src="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/images/illegal_units.png" style="width:50%;float:left;margin-right:10px;"></a>
It could simply be that the owner has not made the effort to register it. Or the suite may not be up to code.
And in some cases, a property may have more than one suite in the main building, which is illegal in the City of Vancouver.
The latter ones we can pick out in census data, since a house with two secondary suites &ndash; so three dwelling units in one building in
total &ndash; is classified as being an &ldquo;Apartment, building that has fewer than five storeys&rdquo;. So, in census dissemination areas that
only have duplex or single family lots as residential land uses based on assessment and land use data, we can look for
how many dwelling units the census places in an &ldquo;Apartment, building that has fewer than five storeys&rdquo;. And
<a href="https://mountainmath.ca/census_mix/map?mapBase=2&amp;layer=5">map them</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[SDH Zoning and Land Use]]></title>
    <link href="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2016/06/17/sdh-zoning-and-land-use/"/>
    <updated>2016-06-17T09:34:37-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2016/06/17/sdh-zoning-and-land-use</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Recently the question around the amount of space taken up (exclusively) by single detached houses has show up on my
Twitter feed citing that
SFH take up <a href="https://twitter.com/WayneFougere/status/743211599821844481">70%</a>,
<a href="https://twitter.com/MitchellReardon/status/739957295564476416">66%</a>,
and <a href="https://twitter.com/karensawa/status/743235428011020288">57%</a>,
<a href="http://www.cknw.com/2016/06/02/the-lynda-steele-show-bob-rennie-on-supply-and-demand/">56% (timestamp 3:50)</a>.
I personally have thrown in
<a href="https://twitter.com/vb_jens/status/738608945741238272">34%</a> as a contender. And, just for the fun of it, by the end of
this post I will have thrown 33% and 28% and my favorite, 81%, into the mix.</p>

<p>What&rsquo;s going on, how can there be such a large range of estimates for what seems to be a simple question? The answer
lies in the details of what exactly the question is asking, all of the above numbers are correct answers to one particular
version of very similar questions.</p>

<h3>TL;DR</h3>

<p>The takeaway I think is most useful for general purposes:</p>

<pre><code>35% of all households live on single family and duplex properties
making up 81% of Vancouver's residential land, while the     
remaining 65% of households live on 19% of the residential land. 
</code></pre>

<!-- more -->


<p>There are two fundamental ways to attack the question. One is through zoning, that is to look at area where only SDH can
be built. The other is through land use, that is looking at what area is currently occupied by SDH lots.</p>

<h3>Single Detached Houses</h3>

<p>First we need to understand what we mean by single detached house. There are two common, but quite different definitions
out there. One stems from the zoning code and refers to a property that is not stratified and has a single main structure
on it, possibly with one suite, and possibly a laneway house. This is the definition most commonly used. When someone says
they own a single family house, this is what they are talking about. Let&rsquo;s call them <em>single detached properties</em>.
There are around 75,000 of these in the City of Vancouver.</p>

<p>Stats Canada employs a different definition. To them a <em>single detached dwelling</em> is single dwelling unit comprised of a
free-standing (detached) structure. A <em>single detached property</em> may contain exactly one dwelling unit, in which case
Stats Canada would also call it a <em>single detached dwelling</em>. If the house has a secondary suite, Stats Canda would
classify it as a <em>duplex</em>. If it has a laneway house, Stats Canada would classify the laneway house as a separate
<em>single detached dwelling</em>. Stats Canada reports 47,530 <em>single detached dwellings</em> in the City of Vancouver.</p>

<p>Because of this discrepancy, sometimes it is useful to look as single family houses and duplexes combined. Especially
if one wants to mix in census data to for example look at the number of households that live in these dwellings. While
there are about 75,000 <em>single detached properties</em> in Vancouver, it is fair to assume that there are significantly more
than 75,000 households living on these properties once we account for secondary suites and laneway houses.</p>

<h3>Zoning</h3>

<p><a href="http://vancouver.ca/files/cov/Zoning-Map-Vancouver.pdf" target="_blank"><img  src="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/images/zoning_van_pdf.png" style="width:50%;float:right;margin-left:10px;"></a>
Vancouver is divided up into zones that determine what can (and cannot) be legally built on the land.
If one is primarily concerned with the area of land that where only single detached houses can be built, then zoning is
the right metric to look at.</p>

<p>There are two zones that essentially only allow single family houses as residential properties, the RS zones and,
to some extent, First Shaughnessy. Each of these has it&rsquo;s own pitfalls. The first issue is that parks are generally zoned
RS, but one cannot build single family homes in parks. Moreover, while RS does not allow residential land uses other
than single detached houses, it does allow for other land uses, like parks, schools, assisted living and other institutional
uses. So RS zoned land area is a poor proxy for the question of where single family houses could be built. At the very
<a href="https://mountainmath.ca/map/assessment?zoom=13&lat=49.2517&lng=-123.1232&layer=6" target="_blank"><img  src="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/images/zoning_van.png" style="width:50%;float:left;margin-right:10px;"></a>
least we should exclude parks from the equation, but probably also schools and other institutional land uses. After all,
it is delusional to think that even if a school were to close down and the land be sold for development that single
detached dwelling would be built on that land. Next comes the question if we should only include the lots that single
family homes could be built on, or also include the surrounding roads. After all, the roads are needed to serve the lots.
But they also serve the schools and parks, so maybe only a certain portion of the roads should be included? It gets messy,
the second image shows only non-institutional and non-park properties (no roads) coloured by zone, interactive version
<a href="http://mountainmath.ca/map/assessment?zoom=14&amp;lat=49.2517&amp;lng=-123.1232&amp;layer=6">here</a>.</p>

<p>The numbers between 70% and 56% mentioned up top are (probably) derived using some version of zoned area, possibly excluding
parks or schools for some, but including roads within RS zoning. It is easy to underestimate
the space roads take up in the City of Vancouver, overall roads right of ways make up 28% of City of Vancouver land.</p>

<p>At the end of this though process, we are starting to gravitate away from zoning and toward land use.</p>

<h3>Land Use</h3>

<p>We can simplify the discussion by asking how much space currently is taken up by single family properties. The answer
to this is 33%. I have previously written about the
<a href="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2016/02/29/land-use/">land use breakdown</a> for Metro Vancouver municipalities, but
single detached homes were not broken out separately, single detached and duplex properties combined take up 34% of
Vancouver&rsquo;s land. One can play the numbers a little more, maybe only look at single detached properties within RS zoning.
That puts the number at 28%. Throw in Shaugnessy and it rises to 29%. Recall that this excludes roads right of way.</p>

<p><a href="https://mountainmath.ca/land_use/map?zoom=13&lat=49.2544&lng=-123.1268&mu_filter=[%22VA%22]&lu_filter_n=[]" target="_blank"><img  src="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/images/land_use_van.png" style="width:50%;float:right;margin-left:10px;"></a>
Here is an interactive (data-heavy) map that shows the land use for
<a href="https://mountainmath.ca/land_use/map?zoom=13&amp;lat=49.2544&amp;lng=-123.1268&amp;mu_filter=[%22VA%22]&amp;lu_filter_n=[]">just for the City of Vancouver (plus Musqueam 2)</a>.</p>

<h3>Multi-Unit Housing</h3>

<p>One can ask the same question about other housing types, and we can read off the numbers from the
<a href="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2016/02/29/land-use/">land use breakdown</a>. 3.2% of land is taken up with low rise
apartments, 1.9% with townhouses, 1.2% with high rise, 0.3% by non-market housing, 0.9% by mixed use low rise and 0.7%
by mixed use high rise. Adding all of this up we get that 8.2% of land is taken up by housing that is not single detached
or duplex. And it also includes some commercial space in the mixed use developments.</p>

<p>That means that overall in Vancouver 42.2% of the land is used for residential purposes, 81% of which is occupied by
single detached and duplex properties and the remaining 19% is occupied by all other building forms.</p>

<h3>Share of Households in Different Land Uses</h3>

<p>We may be interested in the population density these different land use patterns entail. That&rsquo;s where things get a little
tricky, we will turn to the census for answers. From the standard census releases we can only discern the share of
dwellings that are single detached and duplex properties combined, and that number is 93,370 dwelling units. Overall
there are 264,575 dwelling units, so single family and duplex units make up 35% of all dwelling units in CoV. Glossing
over the issue that some of these may not be occupied we conclude that 35% of all households live on single family and
duplex properties making up 81% of Vancouver&rsquo;s residential land,
while the remaining 65% of households live on 19% of the residential land.</p>

<h3>Fine Print</h3>

<p>There are a number of issues with the data that might change the numbers slightly, but not by much. The first is that
the land use dataset I use lump the City of Vancouver together with Musqueam 2. That slightly changes the land use mix
and areas reported, but the effect on all numbers mentioned here is very small. Next up is the number of dwelling units
on single detached or duplex properties. The census number is likely to under report some secondary suites (although it
captures more than BCAssessment does), and properties with more than one secondary suite (so some illegal suites) will
show up as an apartment building in census data. Moreover, the census data is from 2011, the land use data we used is
about a year old, and we have manually adjusted for some recent upzoning. So there is some give or take in the numbers,
I would not expect more than a one percent move in the numbers I reported as a result.</p>

<h3>Further Questions</h3>

<p>This does not answer the question what percentage of the population lives on single family or duplex properties. To
estimate that one would have to first estimate the number of people per houshold for the different land uses, as we
expect them to differ significantly. One can start exploring how the number of people per dwelling unit varies
<a href="https://censusmapper.ca/maps/391">on CensusMapper</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[FSR]]></title>
    <link href="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2016/05/20/density/"/>
    <updated>2016-05-20T22:51:29-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2016/05/20/density</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="https://mountainmath.ca/map/assessment?layer=16" target="_blank"><img  src="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/images/fsr.png" style="width:50%;float:right;margin-left:10px;"></a>
Ever since I played with the <a href="http://mountainmath.ca/vancouver_lidar/map">LIDAR-generated building height data</a> I thought
that I should use that to map gross floor area (GFA) and floor space ratio (FSR). Gross floor area is the total floor area
inside the building envelope. So for a three storey building, it is the area of the footprint times three.
Floor space ratio is the GFA divided by the area of the parcel it sits on. There are several reasons why this may be
interesting.</p>

<p>GFA is the currency of the developer. Especially once we enter the world of apartment or commercial buildings,
gross floor area is directly proportional to the amount of money a developer can charge for a property, either when stratified
and sold or when rented out.</p>

<p>FSR on the other hand is a measure of density, and it is the currency of the zoning code. Height and site coverage are
also regulated in the zoning code and there is an obvious relationship to FSR. But because GFA is so important to the
developer, FSR usually receives more attention in public discussions.</p>

<p>Read on or <a href="https://mountainmath.ca/map/assessment?layer=16" target="_blank" class='btn btn-default'>head straight for the interactive map</a> to browse
Vancouver by FSR. Read the disclaimer at the bottom before using any data for purposes other than general reference.</p>

<!-- more -->


<h3>Maximum Allowable FSR and Spot Zoning.</h3>

<p>The maximum allowable FSR is set by the zoning code. Because land is so valuable in Vancouver, most people will try
to maximize GFA when building a new building, so they typically go right up to the maximum allowable FSR. Previously we have
<a href="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2016/03/05/physical-sfh-form-over-time/">examined the effects of various related metrics like height and site coverage</a>
for single family homes.</p>

<p><a href="https://mountainmath.ca/map/assessment?zoom=15&lat=49.2599&lng=-123.1583&layer=6" target="_blank"><img  src="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/images/spot-zoning.png" style="width:30%;float:right;margin-left:10px;"></a>
At least this is how it works for RS/RT zones. If you are looking to develop a different property, say a mixed use or
an apartment building or commercial building you will probably be looking to up-zone. That is, you will try to convince
the city (and the local population) to allow you to build more GFA than zoning would allow. If successful the city will
create a new zone just for your property and ask for some compensation in form of CACs (aiming to recoup about 80% of the
uplift in value the up-zoning creates) in return. That process is called
spot zoning and it can be seen in form of the little &ldquo;Comprehensive Development&rdquo; zones that are visible as yellow
sprinkles in the otherwise quite uniform zones on the map.</p>

<p>In reality the process of up-zoning a property is a lot more complex, arduous and time consuming, which favours larger
developers with deep pockets that can take the risk and sit out the long process of eventually obtaining higher GFA. One
of the many reasons why the &ldquo;missing middle&rdquo; is missing.</p>

<h3>Mapping Density</h3>

<p><a href="https://censusmapper.ca/maps/302#16/49.2375/-123.1573" target="_blank"><img  src="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/images/kerrisdale_people.png" style="width:30%;float:left;margin-right:10px;"></a>
From Census data we know the <a href="https://censusmapper.ca/maps/302">nighttime density</a>, that is where people live and sleep.
But we don&rsquo;t know where they are
during the daytime.</p>

<p><a href="https://mountainmath.ca/map/assessment?zoom=16&lat=49.238&lng=-123.154&layer=16" target="_blank"><img  src="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/images/kerrisdale_fsr.png" style="width:30%;float:right;margin-left:10px;"></a>
FSR is also often seen as such a measure of density, although it only focuses on density on property parcels and neglects
all the space between parcels, like roads right of ways and parks.</p>

<p>In mostly residential neighbourhoods the two densities correspond quite closely, but in areas with large commercial buildings
(nighttime) population density can be quite low while FSR is very high as can easily be seen by comparing the two maps.</p>

<p><a href="https://mountainmath.ca/assessment_gl/map?zoom=16&lat=49.2384&lng=-123.1567" target="_blank"><img  src="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/images/kerrisdale_tax.png" style="width:30%;float:left;margin-right:10px;"></a>
<a href="https://mountainmath.ca/assessment_gl/map">Tax density</a>, that is property taxes collected per area, give another view of
&ldquo;density&rdquo; in the city that highlights relative property values and emphasises commercial land use that pays five times
the residential tax rate.</p>

<p>There are lots of other measures of density that are important for different purposes, for example <a href="http://mountainmath.ca/census3">household density</a>
(in full 3D, requires modern computer),
<a href="https://censusmapper.ca/maps/359">the density of private dwelling units</a> or <a href="https://censusmapper.ca/maps/35">toddler density</a> just to name a few.</p>

<h3>Next Steps</h3>

<p>There are several directions I want to take this. Now that FSR is available for all properties, I can
compare purpose built rental buildings to strata buildings. For example, in my
<a href="http://mountainmath.ca/assessment/split_map">Buildings and Dirt map</a> I can&rsquo;t integrate purpose
built rentals because I don&rsquo;t know how many rental units they have. The assessment data from the Vancouver Open Data portal,
does not have that information, and BC Assessment won&rsquo;t share it (in a hassle-free way). But I can make a similar map based on GFA instead of
number of units and examine
how GFA effect land and building values across different land uses. And in many ways GFA may be a better unit for comparisons
than number of suites.</p>

<p><a href="https://mountainmath.ca/map/assessment?zoom=13&lat=49.2488&lng=-123.1211&layer=17&filter=res" target="_blank"><img  src="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/images/value_per_gfa.png" style="width:50%;float:right;margin-left:10px;"></a>
Or I can just make a <a href="https://mountainmath.ca/map/assessment?zoom=14&amp;lat=49.2684&amp;lng=-123.1354&amp;layer=17">straight-up map of total assessed value per GFA</a>.
And maybe add a filter to only show this for <a href="https://mountainmath.ca/map/assessment?zoom=13&amp;lat=49.2488&amp;lng=-123.1211&amp;layer=17&amp;filter=res">residential and mixed use units</a>
like in the image if that&rsquo;s what we are interested in.</p>

<p>Another interesting application is to use this data to do something along the lines of this
<a href="http://www.nytimes.com/interactive/2016/05/19/upshot/forty-percent-of-manhattans-buildings-could-not-be-built-today.html?_r=0">excellent analysis the New York Times published</a>
for Vancouver. FSR, next to building heights and lot coverage that I
<a href="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2016/03/05/physical-sfh-form-over-time/">have already analysed from a different angle</a>,
is an important metric to detect buildings that could not be rebuilt under regular zoning.</p>

<p>Lastly, having data on building GFA, together with assessment open data, allows for reverse-engineering of the GFA of individual
strata units. That makes the analysis of condo assessment data more meaningful as we can analyse assessed condo values by
unit size. One of the reasons why we are only talking about single family homes (or in some cases RS zoned homes) and
not condos is that it is very easy to compare single family homes. But comparing condos doesn&rsquo;t make much sense unless
one also has data on the size of each condo. And this has probably focused the public debate too much on single family
homes when we should be paying a lot more attention to condos. And purpose built rental units.</p>

<h3>Disclaimer</h3>

<p>The FSR was estimated using coarse building data extracted from LIDAR data. The motivation was to use the FSR for aggregate
analysis and not for getting accurate estimates of individual buildings.</p>

<p>Secondary buildings like garages or laneway houses are only inconsistently detected and mapped. The data is from 2009,
buildings built after that are greyed out.</p>

<p>The algorithm to compute FSR
from this building data is rather crude and only makes rudimentary attempts to adjust for varying floor heights of buildings
different for land uses, overhangs and eyebrows and dealing with pitched roofs or mechanical units.</p>

<p>Building data was clipped to property polygons to deal with cases of buildings spanning several legal lots or not properly
separated.</p>

<p>The FSR computed only roughly resembles the FSR defined in building codes. In particular our model with grossly
overestimate the FSR for buildings with overhanging features like
the Lookout on the Harbour Centre.</p>

<p>Block level aggregates will underestimate FSR in the presence of properties excluded from the FSR calculation.</p>

<p>Do not be use the FSR estimates as an authoritative source for any individual building FSR.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Physical SFH Form Over Time]]></title>
    <link href="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2016/03/05/physical-sfh-form-over-time/"/>
    <updated>2016-03-05T22:58:06-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2016/03/05/physical-sfh-form-over-time</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I was curious how the physical parameters of Single Family Houses changed over time.</p>

<p>Using the <a href="https://mountainmath.ca/map/assessment">assessment dataset</a> merged with the <a href="https://mountainmath.ca/land_use/map">land use dataset</a>
allows to fairly accurately pick out single family houses, and also holds the age of most properies. Together with
the City of Vancouver LIDAR-generated building dataset <a href="https://mountainmath.ca/vancouver_lidar/map">that I have played with before</a>
we can look at physical building parameters.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>The city dataset is a little coarse, it only contains the main building and does not map things like garages. It&rsquo;s a little
rough and should probably be interpreted cautiously on an individual building level. One could spend the time and derive the
building data directly from the raw LIDAR dataset optimized for this purpose, but for some overview statistics the building
dataset that was derived by the city is just fine. The LIDAR was taken in 2009, so we only consider houses built before that time.</p>

<h3>Site coverage</h3>

<p>One question is how the site coverage of the buildings have changed over time. We simply line up the buildings by the year
they were built, compute the site coverage of the main building relative to the parcel size and graph the quintiles for
each year. For good measure, we throw in the 10 and 90 percentile whiskers.</p>

<div style="margin:10px 50px;padding:5px;border: 1px solid black;border-radius:5px;" class="whiskers">
<div id="sfh_coverage" style="height:200px;max-width:640px;" data-url="/data/sfh_coverage.json"></div>
<div class="legend no-margin" style="padding-bottom:2em;">
</div>
</div>


<p>What jumps out immediately is that around 1988 there apparently was a change in zoning law that reduced site coverage
of the main building. <strike>I don&rsquo;t know anything about the history of building codes, maybe someone that does could shed some
light onto this.</strike> <a href="https://twitter.com/BrendanDawe/status/706737206484795392">Twitter was fast to provide the answer</a>
it appears that changes in building code were implemented to counteract the growing footprint of houses at the time, details
can be found in <a href="https://open.library.ubc.ca/cIRcle/collections/ubctheses/831/items/1.0086386">Barbara Pettit&rsquo;s Ph.D. thesis</a>.</p>

<h3>Building Height</h3>

<p>The next obvious point of analysis is how building height, in meters, changed over time.</p>

<div style="margin:10px 50px;padding:5px;border: 1px solid black;border-radius:5px;" class="whiskers">
<div id="sfh_height" style="height:200px;max-width:640px;" data-url="/data/sfh_height.json"></div>
<div class="legend no-margin" style="padding-bottom:2em;">
</div>
</div>


<p>We observe a similar jump in the data around 1988, with building height jumping up as site coverage decreases.</p>

<h3>Building Volumes</h3>

<p>Now let&rsquo;s look at how &ldquo;massive&rdquo; the buildings are, measured by volume in cubic metres.</p>

<div style="margin:10px 50px;padding:5px;border: 1px solid black;border-radius:5px;" class="whiskers">
<div id="sfh_volume" style="height:200px;max-width:640px;" data-url="/data/sfh_volume.json"></div>
<div class="legend no-margin" style="padding-bottom:2em;">
</div>
</div>


<p>The graph does show that in general houses have gotten more massive starting in the late 80s, but after that have more or less
maintained the same volume. It shows that the combined effect of the regulation change in the late 80s that resulted in
smaller building footprints and taller buildings was that buildings overall got bulkier.</p>

<h3>Roof Type</h3>

<p>Lastly we see how the roof type changes over time, plotting the number of buildings with given roof type for each year.</p>

<div style="margin:10px 50px;padding:5px;border: 1px solid black;border-radius:5px;" class="whiskers">
<div id="sfh_roof" style="height:200px;max-width:640px;" data-url="/data/sfh_roof.json"></div>
<div class="legend no-margin" style="padding-bottom:2em;">
</div>
</div>


<p>Flat roofs seem to have been quite popular between the mid 60s to mid 80s.</p>

<h3>Length to Width Ratio (Update)</h3>

<p>A question about a regulation change in 1938 <a href="https://twitter.com/GRIDSVancouver/status/706879555550613504">came up on Twitter</a>,
so I thought I should check into the length-to-width ratio to see if anything can be seen there. A ratio of 1
would mean a square footprint, a ratio of 2 means the house is twice as long as wide.</p>

<div style="margin:10px 50px;padding:5px;border: 1px solid black;border-radius:5px;" class="whiskers">
<div id="sfh_square" style="height:200px;max-width:640px;" data-url="/data/sfh_square.json"></div>
<div class="legend no-margin" style="padding-bottom:2em;">
</div>
</div>


<p>No obvious changes around 1938, but our houses became a lot more square after the late 80s zoning changes.</p>

<h3>Next Steps</h3>

<p>After starting to see what kind of data can be derived from LIDAR data we can start to explore different questions. The
graphs open a small window into the physical parameters of single family homes over time and are only of limited general
interest.</p>

<p>For
more serious analysis we would most likely have to start from the raw LIDAR data, which takes a little bit of effort.</p>

<div><script src="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/javascripts/box.js"></script></div>




<script>

function stacked_bar_graph(div,shiftAxis,domainFormatter,rangeFormatter,domainLabelFormatter){
    if (!domainFormatter) domainFormatter=d3.format("d")
    if (!rangeFormatter)
     rangeFormatter = function (y) {
        return y;
     };
     if (!domainLabelFormatter) domainLabelFormatter=domainFormatter;

var margin = {top: 20, right: 20, bottom: 40, left: 70},
    width = parseInt(div.style("width")) - margin.left - margin.right,
    height = parseInt(div.style("height")) - margin.top - margin.bottom;

var x = d3.scale.ordinal()
    .rangeRoundBands([0, width], .1);

var y = d3.scale.linear()
    .range([height, 0]);


var xAxis = d3.svg.axis()
    .scale(x)
    .tickFormat(domainFormatter)
    .orient("bottom");


var yAxis = d3.svg.axis()
    .scale(y)
    .orient("left")
    .tickFormat(rangeFormatter)
    .ticks(5, rangeFormatter);

var svg = div.append("svg")
    .attr("width", width + margin.left + margin.right)
    .attr("height", height + margin.top + margin.bottom)
  .append("g")
    .attr("transform", "translate(" + margin.left + "," + margin.top + ")");

var data_url=div[0][0].dataset.url;
var legend=d3.select(div.node().parentNode).select('.legend');


d3.json(data_url, function(error, json) {
  if (error) throw error;
  var graphData=json[0];
  var data=graphData.data;
  var color = d3.scale.ordinal().domain(graphData.colors.map(function(d,i){return i}))
  .range(graphData.colors);
  var domain=data.map(function(d){return d.date;});
  x.domain(domain);

  function graphValueId(i){
      return graphData.class + '_' + i + '_value'
  }

  graphData.labels.forEach(function(text,i){
    var color=graphData.colors[i];
    var html='<i style="background:' + color + '"></i> ' + text + ' <span style="float:right;margin-right:10px;" id="' + graphValueId(i) + '"></span>'
    legend.append('p').html(html);
  });
  
  data.forEach(function(d) {
      var y0 = 0;
      d.values = color.domain().map(function(i) { return {date: d.date, y0: y0, y1: y0 += +d.count[i]}; });
      d.total = d.values[d.values.length - 1].y1;
  });
  y.domain([0, d3.max(data, function(d) { return d.total; })]);

  var domainTickValues=[];
  var skip=Math.round(40/x.rangeBand());
  if (skip<=0) skip=1;
  for (var i=0;i<x.domain().length;i++) {
    if (i % skip==0) domainTickValues.push(x.domain()[i]);
  }
  if (x.domain().length % 5 !=0) domainTickValues.push(x.domain()[x.domain().length-1]);
  xAxis.tickValues(domainTickValues);

  var xShift=shiftAxis ?  x.rangeBand()/2.0 * 1.1 : 0;
  
  svg.append("g")
      .attr("class", "x axis")
      .attr("transform", "translate(" + xShift + "," + height + ")")
      .call(xAxis);

  svg.append("g")
      .attr("class", "y axis")
      .call(yAxis);
//    .append("text")
//      .attr("transform", "rotate(-90)")
//      .attr("y", 6)
//      .attr("dy", ".71em")
//      .style("text-anchor", "end")
//      .text("Probability");

    function updateTooltip(d,i){
       color.domain().forEach(function(j){
             var value=d && i==j ? (domainLabelFormatter(d.date) + ': ' +rangeFormatter(d.y1-d.y0)) : '';
             d3.select('#'+graphValueId(j)).text( value);
       });
    }

  var year=svg.selectAll(".year")
    .data(data)
        .enter().append("g")
          .attr("class", "g");
  year.selectAll(".color-bar")
      .data(function(d) { return d.values; })
    .enter().append("rect")
      .attr("class", graphData.class + " color-bar")
      .attr("fill", graphData.color)
      .attr("x", function(d) { return x(d.date); })
      .attr("width", x.rangeBand())
      .attr("y", function(d) { return y(d.y1); })
      .attr("height", function(d) { return Math.max(0, y(d.y0) - y(d.y1)); })
      .attr("fill",function(d,i) {return color(i);})
      .on('mouseover',updateTooltip)
      .on('click',updateTooltip)
      .on('touch',updateTooltip) 
      .on('mouseout',function(){updateTooltip(null,i)});

      
});

}

var yearFormatter=d3.format();
stacked_bar_graph(d3.select("#sfh_roof"),true,yearFormatter,null,yearFormatter);
</script>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Property Taxes and Land Use]]></title>
    <link href="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2016/03/02/property-taxes-and-land-use/"/>
    <updated>2016-03-02T20:42:02-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2016/03/02/property-taxes-and-land-use</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Since I started thinking about <a href="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2015/05/31/density-in-vancouver/">tax density</a>,
the amount of property taxes collected per area, I always felt that the data presentation in the map fell short.</p>

<p>Property taxes are somewhat insulated from the ups and downs of the real estate market as they are need-based and the mill
rate changes to flatten out the crazyness of the market. But what they lack in interesting patterns over time they more than
makes up for in interesting patterns in space.</p>

<p>To recognize these spacial patterns, one needs to switch layers in my
<a href="https://mountainmath.ca/map/assessment?zoom=14&amp;lat=49.2741&amp;lng=-123.1321&amp;layer=10">assessment maps</a> and that&rsquo;s
a little awkward and most people won&rsquo;t do this.</p>

<p>I can&rsquo;t remember where I first saw some 3D data visualization around something like this, maybe in
<a href="http://www.strongtowns.org/journal/2015/11/18/mapping-the-effects-of-parking-minimums">this excellent Strong Towns post</a> that
explores tax density and parking.
When I was chatting with <a href="https://twitter.com/dnproulx">Darren Proulx</a> about this I realized this is the perfect case
to rev up <a href="https://mapzen.com">Mapzen&rsquo;s awesone 3D map engine</a> for data visualization. Previously I had tried out the 3D
mapping capabilities to map
<a href="https://mountainmath.ca/vancouver_lidar/map">the physical form of Vancouver&rsquo;s buildings obtained from LIDAR data</a>,
now it was time to map abstract data in 3D.</p>

<!-- more -->


<h3>3D Tax Density Maps</h3>

<p><a href="https://mountainmath.ca/assessment_gl/map?zoom=14&lat=49.2814&lng=-123.1312" target="_blank"><img  src="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/images/tax_density.png" style="width:50%;float:left;margin-right:10px;"></a>
The spacial patterns of tax density are closely related to zoning, so the obvious thing to do is to map both at the same
time. Tax density as the height and the zoning as the colour. But the relation between tax density and zoning is indirect,
it is given through land use. So when I
<a href="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2016/01/31/land-use/">folded the Metro Vancouver land use dataset into the asessment data</a>
I added another option to colour the map by land use. And the visualization works pretty well to show the relationship
between the variables.
Check out the <a class='btn' href="https://mountainmath.ca/assessment_gl/map?zoom=14&lat=49.2814&lng=-123.1312" target="_blank">interactive map</a>.</p>

<h3>Some Quick Observations</h3>

<p>When comparing this to the <a href="http://www.strongtowns.org/journal/2015/11/18/mapping-the-effects-of-parking-minimums">Strong Towns post</a>
mentioned above it is interesting to note that the &ldquo;tax contribution of bare pavement&rdquo; is actually quite high relative to
many other commercial properties. For example, the giant parking lot around Safeway on 10th near UBC can&rsquo;t be discerned
from the map. Similarly, Oakridge Mall does not stand out as a low tax area. That&rsquo;s basically because in today&rsquo;s property
market the value of the property is dictated by the land value and few properties, even few commercial properties outside
of downtown, have building values in the same order of magnitude as the land value.</p>

<p>And that keeps the pressure on to redevelop the low building value commercial stock, typically replacing it with mixed use.
One example is the Safeway on Granville and 70th, that went from parking lot to mixed use. The high land values make this
kind of redevelopment attractive. Typically this redevelopment process will raise commercial rents, lower commercial
property taxes, add housing supply and increase tax density.</p>

<p><a href="https://mountainmath.ca/assessment_gl/map?zoom=16&lat=49.2433&lng=-123.151" target="_blank"><img  src="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/images/triangle.png" style="width:50%;float:right;margin-left:10px;"></a>
Another interesting area is the
<a href="https://mountainmath.ca/assessment_gl/map?zoom=16&lat=49.2433&lng=-123.151" target="_blank">condo/apartment triangle at Arbutus and 33rd</a>.
These condos/apartments abut Quilchena Park, have a grocery store in proximity but otherwise sit in a see of single family housing.
I would like to highlight two alternative development models. One is the single family housing that surrounds this area,
the other is one where one takes the condo/apartment complex and throws in the adjacent Quilchena Park. The park does not
house any people and does not generate tax revenue but provides great recreational value. Overall, the tax density, that is the
amount of taxes collected per area, of those two models are the same. So the condo complex together with the entire park
collects the same amount of taxes per area as single family housing. On the other hand, the condo complex plus park houses
3 to 4 times as many people per (combined) area as the surrounding single family housing.</p>

<p>Presenting these as alternative
development models one can ask how many people would prefer condo (and one dedicated rental building) plus park over
single family housing without park.
Condo values range between $448k to $2.6m with median of $745k. 56% of all units have 2 bedrooms, 9% with 3 bedrooms.
The surrounding single family housing start at
around $2.5m for a teardown. My guess is that there are more people interested in the condo plus park model than the
current Vancouver market offers.</p>

<h3>More Detailed Analysis</h3>

<p>Now let&rsquo;s take the tax density information and measure it against city services rendered. In other words, let&rsquo;s see who
pays their &ldquo;fair share&rdquo; of property taxes. Well, that&rsquo;s where I ran out of juice. There is lots of
work involved to do it right, too much to fit into my evening side project time budget.</p>

<p>Some have done some
<a href="http://mapstoryblog.thenittygritty.org/costofstreets/">really amazing work</a> trying to understand the give and take of
property taxes and services rendered, to the bar is pretty high.</p>

<p>Vancouver&rsquo;s situation, with the commercial property tax 5x the residential rate, has it&rsquo;s own quirks to add to the
complexity.</p>

<p>If someone is interested in spending the time to sieve through the city budget and process the data I would be happy to help out
with graphing and mapping. As long as the data is clean enough that it stays under my &ldquo;one evening side project time budget&rdquo;. :-)</p>

<h3>Looking Forward</h3>

<p>General public awareness about taxes, zoning and fairness seem to be rising. Recently a
<a href="http://www.capitalnewyork.com/article/city-hall/2014/02/8540903/lawsuit-claims-discrimination-real-estate-taxes">class action alleging discrimination in New York&rsquo;s property tax code</a>
was launched. An interesting precedent, and it will be interesting to watch the outcome.
And to see how this could apply to the tax and services balance
of low density vs high density. Or exclusionary zoning policies as the motor of unequal tax density.
Or minimum parking requirements which <a href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/news/in-theory/wp/2016/03/03/how-parking-requirements-hurt-the-poor/">disproportionally hurt poor people</a>.</p>

<p>As this kind of data becomes more publicly accessible and better visualizations make this complex issue more
accessible I expect these kind of questions to gain more traction.</p>

<hr>


<h5>I can&rsquo;t view the 3D map!</h5>

<p>Sorry. Welcome to the world of modern web technology. (WebGL in this case.) If you try to look at the interactive map and don&rsquo;t see anything like the image above, then that&rsquo;s probably because
you either have and old (windows?) computer and/or an old (Internet Explorer) browser. If switching to Chrome or Firefox does
not fix this for you your best option is to cramp that map into your phone screen. Your phone is probably newer and supports
modern web technology much better than your computer. Or you can always view the 2D maps linked above.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
