<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: census | Mountain Doodles]]></title>
  <link href="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/categories/census/feed.atom" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/"/>
  <updated>2017-03-06T22:45:22-08:00</updated>
  <id>http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[MountainMath]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[RS Population Change]]></title>
    <link href="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2017/03/06/rs-population-change/"/>
    <updated>2017-03-06T11:06:57-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2017/03/06/rs-population-change</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="https://censusmapper.ca/maps/583"><img src="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/images/pop_change_ct.png" style="width:50%;float:right;margin-left:10px;"></a>
With reporting on the new census numbers gaining traction, and now
<a href="http://www.cbc.ca/news/canada/british-columbia/gregor-robertson-statement-vancouver-character-homes-review-1.4011100">Mayor Robertson</a>
picking up on single family neighbourhoods losing population we thought
it is time to crunch some numbers.</p>

<!-- more -->


<h3>Comparing Censuses</h3>

<p>Comparing data across censuses is hard. For one, definitions change from one census to the next
and thus variables aren&rsquo;t always comparable. Four our immediate goal of comparing
population, private dwellings, and private households between the 2011 and 2016 censuses
that is not a concern.</p>

<p>Comparing data is relatively easy when census geographies are large (i.e. CT, CSD level or higher)
and the census geography matches exactly the area that we are interested in. For CSDs (Municipalities)
this is often the case, but at the sub-municipal level, the CTs (Census Tracts) or other sub-municipal
aggregation levels rarely line up with the regions one is interested in.</p>

<p>For example, if one is interested in changes in population in RS (single family zoned) neighbourhoods in
Vancouver, looking at selected CTs will only give some initial indication. The reason is that
there is actually no CT in the City of Vancouver that is entirely RS zoned. There are several that
come close (the closest one is CT 9330015.01 around 41st and Thyne, which actually
increased population from 5,364 in 2011 to 5,485 in 2016) but it shows how tricky
it is to answer the really simple question how the population changed in RS neighbourhoods.</p>

<p>Just glossing over this and only looking at CTs that are mostly RS zoned is tempting,
but may well result in misleading results, like we have seen in recent reporting on
unoccupied dwellings in the &ldquo;Marine Gateway neighbourhood&rdquo;.</p>

<p>So how to avoid this? The cleanest way is a custom tabulation from StatCan, but that takes
time, costs money, and may still
<a href="https://twitter.com/vb_jens/status/838561779970011136">result in problems when data was not geocoded correctly</a>,
which is next to impossible to detect in custom tabulations.</p>

<p>An alternative way is to compare censuses at finer aggregation levels, that is at DAs (Dissemination Areas) or
DBs (Dissemination Blocks).</p>

<h3>Comparing Censuses at DA or DB levels</h3>

<p>For our concrete example, that means we look for DBs within RS zoning and work with these.</p>

<p>There are several difficulties with this approach. The most important is that the finer data we look at,
the more likely we pick up problems with Census data (yes, there are problems) and mistake them for real world data.
For our case through, we can avoid some of that by aggregating over all DBs within RS zoning to even out some
of these issues. Morever, we can visually inspect the data to look for any particular DB that seems to be problematic
and do some ground-truthing to see if the issues are only in the data or actually on the ground.</p>

<p>The next difficulty is technical in nature. Census geographies, including DBs and DAs, can change from one census to
another and thus may not be comparable. In order to get reliable results we need to make sure that we work with
a common set of geographies for both the 2011 and 2016 censuses. Luckily this is only a technical problem that can be
overcome as census geographies don&rsquo;t just change randomly but still retain some basic comparability.</p>

<p>So we got to work and wrote some scripts that take the geographies for two particular censuses at a given aggregation
level and we create a &ldquo;least common denominator&rdquo; tiling that combines 2011 and 2016 DBs and DAs until they match up. At
CensusMapper we work with &ldquo;cartographic&rdquo; DBs (so we clip our major bodies of water), which leads to a minor issue where
between 2011 and 2016 things were clipped slightly differently which yielded two DBs in 2011 (with 16 and 17 people in it)
being clipped out (and having no people in it) in 2017, likely a combination of adjusting some tolerances in the StatCan
algorithms as well as some minor changes in geocoding that moved the population into an adjacent DB
(like e.g. happened with 59150971009 and 59150971008 south of King Edward split along Camarvon). Apart from that, the
result is a tiling of Canada by DB and DA-based geographies that allow for consistent comparisons across the two censuses.</p>

<p>In numbers there were 493,192 cartographic DBs in 2016, 489,676 in 2016, and these resulted in a least common denominator tiling
by 445,953 DB-based geographies.</p>

<h3>RS, RT and FSD Zones and Population Change</h3>

<p><img src="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/images/filter_all.png" style="width:50%;float:right;margin-left:10px;">
Back to our original question, how did population change in RS zoning. Before we go there, we think it makes more sense to expand
the question to ask for RS, RT (duplex) and FSD (First Shaughnessy) combined as these are about equally restrictive in what
we allow there.</p>

<p>Grabbing the <a href="http://data.vancouver.ca/datacatalogue/zoning.htm">latest available zoning data</a> and uploading it to
CensusMapper makes it easy to download the 2011 and 2016 dissemination blocks that intersect RS, RT and FSD zoning. We removed the RS part
that snakes along the downtown beaches and covers Stanley Park, as well as the sliver creaping up False Creek and covering the marinas there.</p>

<p>When we intersect the census data with the zones, we also compute the overlap each DB has with the zoning and disregard any region
with less than 10% overlap. Moreover we divide the dissemination blocks into <bf>core</bf> blocks where
the overlap is greater than 99% and <bf>fringe</bf> blocks, where the overlap is less than 99%.</p>

<p>Here are the results:</p>

<pre><code>RS, RT, FSD
core: 236 DB, fringe: 475 DB
Population 2011 - 2016
core pop change: -69, fringe pop change: 6673, core total pop: 124916, fringe total pop: 284231
Dwellings 2011 - 2016
core dw change: 2812, fringe dw change: 7142, core total dw: 47008, fringe total dw: 121488
Households 2011 - 2016
core hh change: 1194, fringe hh change: 5127, core total hh: 42298, fringe total hh: 111801
</code></pre>

<p><img src="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/images/filter_core.png" style="width:50%;float:right;margin-left:10px;">
What we see is that the population in the &ldquo;core&rdquo; DBs did drop. Slightly. At the same time the number of dwellings
increased quite noticeably by 6.3% in the core, with essentially all of the dwelling growth located within RS zones
(as opposed to RT and FSD). So most of that dwelling
growth is due to suites and laneway houses. Note that we only capture 47008 dwellings in the &ldquo;core&rdquo; RS, RT, FSD areas,
which is less
than half of the dwelling units in RS, RT and FSD with the remaining dwellings are located within the &ldquo;fringe&rdquo; regions.</p>

<p><a href="https://censusmapper.ca/maps/596"><img src="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/images/van_pop_comp.png" style="width:50%;left:right;margin-right:10px;"></a>
Interestingly, the number of households grew much slower than the number of dwellings in the &ldquo;core&rdquo; regions, increasing the rate
of unoccupied units from 7% to 10%. Following our decomposition of population growth <a href="https://censusmapper.ca/maps/596">mapped here</a>
and <a href="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2017/02/10/2016-census-data/">explained in more detail in a previous post</a>, we see
that the population growth of -69 in the &ldquo;core&rdquo; regions can be decomposed into:</p>

<ul>
<li>-3,699 due to declining household size,</li>
<li>-4,321 due to increase in unoccupied dwellings, and</li>
<li>7,952 due to increase in dwelling units.</li>
</ul>


<p><img src="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/images/filter_fringe.png" style="width:50%;float:right;margin-left:10px;">
We can do the same analysis for the &ldquo;fringe&rdquo; areas, where RS, RT and FSD zoning mixes with other zones. Here we get a population
increase by 2.4%, driven by an increase
in dwelling units by 6.2%, and dampened by shrinking household size and a
more modest increase in the rate of unoccupied units from 6.7% in 2011 to 8% in 2016. We note that
the rate of unoccupied units increased significantly less on the fringe when compared to the core.</p>

<p>Breaking up the population growth of 6,673 people as before we have:</p>

<ul>
<li>-6,667 due to declining household size,</li>
<li>-3,996 due to increase in unoccupied dwellings, and</li>
<li>17,336 due to increase in dwelling units.</li>
</ul>


<p>Lastly, we probably can&rsquo;t talk about this without running a separate analysis for the west side. So here we go.</p>

<pre><code>RS, RT, FSD
core: 88 DB, fringe: 184 DB
Population 2011 - 2016
core pop change: -510, fringe pop change: 1631, core total pop: 42878, fringe total pop: 105309
Dwellings 2011 - 2016
core dw change: 572, fringe dw change: 2426, core total dw: 16735, fringe total dw: 49210
Households 2011 - 2016
core hh change: -18, fringe hh change: 1226, core total hh: 15066, fringe total hh: 44907
</code></pre>

<p>We see that this confirms conventional wisdom that the population decline in the core areas of RS, RT, FSD is stronger
on the west side (and in fact population did increase overall in the core areas on the east side). The rate of unoccupied (by usual residents)
units was quite similar to the overall RS, RT, FSD, climbing from 6.7% in 2011 to 10% in 2016.</p>

<p>Again splitting up the population change of -510 people in the &ldquo;core&rdquo; area into components we get:</p>

<ul>
<li>-458 due to declining household size,</li>
<li>-1,587 due to increase in unoccupied dwellings, and</li>
<li>1,535 due to increase in dwelling units.</li>
</ul>


<p>and for the &ldquo;fringe&rdquo; west side areas we again observe that population increased at 1.5%, dwellings by 5.1% and
the rate of unoccupied units grew slower from 6.6% to 8.7% and splitting up the population change of 1,631 people:</p>

<ul>
<li>-1,278 due to declining household size,</li>
<li>-2,466 due to increase in unoccupied dwellings, and</li>
<li>5,376 due to increase in dwelling units.</li>
</ul>


<h3>Summary</h3>

<p>In summary, we see that the growth in the &ldquo;fringe&rdquo; zones of RS, RT and FSD outpaces the &ldquo;core&rdquo; zones, despite the fringes
containing more than half of the RS, RT and FSD dwellings which presumably perform similar to the core zones.</p>

<p>Fringe zones have lower rates of unoccupied (by usual residents) buildings than the core.</p>

<p>Overall, the &ldquo;core&rdquo; regions had a slight decline in population. The west side lost population in the core
at a higher pace than the overall rate.</p>

<h3>Glossary</h3>

<p>We are a little loose with our use of language. In this post &ldquo;unoccupied&rdquo; is always short for &ldquo;not occupied by usual residents&rdquo;,
so in simpler terms &ldquo;not used as primary residence&rdquo;. &ldquo;Occupied&rdquo; refers to &ldquo;used as primary residence&rdquo;.</p>

<p>West side and east side were divided along the longitude for Ontario road.</p>

<p>Core regions are Dissemination Blocks that have at least 99% overlap with RS, RT or FSD zoning.</p>

<p>Fringe regions are Dissemination Blocks that have between 10% and 99% overlap with RS, RT or FSD zoning.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[2016 Census Data - Part 1]]></title>
    <link href="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2017/02/10/2016-census-data/"/>
    <updated>2017-02-10T20:27:10-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2017/02/10/2016-census-data</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="https://censusmapper.ca/maps/583"><img src="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/images/van_pop_change.png" style="width:50%;float:right;margin-left:10px;"></a>
Finally the first batch of 2016 census data has arrived on Tuesday AM and
CensusMapper was updated with the new census numbers by mid-morning.</p>

<p>Dissemination Block data was a little harder to find, but with the help
of some friendly StatCan people I finally managed to locate the data and
add that too this afternoon.</p>

<p>Time for writing up some observations. I am hoping to find time to do
this regularly as more data gets released.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>The first batch of data only comes with three variables: Population, dwellings and households.
And two more, a data quality flag indicating areas with incomplete enumeration and the area of
each geographic region. Area itself is more tricky than it seems at first, one has
to make decisions what to count. Lakes? Rivers? National or Regional Parks?</p>

<p>Next to these variables, we also got the corresponding 2011 population for all geographic
regions at the CT/CSD level and above to aid the comparison, but these
were not available at the DA or DB level.</p>

<p>The variables seem straight forward, but nothing is simple when it comes to big projects like a census,
so it might we worthwhile to spend a little bit of time looking at them.</p>

<h3>Population</h3>

<p><a href="https://censusmapper.ca/maps/591"><img src="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/images/van_pop_density.png" style="width:50%;float:right;margin-left:10px;"></a>
The quintessential census variable counts the number of people in each census region. With the exception
of people that have a primary residence elsewhere in Canada or abroad. There are several reasons for this,
the simples one is to avoid the double-counting of people.</p>

<h3>Dwellings</h3>

<p>&ldquo;Dwellings&rdquo; is short for &ldquo;private dwellings&rdquo;, this does not count collective dwellings
like prisons, student dorms, hospitals or nursery homes or even some coops. This can lead
to interesting situation where there are zero private dwellings (and zero households) but non-zero population.
Metro Vancouver has 45 such dissemination blocks. But these people are
only counted if they don&rsquo;t have a primary residence somewhere else, which
often is the case for students in dorms. But not for all students, as the
Dissemination Block on UBC campus that&rsquo;s wedged between NW Marine, University,
Lower Mall and Agronomy shows.
It has zero dwellings, zero households, but a population of 890 people.</p>

<h3>Households</h3>

<p>The &ldquo;dwellings, occupied by usual residents&rdquo; is also called &ldquo;households&rdquo;. It
refers to a private dwelling that is used as a primary residence, and the inhabitants
make up a household. If inhabitants of a dwelling only live there temporarily and/or has
a primary residence somewhere else in Canada or abroad, then they are not
counted in the population nor the household counts.</p>

<h3>Unoccupied Dwellings</h3>

<p><a href="https://censusmapper.ca/maps/584"><img src="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/images/van_unoccupied.png" style="width:50%;float:left;margin-right:10px;"></a>
The difference between dwellings and households is &ldquo;dwellings, not occupied by usual residents&rdquo;. Essentially, that&rsquo;s
dwellings that are not used as primary residences. It&rsquo;s a fun variable to look at, and it
is available at the very fine Census Block level. In some cases, a Census Block can contain just one apartment building.</p>

<h3>Mixing Variables</h3>

<p>The fun starts when we mix these variables. And compare them to the previous
censuses. And there are lots of ways to do that, here are a few:</p>

<h4>Population Change</h4>

<p><a href="https://censusmapper.ca/maps/583"><img src="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/images/van_pop_change.png" style="width:50%;float:right;margin-left:10px;"></a>
The most immediate variable to look at is population change. We have
complete Canada-wide data at the CT level or above, but if we are really
interested we can also view this data for DAs and DBs that stayed the same
across the census years. The issue with doing that is that some regions will have
not data, and one has to be very careful not to read too much into an incomplete
dataset. Which is why I usually don&rsquo;t like giving out maps that contain incomplete data like this.
But this is great for diving into specific regions to get more information.</p>

<h4>Dwelling Change</h4>

<p><a href="https://censusmapper.ca/maps/588"><img src="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/images/van_dw_change.png" style="width:50%;float:left;margin-right:10px;"></a>
This is a great way to see where more dwellings got built. This only measures
net changes, so even if a region shows zero dwelling increase, there could have
been quite a bit of construction in the area. In particular, if houses with secondary
suites get torn down and replaced by houses without secondary suites, it will
show up as a decline in the number of dwelling units.</p>

<h4>Non-primary residence dwellings</h4>

<p><a href="https://censusmapper.ca/maps/586"><img src="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/images/van_uo_change.png" style="width:50%;float:right;margin-left:10px;"></a>
More formally, these are &ldquo;dwellings not occupied by usual residents&rdquo;, it&rsquo;s
the difference between dwellings and households and the object of continued
scrutiny in Vancouver. And a good portion of these are the target of the
upcoming empty home tax to either monetize non-primary resident homes or
nudge them into the rental market.</p>

<h4>Household size change</h4>

<p><a href="https://censusmapper.ca/maps/590"><img src="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/images/van_hs_change.png" style="width:50%;float:left;margin-right:10px;"></a>
A big part of population change is the change in household size. Canada wide the
trend to smaller households is continuing. That means that if the number of dwellings
and the rate of unoccupied dwellings in a region remain unchanged, then the
population in the area will decline if it follows the national trend to
smaller household size.</p>

<h3>Population Change Null Sum Game</h3>

<p>From looking at CensusMapper, the variable that got by far the most attention
nationally in the past three days is Population Change. It&rsquo;s great to
see where population grew or declined. But almost immediately people wonder
why population change was different in one region compared to another.</p>

<p>The first step to this is the Population Null Sum Game. You need the</p>

<ul>
<li>Dwelling Change</li>
<li>Change in Unoccupied Dwellings</li>
<li>Change in Household size</li>
</ul>


<p>to play. The game is then to express Population Change in terms of those three,
and thus &ldquo;explaining&rdquo; population change in terms of these variables. There are
of course other ways to split up the Population Change variable, but I find
this a useful one.</p>

<p>Nathaniel Lauster kicked the game off
<a href="https://homefreesociology.wordpress.com/2017/02/10/if-you-build-it-will-they-come/">with this great post</a>.
Let&rsquo;s follow up his inter-municipal level analysis with some intra-municipal numbers.</p>

<p>We will focus on the City of Vancouver only. People are welcome to use CensusMapper
to repeat this for whatever region they are interested in. Vancouver has the
nice advantage that at the dissemination area geography only on change was made.
A 2011 downtown DA got split into two for 2016. That makes it very easy to carry
this out at the DA level.</p>

<h3>Components of Population Change</h3>

<p>First we refine our variables a little bit it seems more interesting to use the rate of unoccupied builings as a variable,
rather than the number of these. We want to express population change <code>Δpop</code> as a
linear combination of</p>

<ul>
<li>Dwelling change <code>Δdw</code></li>
<li>Change in ratio of unoccupied dwellings <code>Δur</code></li>
<li>Change in household size <code>Δhs</code></li>
</ul>


<p>More formally:</p>

<pre><code>Δpop = hs₁₁ * (1-ur₁₁) * Δdw - hs₁₁ * dw₁₆ * Δur +  hh₁₆ * Δhs
</code></pre>

<p>where <code>hs₁₁=pop₁₁/hh₁₁</code> is the household size in 2011 as computed by dividing the population by the number of households,
<code>ur₁₁</code> is the rate of unoccupied dwellings in 2011, <code>dw₁₆</code> is the number of dwellings in 2016 and <code>hh₁₆</code> is the number of households in 2016.</p>

<p>It is simple algebra to check that the identity holds.</p>

<p><a href="https://censusmapper.ca/maps/596"><img src="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/images/van_pop_comp.png" style="width:50%;float:right;margin-left:10px;"></a>
The first term gives the contribution to population growth due to the growth in dwellings, assuming that household size and the rate of unoccupied dwellings
are unchanged from 2011.</p>

<p>The second term give the population growth due to the change in the rate of unoccupied dwellings and the third term gives the
population growth due to a change in household size.</p>

<p>Great, all that&rsquo;s left to do is to type the formula into CensusMapper and graph the relative contribution of each of these terms. To make this work
we will have to make due with using only the magnitude of each term, but we can visualize the sign in the bar graph widget when
we hover over an area.</p>

<p>This makes it very easy to compare different areas and see how the different components contribute to the change in
population in each area.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Bumper Year for Thumb Twiddlers]]></title>
    <link href="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2017/01/18/bumper-year-for-thumb-twiddlers/"/>
    <updated>2017-01-18T11:10:43-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2017/01/18/bumper-year-for-thumb-twiddlers</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="https://www.mountainmath.ca/map/assessment?zoom=12&amp;lat=49.2494&amp;lng=-123.1241&amp;layer=12"><img src="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/images/twiddling_thumbs_2006_2017.png" style="width:50%;float:right;margin-left:10px;"></a>
Almost a year has passed since we first noticed how
<a href="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2016/01/24/work-vs-twiddling-thumbs/">sitting on single family homes and twiddling thumbs generates more income than working</a>.
And not just at the level of individual single family households. In the
City of Vancouver, the cumulative
land value gains of just the single family homes eclipsed the cumulative taxable earnings
reported to the CRA for the entire population.</p>

<p>With the new assessment data available now, it is time to run the numbers
and see how our thumb-twiddlers fared vs workers this year. If you thought
last year&rsquo;s twiddling thumbs returns were crazy high, you better hold onto
your hats!</p>

<!-- more -->


<h3>Work</h3>

<p>Not much changed in terms of the income people earned. CANSIM does not make the
taxfiler data freely available at the municipal level, we we will again estimate
the cumulative income for residents of the City of Vancouver by using 2010
Census data and extrapolating by applying the Metro Vancouver rate of income
growth.</p>

<p>This way we get a cumulative $22.3bn pre-tax or $18.6bn after-tax income in 2010,
<a href="http://www5.statcan.gc.ca/cansim/a26?lang=eng&amp;retrLang=eng&amp;id=1110009&amp;&amp;pattern=&amp;stByVal=1&amp;p1=1&amp;p2=37&amp;tabMode=dataTable&amp;csid=">which grew around 13% between 2010 and 2014</a>.
Extrapolating this for another two years to 2016 we estimate an income growth of around 20% since 2010,
which then pegs the cumulative income for the City of Vancouver at
$26.8bn pre-tax or $22.3bn after-tax (ignoring financial drag and other issues).</p>

<h3>Twiddling Thumbs</h3>

<p>Let&rsquo;s compare this to how much Vancouver home owner households &ldquo;earned&rdquo; last year by twiddling thumbs while sitting on their
property. To keep things simple and consistent with last year, we again focus on just the single family homes (SFH).
And again, we only consider land value changes, after all changing the
building value because of renovation or rebuilding certainly does not happen by twiddling thumbs.</p>

<p>The median SFH land value increased was $435,000 (the average was $594,005), for a cumulative land value increase
of $46.7bn, accounting for about half of the
<a href="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2017/01/16/2017-assessment-data/">total land value increase of the City of Vancouver</a>
or two thirds of the land value increase for residential (and mixed) land uses.</p>

<p>So while last year the twiddling thumbs return were still comparable to the cumulative income in the City of Vancouver,
this year the thumb twiddlers blow the income earners out of the water.
<span style="font-weight:bolder;">Just by by twiddling their thumbs, the SFH property owners alone earned twice as much
as the entire population of the
City of Vancouver did by actually working</span>. And in most cases homeowners won&rsquo;t pay taxes on
their thumb-twiddle earnings, although the
<a href="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2016/10/04/secondary-suites-and-taxes/">CRA recently made it harder with their new reporting rules</a>.</p>

<p>We are glossing over a couple of details here, for example the numbers are not adjusted for inflation, and costs like
property taxes and property transfer tax are not taken into account.</p>

<p>Of course, comparing income from work to income from twiddling thumbs is not entirely fair. The income from twiddling thumbs
is frozen in the property until the owner sells. But gains accumulate over the years, and eventually everyone sells and realizes
the gains (or passes them on to the next generation). And it&rsquo;s always good to remember that
&ldquo;<a href="https://twitter.com/GRIDSVancouver/status/813516103490015232">house-rich cash-poor homeowners are one transaction away from simply being rich renters</a>&rdquo;.</p>

<h3>The Long Term</h3>

<p><a href="https://www.mountainmath.ca/map/values?filter=sfh&zoom=13&lat=49.2482&lng=-123.1213&layer=25&mapBase=2&year=2016"><img src="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/images/twiddling_thumbs_animated_2017.gif" style="width:50%;float:left;margin-right:10px;"></a>
Most people don&rsquo;t trade houses like stocks, so what really matters is the long term gains, not the year to year changes. The 11 year
timeframe for which we have data roughly matches the average holding time for a single family house. The year over year
changes in land value vary dramatically, as the image shows and can be explored further using the
<a href="https://www.mountainmath.ca/map/values?filter=sfh&amp;zoom=13&amp;lat=49.2482&amp;lng=-123.1213&amp;layer=25&amp;mapBase=2&amp;year=2016">interactive version</a>.</p>

<p>Over 11 years, the single family home land value quadrupled. The median (nominal) single family home land value increase over that timespan
was $1,233,000, or $112,000 per year. Broken down further, that&rsquo;s $2,339,000 ($213,000 per year) for the median west side home
and $1,031,000 ($94,000 per year) for the median east side home.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.mountainmath.ca/map/assessment?filter=sfh&amp;zoom=13&amp;lat=49.2494&amp;lng=-123.1241&amp;layer=12"><img  src="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/images/twiddling_thumbs_2006_2017.png" style="width:50%;float:right;"></a>
We <a href="https://www.mountainmath.ca/map/assessment?filter=sfh&amp;zoom=13&amp;lat=49.2494&amp;lng=-123.1241&amp;layer=12">mapped the land value gain averaged over 11 years</a>.
We can observe that the average yearly increase depends on the square footage of the property as well as the location. The rates are mostly uniform
throughout the city (with some notable exceptions), but properties starting out with a higher value will see higher total value
increases. It&rsquo;s probably fair to say that even using the 11 year average, most homeowners &ldquo;earned&rdquo; more money twiddling thumbs
than pursuing a more traditional employment.</p>

<h3>Hourly Rate for Twiddling Thumbs</h3>

<p>Using the <a href="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2016/01/24/work-vs-twiddling-thumbs/">same methods as last year</a>
we can compute the hourly earnings of thumb twiddlers. For the July 2016 to July 2017 timeframe, thumb twiddlers
in the City of Vancouver averaged a tidy $239 per hour.
Using the 11 year averaged numbers instead of focusing on just the last year we still get a healthy average
thumb twiddling rate of $62 per hour.</p>

<p>Another bumper year for thumb twiddlers!
Considering to change your line work to thumb twiddling? To bad thumb twiddling is so unaffordable!</p>

<h3>Data Dump</h3>

<p>Here is the raw output of the stats run on the single family properties for anyone interested.</p>

<h5>SFH Land Value Rise (2016 - 2017)</h5>

<ul>
<li>City Wide: Average $594,005 Median $435,000, Count: 78648, Total: $46,717,325,799, Hourly: $239</li>
<li>Eastside: Average $373,306 Median $358,000, Count: 47988, Total: $17,914,233,199, Hourly: $150</li>
<li>Westside: Average $939,435 Median $866,000, Count: 30660, Total: $28,803,092,600, Hourly: $378</li>
</ul>


<h5>SFH Land Value Rise (2006 - 2017)</h5>

<ul>
<li>City Wide: Average $153,777 Median $112,090, Count: 77809, Total: $11,965,271,272, Hourly: $62</li>
<li>Eastside: Average $96,892 Median $93,727, Count: 47545, Total: $4,606,748,985, Hourly: $39</li>
<li>Westside: Average $243,144 Median $212,636, Count: 30264, Total: $7,358,522,287, Hourly: $98</li>
</ul>


<p>The total number of units for the 2006 to 2017 analysis are a little lower since not all properties can be traced over that time
period without resorting to more tedious analysis.</p>

<script>
function resetImages(){
    $('img').each(function(img){
        imgsrc = $(img).attr('src');
        if (imgsrc.slice(imgsrc.length-4)=='.gif') {
            $(img).attr('src', '');
            $(img).attr('src', imgsrc);

        }
    });
    setTimeout(function(){
        resetImages();
    },25000);
}
setTimeout(function(){
    resetImages();
},25000);
</script>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Measuring Housing Affordability]]></title>
    <link href="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2016/09/14/measuring-housing-affordability/"/>
    <updated>2016-09-14T12:06:06-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2016/09/14/measuring-housing-affordability</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="https://mountainmath.ca/assessment/split_map" target="_blank"><img  src="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/images/sfh_price_2015.png" style="width:50%;float:right;margin-left:10px;"></a>
Housing affordability is a serious issue that deserves attention. Affordability is generally defined comparing incomes
to housing costs. And ideally also factoring in transportation cost, although that&rsquo;s seldom done and we will not attempt
today.</p>

<p>Recently we <a href="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2016/08/31/incomes/">took a detailed look at income data</a>. Using what we
learned, together with our
<a href="https://mountainmath.ca/assessment/split_map">detailed data on the development of prices of single family properties in Vancouver</a>,
we turn to the never dying question of affordability of single family homes.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p><a href="https://mountainmath.ca/assessment/split_map?year=2010" target="_blank"><img  src="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/images/sfh_price_2010.png" style="width:50%;float:left;margin-right:10px;"></a>
Let&rsquo;s go through the motions of how different choices in income data can lead to different stories. Some general choices of
what income to use is often pretty obvious. Others are more subtle and a matter of judgement. For simplicity we focus
entirely on the situation in 2010, because that&rsquo;s the last year we have detailed income data for the City of Vancouver
and we also have <a href="https://mountainmath.ca/assessment/split_map?year=2010">detailed publicly available single family housing price data</a>.</p>

<p>When talking about housing, the starting point is to look at income of (private) households (as opposed to individual income).
We may also want to consider the owner-renter split in the region we are interested in. For simplicity we will skip this.</p>

<h3>Household Income</h3>

<p>Households are as diverse as
dwelling types. If we write a story about single family housing, household income of all households is too broad to be
relevant. For example,
in the city of Vancouver there are about 75,500 single family lots, but 264,573 households. So at most 28% of households
can live in the main house on a single family lot. Taking the median household income makes no sense in this situation.
We need to narrow down the target group. In Calgary on the other hand,
59% of the dwelling stock is single detached (and there are more properties if we count the ones with suites like we
did for Vancouver), so in that case the assumption that the median household is looking to buy a single family home is
more reasonable. Although the median household probably won&rsquo;t be looking to buy the median single family home but a lower-priced one.</p>

<h3>Family Income</h3>

<p>So how should we measure the affordability of single family properties? That&rsquo;s not an easy question. A natural choice may
be to focus in on the 151,330 census families in Vancouver. Again, there are more than twice as many candidates as single
family properties. So maybe narrow it down even further an only look at the 88,515 census
families with children at home. Or the 63,790 couple families with children at home. Realistically speaking, even
going with couple families with children at home there just aren&rsquo;t enough single family properties to go around. Unless we
are willing to force out all of the roughly 45% of the occupants of the main house on single family lots that currently only have
1 or 2 people living in there. But overall, couple families with children is probably a better metric for affordability
for single family homes. Others will of course also buy single family homes, but maybe we will be less worried if
they can&rsquo;t afford one.</p>

<h3>Family with Children Income</h3>

<p>To complete the example, in 2010 the median single family property cost $848,000 (average $1,133,000) and the median
couple family with children income in private households was $92,068 (average $123,252).
That gives a dwelling value to income ratio of around 9.2, showing that the median single family property is not
affordable for the median couple family with children. By affordable we mean that with a 20% down payment the shelter
costs stay below 30% of pre-tax income, which requires a ratio of at most 6.6 assuming an interest rate of 3% and 25
years amortization.</p>

<p>If we were to more realistically assume that the median income couple family with children were to look to buy a single
family property priced at the 10 percentile level of $606,100 we get a dwelling value to income ratio of 6.6, barely
squeezing in below our affordability cutoff.</p>

<h3>Matching Income Quantiles with Housing Quantiles</h3>

<p>Another way to slice the data is to look at the household income distribution. By definition there are 37,750
single family homes more expensive than the median single family home. From the income distribution there are 44,215
households with income over $125,000. Taking $125,000 as our income we get a median dwelling value to income ratio of 6.8.
Only when throwing in some secondary suite rental income can we get to the
&lsquo;barely affordable&rsquo; 6.6 ratio. Adding rental income is double-dipping though, rental income should already be
included in our total income numbers. Assuming secondary suite rental income is correctly reported.</p>

<h3>Using Median Household Income</h3>

<p>Using the household income instead we would have gotten a ratio of 13.4, which is ridiculously unaffordable. But then
again, the notion that the median household should be able to purchase the median single family property
(or even a low-value single family property) is also ridiculous.</p>

<p><a href="https://censusmapper.ca/maps/37" target="_blank"><img  src="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/images/local_affordability_index.png" style="width:50%;float:right;margin-left:10px;"></a>
Somewhat more reasonable is to <a href="https://censusmapper.ca/maps/37">compare household income to all housing</a>,
not just single family. This still ignores that
half of the population in Vancouver is renting, but still can yield some interesting insights if one is interested in
more detailed spatial distribution of affordability and compare it to other cities.</p>

<p>Adding a scatter plot of local affordability index by proportion of owner households shows how in Vancouver, unlike
in comparable cities, the percentage of owner households is a weak determinant of local affordability.</p>

<h3>What about Affordability Today?</h3>

<p>This analysis assumes that all these households are comfortable to max out when buying a home and that there are no other
competing significant financial obligations like heavy student loans. And, just as a reminder, we were looking at 2010.
As of 2015 the price of the median single family home has increased 67%. We don&rsquo;t have 2015 income numbers for the City of
Vancouver (yet), but Couple Family median income for Metro Vancouver has increased 13% between 2010 and 2014, the last
year with available data. Extrapolating out that trend to 2015, and assuming that whatever other income metrics we were
looking at, we get an estimated income increase by 16%. So any affordability ratio is about 1.4 times worse in 2015 compared
to the 2010 ratio. What may have been &lsquo;barely affordable&rsquo; in 2010 is clearly unaffordable in 2015.</p>

<p>So we used the detailed income data available for 2010 to get very good understanding of the affordability situation in 2010.
Then we used regional income trends to extrapolate that data to 2015 and matched it with 2015 housing data to get more up-to-date
estimates. This is generally an effective method that yields good results.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Quick Guide to Income Data]]></title>
    <link href="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2016/08/31/incomes/"/>
    <updated>2016-08-31T09:17:12-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2016/08/31/incomes</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The news media has an extraordinarily difficult time with income data. And that&rsquo;s only partially the media&rsquo;s fault.
In general, income data is a funny beast. So I decided to give a quick overview over income data that&rsquo;s available through
Statistics Canada. To make things a little more concrete I focused on Vancouver as an example, but everything applies
equally well to any other area in Canada.</p>

<p>Most journalists I talked to care about accurate and relevant statements. If that&rsquo;s you, you will need to keep reading
and dive down the slightly wonkish income rabbit hole.</p>

<p>For those that don&rsquo;t really care, I made a
<em>quotable random income generator</em>. Just hit the &ldquo;generate&rdquo; button copy &amp; paste the result and link this post as source.
(Use at own risk!)</p>

<!-- more -->




<div class='income-generator'>
    <div class='income-choices'>
        <div class="geo"></div>
        <div class="med_av"></div>
        <div class="tax"></div>
        <div class="hh"></div>
        <div> income is </div>
        <div class="income"></div>
    </div>
    <a class="btn btn-default" style="background:orange;">Click to Generate Random Income Numbers</a>
</div>


<p>The income numbers don&rsquo;t fit the story? No problem, just play again until you get something you like!</p>

<h3>Geographic Regions</h3>

<p>The first thing to do when quoting income numbers of any sort is to decide what region to use. Seems straight forward
enough, but in reality <a href="https://twitter.com/vb_jens/status/744407354867736576">hardly ever done</a>. In the Vancouver
context, it simply comes down to deciding if one wants to
report on income for the City of Vancouver or Metro Vancouver. Both are frequently referred to as just &ldquo;Vancouver&rdquo;. Which
is just fine as long as it is clear from the context which region we are talking about. And more importantly, whatever
the income is compared to (e.g. housing price data) are taken for the same region.</p>

<h3>Base Demographics</h3>

<p>Next we have to choose a base demographic we are interested in, choose which income distribution is relevant for our context.
In some cases this choice is obvious. If we are writing a story on lone parents in the City of Vancouver, we would want
to look at the income distribution of lone parent households. If we are looking at the development of wages, we should
consider individual incomes. For a story on consumer spending we may want to look at after-tax income.</p>

<p>We may also be interested in specific type of income, for example only in investment income. Or the net capital gains
and losses. Or pension benefits. Or self-employment income.</p>

<h3>Statistic</h3>

<p>Often we would like to distill everything down to a single number. Typically we would choose the average or median
income from the distribution we are interested in, but we may also choose other statistics, for example the top quintile.
Which one we choose really depends on the story. As a rule of thumb, choose median incomes if you are interested in the
&lsquo;typical&rsquo; person or household. Choose average income if you are interested in the questions relating to the total amount
of money earned in a given area. Income quantiles are great to focus in on certain subgroups of the population.</p>

<h3>Availability</h3>

<p>Generally we also have to consider the availability of information. The census has very detailed income data in their
standard release that allow us to be very specific about what kind of incomes we are interested in. And if that&rsquo;s not
enough we can make a special request to StatsCan to narrow the incomes down to a group we are interested in, for example incomes
of renter households as was done in the <a href="http://rentalhousingindex.ca">rental housing index</a>.</p>

<p>Annual income data is available from CANSIM (Statistics Canada&rsquo;s socioeconomic database), but the geography is coarser
than in the census. Generally we can only
expect to get annual data for the whole country, provinces, census metropolitan areas, but not census
subdivisions (municipalities) or finer geographies.</p>

<h3>Sources and Comparability</h3>

<p>All income data eventually come down to CRA taxfiler data. But the devil is in the details. For the 2006 and 2011
censuses, there was a mixture between self-reporting and cross-referencing of individual level income data with CRA data.
And even self-reported data would again undergo quality control and get somewhat adjusted according to CRA data.</p>

<p>But there are important differences in the data, both on what kind of income is included and also what people are included.</p>

<p>The details are endless, many of them won&rsquo;t matter. Here are a couple to look out for:</p>

<ul>
<li>CANSIM is a comprehensive sample, census data is roughly a 1 in 5 subsample which may lead to sampling bias especially
in small geographies.</li>
<li>CENSUS data is sensitive to non-return bias. Not just no-return bias introduced by the NHS, but also by census undercounts
which, for example, were in the 10% range for the 25 to 29 year old demographic in both the 2006 and 2011 censuses.</li>
<li>CANSIM and the Census have different denominators for reporting average or median incomes. CANSIM reports on all
T1 taxfilers, as well as various family types. Some data can be broken out into age groups at
the 15 and 65 year cutoffs,
whereas Census reports only on people (15 or older) (or families or households) in &ldquo;private households&rdquo; with income greater
than zero.</li>
<li>the definition of &ldquo;private household&rdquo; changed between 2006 and 2011 censuses.</li>
<li>2011 and 2006 censuses differ slightly in what is included as income, for example
<a href="http://www12.statcan.gc.ca/census-recensement/2006/ref/dict/pop123-eng.cfm">2006 included RRSP withdrawls</a>,
<a href="https://www12.statcan.gc.ca/nhs-enm/2011/ref/dict/pop123-eng.cfm">2011 didn&rsquo;t</a> (both include pensions and RRIFs).
2011 includes net capital gains and losses as a percentage of total income in a separate category, 2006 did not
include any information on capital gains.</li>
</ul>


<p>So even when comparing CANSIM income data to census income data for the appropriate year we should expect some differences.
Or comparing 2006 to 2011 income, even if hypothetically an area had identical tax returns, we would still see differences.
Generally speaking, CANSIM average and median income estimates are lower than census estimates as it includes a larger pool
of people that are likely to have lower income.</p>

<h3>Where to get the goods?</h3>

<p><img  src="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/images/yvr_income.png" style="width:50%;float:right;margin-left:10px;">
The latest census income numbers are available via <a href="https://www12.statcan.gc.ca/nhs-enm/2011/dp-pd/prof/index.cfm">Statistics Canada</a>.
I am biased and prefer the <a href="https://censusmapper.ca/maps/467">CensusMapper</a> interface. For 2011 data, choose any
2011 CensusMapper map, select the geographic
region you are interested in and press the &ldquo;more&rdquo; button on the popup to bring up the &ldquo;census wheel&rdquo;. Then drill into the
&ldquo;income&rdquo; section, the last NHS variable in the widget.</p>

<p>CANSIM has annual data based on taxfiler information for coarser geographies. So you won&rsquo;t be able to get data for the City of Vancouver
or neighbourhoods within the city like with census data, but you can get data for Metro Vancouver. And you can get it for
more recent years. Things get complex very fast there are
<a href="http://www5.statcan.gc.ca/cansim/a33?themeID=3868&amp;spMode=tables&amp;chunkSize=213">213 CANSIM tables with income data</a></p>

<p>At CensusMapper we are still firmly planning integrate CANSIM data into the CensusMapper interface, but their API refresh got pushed back
to sometime 2018 and we can&rsquo;t justify the extra resources to integrate CANSIM data temporarily using the old API just
to switch it over a year later.</p>

<h3>Too Abstract?</h3>

<p>Want to see how this works on an example? Just read the
<a href="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2016/09/14/measuring-housing-affordability/">next post on using income data for housing affordability</a>.</p>

<script>
var geoData=['City of Vancouver','Metro Vancouver'];
var med_avData=['median','average'];
var taxData=['pre-tax','after-tax'];
var hhData=['individual','household','family','family with children'];
$('.income-generator .btn').on('click',function(e){
     $('.income-generator').addClass('active');
     $('.income-choices .geo').text(geoData[Math.round(Math.random())]);
     $('.income-choices .med_av').text(med_avData[Math.round(Math.random())]);
     $('.income-choices .tax').text(taxData[Math.round(Math.random())]);
     $('.income-choices .hh').text(hhData[Math.round(3.9999*Math.random()-0.5)]);
     $('.income-choices .income').text('$' + Math.round(80*Math.random()+40)+',000');
});
</script>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
