<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: census | Mountain Doodles]]></title>
  <link href="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/categories/census/feed.atom" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/"/>
  <updated>2016-10-22T09:29:42-07:00</updated>
  <id>http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[MountainMath]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Measuring Housing Affordability]]></title>
    <link href="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2016/09/14/measuring-housing-affordability/"/>
    <updated>2016-09-14T12:06:06-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2016/09/14/measuring-housing-affordability</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="https://mountainmath.ca/assessment/split_map" target="_blank"><img  src="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/images/sfh_price_2015.png" style="width:50%;float:right;margin-left:10px;"></a>
Housing affordability is a serious issue that deserves attention. Affordability is generally defined comparing incomes
to housing costs. And ideally also factoring in transportation cost, although that&rsquo;s seldom done and we will not attempt
today.</p>

<p>Recently we <a href="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2016/08/31/incomes/">took a detailed look at income data</a>. Using what we
learned, together with our
<a href="https://mountainmath.ca/assessment/split_map">detailed data on the development of prices of single family properties in Vancouver</a>,
we turn to the never dying question of affordability of single family homes.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p><a href="https://mountainmath.ca/assessment/split_map?year=2010" target="_blank"><img  src="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/images/sfh_price_2010.png" style="width:50%;float:left;margin-right:10px;"></a>
Let&rsquo;s go through the motions of how different choices in income data can lead to different stories. Some general choices of
what income to use is often pretty obvious. Others are more subtle and a matter of judgement. For simplicity we focus
entirely on the situation in 2010, because that&rsquo;s the last year we have detailed income data for the City of Vancouver
and we also have <a href="https://mountainmath.ca/assessment/split_map?year=2010">detailed publicly available single family housing price data</a>.</p>

<p>When talking about housing, the starting point is to look at income of (private) households (as opposed to individual income).
We may also want to consider the owner-renter split in the region we are interested in. For simplicity we will skip this.</p>

<h3>Household Income</h3>

<p>Households are as diverse as
dwelling types. If we write a story about single family housing, household income of all households is too broad to be
relevant. For example,
in the city of Vancouver there are about 75,500 single family lots, but 264,573 households. So at most 28% of households
can live in the main house on a single family lot. Taking the median household income makes no sense in this situation.
We need to narrow down the target group. In Calgary on the other hand,
59% of the dwelling stock is single detached (and there are more properties if we count the ones with suites like we
did for Vancouver), so in that case the assumption that the median household is looking to buy a single family home is
more reasonable. Although the median household probably won&rsquo;t be looking to buy the median single family home but a lower-priced one.</p>

<h3>Family Income</h3>

<p>So how should we measure the affordability of single family properties? That&rsquo;s not an easy question. A natural choice may
be to focus in on the 151,330 census families in Vancouver. Again, there are more than twice as many candidates as single
family properties. So maybe narrow it down even further an only look at the 88,515 census
families with children at home. Or the 63,790 couple families with children at home. Realistically speaking, even
going with couple families with children at home there just aren&rsquo;t enough single family properties to go around. Unless we
are willing to force out all of the roughly 45% of the occupants of the main house on single family lots that currently only have
1 or 2 people living in there. But overall, couple families with children is probably a better metric for affordability
for single family homes. Others will of course also buy single family homes, but maybe we will be less worried if
they can&rsquo;t afford one.</p>

<h3>Family with Children Income</h3>

<p>To complete the example, in 2010 the median single family property cost $848,000 (average $1,133,000) and the median
couple family with children income in private households was $92,068 (average $123,252).
That gives a dwelling value to income ratio of around 9.2, showing that the median single family property is not
affordable for the median couple family with children. By affordable we mean that with a 20% down payment the shelter
costs stay below 30% of pre-tax income, which requires a ratio of at most 6.6 assuming an interest rate of 3% and 25
years amortization.</p>

<p>If we were to more realistically assume that the median income couple family with children were to look to buy a single
family property priced at the 10 percentile level of $606,100 we get a dwelling value to income ratio of 6.6, barely
squeezing in below our affordability cutoff.</p>

<h3>Matching Income Quantiles with Housing Quantiles</h3>

<p>Another way to slice the data is to look at the household income distribution. By definition there are 37,750
single family homes more expensive than the median single family home. From the income distribution there are 44,215
households with income over $125,000. Taking $125,000 as our income we get a median dwelling value to income ratio of 6.8.
Only when throwing in some secondary suite rental income can we get to the
&lsquo;barely affordable&rsquo; 6.6 ratio. Adding rental income is double-dipping though, rental income should already be
included in our total income numbers. Assuming secondary suite rental income is correctly reported.</p>

<h3>Using Median Household Income</h3>

<p>Using the household income instead we would have gotten a ratio of 13.4, which is ridiculously unaffordable. But then
again, the notion that the median household should be able to purchase the median single family property
(or even a low-value single family property) is also ridiculous.</p>

<p><a href="https://censusmapper.ca/maps/37" target="_blank"><img  src="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/images/local_affordability_index.png" style="width:50%;float:right;margin-left:10px;"></a>
Somewhat more reasonable is to <a href="https://censusmapper.ca/maps/37">compare household income to all housing</a>,
not just single family. This still ignores that
half of the population in Vancouver is renting, but still can yield some interesting insights if one is interested in
more detailed spatial distribution of affordability and compare it to other cities.</p>

<p>Adding a scatter plot of local affordability index by proportion of owner households shows how in Vancouver, unlike
in comparable cities, the percentage of owner households is a weak determinant of local affordability.</p>

<h3>What about Affordability Today?</h3>

<p>This analysis assumes that all these households are comfortable to max out when buying a home and that there are no other
competing significant financial obligations like heavy student loans. And, just as a reminder, we were looking at 2010.
As of 2015 the price of the median single family home has increased 67%. We don&rsquo;t have 2015 income numbers for the City of
Vancouver (yet), but Couple Family median income for Metro Vancouver has increased 13% between 2010 and 2014, the last
year with available data. Extrapolating out that trend to 2015, and assuming that whatever other income metrics we were
looking at, we get an estimated income increase by 16%. So any affordability ratio is about 1.4 times worse in 2015 compared
to the 2010 ratio. What may have been &lsquo;barely affordable&rsquo; in 2010 is clearly unaffordable in 2015.</p>

<p>So we used the detailed income data available for 2010 to get very good understanding of the affordability situation in 2010.
Then we used regional income trends to extrapolate that data to 2015 and matched it with 2015 housing data to get more up-to-date
estimates. This is generally an effective method that yields good results.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Quick Guide to Income Data]]></title>
    <link href="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2016/08/31/incomes/"/>
    <updated>2016-08-31T09:17:12-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2016/08/31/incomes</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The news media has an extraordinarily difficult time with income data. And that&rsquo;s only partially the media&rsquo;s fault.
In general, income data is a funny beast. So I decided to give a quick overview over income data that&rsquo;s available through
Statistics Canada. To make things a little more concrete I focused on Vancouver as an example, but everything applies
equally well to any other area in Canada.</p>

<p>Most journalists I talked to care about accurate and relevant statements. If that&rsquo;s you, you will need to keep reading
and dive down the slightly wonkish income rabbit hole.</p>

<p>For those that don&rsquo;t really care, I made a
<em>quotable random income generator</em>. Just hit the &ldquo;generate&rdquo; button copy &amp; paste the result and link this post as source.
(Use at own risk!)</p>

<!-- more -->




<div class='income-generator'>
    <div class='income-choices'>
        <div class="geo"></div>
        <div class="med_av"></div>
        <div class="tax"></div>
        <div class="hh"></div>
        <div> income is </div>
        <div class="income"></div>
    </div>
    <a class="btn btn-default" style="background:orange;">Click to Generate Random Income Numbers</a>
</div>


<p>The income numbers don&rsquo;t fit the story? No problem, just play again until you get something you like!</p>

<h3>Geographic Regions</h3>

<p>The first thing to do when quoting income numbers of any sort is to decide what region to use. Seems straight forward
enough, but in reality <a href="https://twitter.com/vb_jens/status/744407354867736576">hardly ever done</a>. In the Vancouver
context, it simply comes down to deciding if one wants to
report on income for the City of Vancouver or Metro Vancouver. Both are frequently referred to as just &ldquo;Vancouver&rdquo;. Which
is just fine as long as it is clear from the context which region we are talking about. And more importantly, whatever
the income is compared to (e.g. housing price data) are taken for the same region.</p>

<h3>Base Demographics</h3>

<p>Next we have to choose a base demographic we are interested in, choose which income distribution is relevant for our context.
In some cases this choice is obvious. If we are writing a story on lone parents in the City of Vancouver, we would want
to look at the income distribution of lone parent households. If we are looking at the development of wages, we should
consider individual incomes. For a story on consumer spending we may want to look at after-tax income.</p>

<p>We may also be interested in specific type of income, for example only in investment income. Or the net capital gains
and losses. Or pension benefits. Or self-employment income.</p>

<h3>Statistic</h3>

<p>Often we would like to distill everything down to a single number. Typically we would choose the average or median
income from the distribution we are interested in, but we may also choose other statistics, for example the top quintile.
Which one we choose really depends on the story. As a rule of thumb, choose median incomes if you are interested in the
&lsquo;typical&rsquo; person or household. Choose average income if you are interested in the questions relating to the total amount
of money earned in a given area. Income quantiles are great to focus in on certain subgroups of the population.</p>

<h3>Availability</h3>

<p>Generally we also have to consider the availability of information. The census has very detailed income data in their
standard release that allow us to be very specific about what kind of incomes we are interested in. And if that&rsquo;s not
enough we can make a special request to StatsCan to narrow the incomes down to a group we are interested in, for example incomes
of renter households as was done in the <a href="http://rentalhousingindex.ca">rental housing index</a>.</p>

<p>Annual income data is available from CANSIM (Statistics Canada&rsquo;s socioeconomic database), but the geography is coarser
than in the census. Generally we can only
expect to get annual data for the whole country, provinces, census metropolitan areas, but not census
subdivisions (municipalities) or finer geographies.</p>

<h3>Sources and Comparability</h3>

<p>All income data eventually come down to CRA taxfiler data. But the devil is in the details. For the 2006 and 2011
censuses, there was a mixture between self-reporting and cross-referencing of individual level income data with CRA data.
And even self-reported data would again undergo quality control and get somewhat adjusted according to CRA data.</p>

<p>But there are important differences in the data, both on what kind of income is included and also what people are included.</p>

<p>The details are endless, many of them won&rsquo;t matter. Here are a couple to look out for:</p>

<ul>
<li>CANSIM is a comprehensive sample, census data is roughly a 1 in 5 subsample which may lead to sampling bias especially
in small geographies.</li>
<li>CENSUS data is sensitive to non-return bias. Not just no-return bias introduced by the NHS, but also by census undercounts
which, for example, were in the 10% range for the 25 to 29 year old demographic in both the 2006 and 2011 censuses.</li>
<li>CANSIM and the Census have different denominators for reporting average or median incomes. CANSIM reports on all
T1 taxfilers, as well as various family types. Some data can be broken out into age groups at
the 15 and 65 year cutoffs,
whereas Census reports only on people (15 or older) (or families or households) in &ldquo;private households&rdquo; with income greater
than zero.</li>
<li>the definition of &ldquo;private household&rdquo; changed between 2006 and 2011 censuses.</li>
<li>2011 and 2006 censuses differ slightly in what is included as income, for example
<a href="http://www12.statcan.gc.ca/census-recensement/2006/ref/dict/pop123-eng.cfm">2006 included RRSP withdrawls</a>,
<a href="https://www12.statcan.gc.ca/nhs-enm/2011/ref/dict/pop123-eng.cfm">2011 didn&rsquo;t</a> (both include pensions and RRIFs).
2011 includes net capital gains and losses as a percentage of total income in a separate category, 2006 did not
include any information on capital gains.</li>
</ul>


<p>So even when comparing CANSIM income data to census income data for the appropriate year we should expect some differences.
Or comparing 2006 to 2011 income, even if hypothetically an area had identical tax returns, we would still see differences.
Generally speaking, CANSIM average and median income estimates are lower than census estimates as it includes a larger pool
of people that are likely to have lower income.</p>

<h3>Where to get the goods?</h3>

<p><img  src="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/images/yvr_income.png" style="width:50%;float:right;margin-left:10px;">
The latest census income numbers are available via <a href="https://www12.statcan.gc.ca/nhs-enm/2011/dp-pd/prof/index.cfm">Statistics Canada</a>.
I am biased and prefer the <a href="https://censusmapper.ca/maps/467">CensusMapper</a> interface. For 2011 data, choose any
2011 CensusMapper map, select the geographic
region you are interested in and press the &ldquo;more&rdquo; button on the popup to bring up the &ldquo;census wheel&rdquo;. Then drill into the
&ldquo;income&rdquo; section, the last NHS variable in the widget.</p>

<p>CANSIM has annual data based on taxfiler information for coarser geographies. So you won&rsquo;t be able to get data for the City of Vancouver
or neighbourhoods within the city like with census data, but you can get data for Metro Vancouver. And you can get it for
more recent years. Things get complex very fast there are
<a href="http://www5.statcan.gc.ca/cansim/a33?themeID=3868&amp;spMode=tables&amp;chunkSize=213">213 CANSIM tables with income data</a></p>

<p>At CensusMapper we are still firmly planning integrate CANSIM data into the CensusMapper interface, but their API refresh got pushed back
to sometime 2018 and we can&rsquo;t justify the extra resources to integrate CANSIM data temporarily using the old API just
to switch it over a year later.</p>

<h3>Too Abstract?</h3>

<p>Want to see how this works on an example? Just read the
<a href="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2016/09/14/measuring-housing-affordability/">next post on using income data for housing affordability</a>.</p>

<script>
var geoData=['City of Vancouver','Metro Vancouver'];
var med_avData=['median','average'];
var taxData=['pre-tax','after-tax'];
var hhData=['individual','household','family','family with children'];
$('.income-generator .btn').on('click',function(e){
     $('.income-generator').addClass('active');
     $('.income-choices .geo').text(geoData[Math.round(Math.random())]);
     $('.income-choices .med_av').text(med_avData[Math.round(Math.random())]);
     $('.income-choices .tax').text(taxData[Math.round(Math.random())]);
     $('.income-choices .hh').text(hhData[Math.round(3.9999*Math.random()-0.5)]);
     $('.income-choices .income').text('$' + Math.round(80*Math.random()+40)+',000');
});
</script>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Mixing Data]]></title>
    <link href="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2016/07/06/mixing-data/"/>
    <updated>2016-07-06T09:19:04-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2016/07/06/mixing-data</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Census data is very rich and with <a href="https://censusmapper.ca">CensusMapper</a> we now have about 1 billion data points right at
our fingertips. And we have managed to open up some of our interfaces for everyone to <a href="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2016/05/04/census-mapping-for-everyone/">explore data and make their own maps
and freely share them</a>.</p>

<p>Things really get interesting when one mixes custom data with census data. While, at this point, these are not part of
the freely available CensusMapper functionality we still wanted to share what can be done.</p>

<p>At CensusMapper we have developed three basic ways to rapidly mix custom data with census data. So this is really three
blog posts in one.</p>

<!-- more -->


<h3>1. Overlay Mapping</h3>

<p>First up, advanced users can upload custom datasets and map them on top of census data.
<a href="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/images/restaurants_2.png"><img  src="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/images/restaurants_2.png" style="width:50%;float:right;margin-left:10px;"></a>
For example, we took a
<a href="http://data.vancouver.ca/datacatalogue/businessLicence.htm">business license dataset</a> from the City of Vancouver open
data catalogue, filtered it by the <em>BusinessType</em> field to only include businesses starting with &ldquo;Restaurant&rdquo; or
&ldquo;Liquor Establishment&rdquo; and uploaded them to CensusMapper to map it on top of census data. We have used a map
for <em>median age</em> that was <a href="https://twitter.com/jofu_/status/750564269796823041">recently created using CensusMapper&rsquo;s free public interface</a>
(have you made <a href="https://censusmapper.ca/maps/new">your own CensusMapper map</a> yet?), we have faded out areas outside of
Vancouver and coloured <em>Liquor Establishments</em> in red and <em>Restaurants</em> in blue.</p>

<p>Giving a visual impression of your own dataset in relation to census data is the first step to location analysis.</p>

<h3>2. Populate Custom Data with Census Data</h3>

<p>Next
up is to populate your own dataset with census data for further analysis. For the restaurants, we may be interested in
attaching population estimates in 5 minute walking distance from each location. We might also be interested in specific
age brackets, or numbers of recent immigrants
from specific countries that we may want to target with a new restaurant, or maybe even     income data.</p>

<p>This can be a time consuming and painful process,
but we have automated this at CensusMapper.</p>

<p>To showcase how this works we will show an example using elementary school catchment areas in the City of Vancouver. The
areas we have (from the <a href="http://data.vancouver.ca/datacatalogue/publicPlaces.htm">Vancouver Open Data Catalogue</a>) are
quite out of date, but for the purpose of this example they work as we will compare them to 2011 census data. We will look at the
<a href="https://censusmapper.ca/maps/419">school aged population</a> in each catchment.</p>

<!--
The general census release data does not fit our task perfectly, the census splits by age in early May 2011 and not by
year born and it does not have fine enough age brackets to estimating accurate school catchment numbers.
[BC Stats](http://www.bcstats.gov.bc.ca/StatisticsBySubject/Demography/PopulationEstimates.aspx) has finer age brackets
computed to school district (not catchment) boundaries, but their estimates are ridiculously far off of census numbers
when using matching age brackets and years that their usefulness is highly questionable. 
-->


<p><a href="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/images/e-schools.png"><img  src="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/images/e-schools.png" style="width:50%;float:left;margin-right:10px;"></a>
Using the visual overlay we notice that the catchment areas do fit boundaries of Dissemination Areas shown on the map
reasonably well, with some exceptions. The same cannot be said for Census Tracts, we can be reasonably confident that
Dissemination Area data is fairly accurate.</p>

<p>Next we use the built-in CensusMapper functionality to automatically populate the catchment areas with the census
data we are interested
in. When Dissemination Areas don&rsquo;t line up with the catchment boundaries we go down to Dissemination Blocks to estimate
how many children live on what side of the catchment boundary. We
<a href="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2016/04/06/tod/">previously explained this process in more detail</a>, the result is
a spreadsheet with the population data by age for each catchment area.</p>

<div id='schools'></div>


<div><script src="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/javascripts/colorbrewer.js" charset="utf-8"></script></div>


<div><script src="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/javascripts/school_bar_graph.js" charset="utf-8"></script></div>


<p>Here we show the results by school, the select element can be used to select any school of interest. The whole process
of populating the school data with census data just required uploading the catchment boundaries and selecting which
variables to attach.</p>

<h3>3. Custom Census Data Mapping</h3>

<p>Sometimes it is not practical to map custom data on CensusMapper. Maybe the custom data is too sensitive to be uploaded
to CensusMapper servers. Or it is quite complex and is better mapped separately. So we created an API to pull in
census data from CensusMapper to easily show census data on custom maps. And dynamically mix in your own data. As an
example we mix census data with data from BCAssessment, again obtained through the
<a href="http://vancouver.ca/your-government/open-data-catalogue.aspx">Vancouver Open Data Catalogue</a> (and enriched with
<a href="http://www.metrovancouver.org/data">open data from Metro Vancouver</a>).
For demonstration purposes take Dissemination Area
geographies and Dwelling Characteristic data from CensusMapper and mash it up with our
<a href="http://mountainmath.ca/map/assessment?zoom=14&amp;lat=49.2604&amp;lng=-123.1417&amp;layer=14&amp;mapBase=2">processed assessment data</a>
to explore the <a href="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2016/06/17/sdh-zoning-and-land-use/">differences in how single family properties are classified</a>.</p>

<p><a href="https://mountainmath.ca/census_mix/map?mapBase=2&layer=0" target="_blank"><img  src="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/images/sfh_unit_count.png" style="width:50%;float:right;margin-left:10px;"></a>
For example we can <a href="https://mountainmath.ca/census_mix/map?mapBase=2&amp;layer=0">compare BC Assessment single family lot count to Stats Canada unit count</a>
in the dissemination areas
that are exclusively made up of single family lots. This gives an indication of how many suites and laneway houses there
are in those areas. The census is prone to undercount units, but still does a better job at estimating them than other data sources,
like the city or BC Assessment.</p>

<p>One of the reasons why census unit counts come up higher than other methods is that the census also counts illegal units,
which naturally are not part of other official government counts. There are different reasons why a suite may be illegal:
<a href="https://mountainmath.ca/census_mix/map?mapBase=2&layer=5" target="_blank"><img  src="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/images/illegal_units.png" style="width:50%;float:left;margin-right:10px;"></a>
It could simply be that the owner has not made the effort to register it. Or the suite may not be up to code.
And in some cases, a property may have more than one suite in the main building, which is illegal in the City of Vancouver.
The latter ones we can pick out in census data, since a house with two secondary suites &ndash; so three dwelling units in one building in
total &ndash; is classified as being an &ldquo;Apartment, building that has fewer than five storeys&rdquo;. So, in census dissemination areas that
only have duplex or single family lots as residential land uses based on assessment and land use data, we can look for
how many dwelling units the census places in an &ldquo;Apartment, building that has fewer than five storeys&rdquo;. And
<a href="https://mountainmath.ca/census_mix/map?mapBase=2&amp;layer=5">map them</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[SDH Zoning and Land Use]]></title>
    <link href="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2016/06/17/sdh-zoning-and-land-use/"/>
    <updated>2016-06-17T09:34:37-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2016/06/17/sdh-zoning-and-land-use</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Recently the question around the amount of space taken up (exclusively) by single detached houses has show up on my
Twitter feed citing that
SFH take up <a href="https://twitter.com/WayneFougere/status/743211599821844481">70%</a>,
<a href="https://twitter.com/MitchellReardon/status/739957295564476416">66%</a>,
and <a href="https://twitter.com/karensawa/status/743235428011020288">57%</a>,
<a href="http://www.cknw.com/2016/06/02/the-lynda-steele-show-bob-rennie-on-supply-and-demand/">56% (timestamp 3:50)</a>.
I personally have thrown in
<a href="https://twitter.com/vb_jens/status/738608945741238272">34%</a> as a contender. And, just for the fun of it, by the end of
this post I will have thrown 33% and 28% and my favorite, 81%, into the mix.</p>

<p>What&rsquo;s going on, how can there be such a large range of estimates for what seems to be a simple question? The answer
lies in the details of what exactly the question is asking, all of the above numbers are correct answers to one particular
version of very similar questions.</p>

<h3>TL;DR</h3>

<p>The takeaway I think is most useful for general purposes:</p>

<pre><code>35% of all households live on single family and duplex properties
making up 81% of Vancouver's residential land, while the     
remaining 65% of households live on 19% of the residential land. 
</code></pre>

<!-- more -->


<p>There are two fundamental ways to attack the question. One is through zoning, that is to look at area where only SDH can
be built. The other is through land use, that is looking at what area is currently occupied by SDH lots.</p>

<h3>Single Detached Houses</h3>

<p>First we need to understand what we mean by single detached house. There are two common, but quite different definitions
out there. One stems from the zoning code and refers to a property that is not stratified and has a single main structure
on it, possibly with one suite, and possibly a laneway house. This is the definition most commonly used. When someone says
they own a single family house, this is what they are talking about. Let&rsquo;s call them <em>single detached properties</em>.
There are around 75,000 of these in the City of Vancouver.</p>

<p>Stats Canada employs a different definition. To them a <em>single detached dwelling</em> is single dwelling unit comprised of a
free-standing (detached) structure. A <em>single detached property</em> may contain exactly one dwelling unit, in which case
Stats Canada would also call it a <em>single detached dwelling</em>. If the house has a secondary suite, Stats Canda would
classify it as a <em>duplex</em>. If it has a laneway house, Stats Canada would classify the laneway house as a separate
<em>single detached dwelling</em>. Stats Canada reports 47,530 <em>single detached dwellings</em> in the City of Vancouver.</p>

<p>Because of this discrepancy, sometimes it is useful to look as single family houses and duplexes combined. Especially
if one wants to mix in census data to for example look at the number of households that live in these dwellings. While
there are about 75,000 <em>single detached properties</em> in Vancouver, it is fair to assume that there are significantly more
than 75,000 households living on these properties once we account for secondary suites and laneway houses.</p>

<h3>Zoning</h3>

<p><a href="http://vancouver.ca/files/cov/Zoning-Map-Vancouver.pdf" target="_blank"><img  src="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/images/zoning_van_pdf.png" style="width:50%;float:right;margin-left:10px;"></a>
Vancouver is divided up into zones that determine what can (and cannot) be legally built on the land.
If one is primarily concerned with the area of land that where only single detached houses can be built, then zoning is
the right metric to look at.</p>

<p>There are two zones that essentially only allow single family houses as residential properties, the RS zones and,
to some extent, First Shaughnessy. Each of these has it&rsquo;s own pitfalls. The first issue is that parks are generally zoned
RS, but one cannot build single family homes in parks. Moreover, while RS does not allow residential land uses other
than single detached houses, it does allow for other land uses, like parks, schools, assisted living and other institutional
uses. So RS zoned land area is a poor proxy for the question of where single family houses could be built. At the very
<a href="https://mountainmath.ca/map/assessment?zoom=13&lat=49.2517&lng=-123.1232&layer=6" target="_blank"><img  src="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/images/zoning_van.png" style="width:50%;float:left;margin-right:10px;"></a>
least we should exclude parks from the equation, but probably also schools and other institutional land uses. After all,
it is delusional to think that even if a school were to close down and the land be sold for development that single
detached dwelling would be built on that land. Next comes the question if we should only include the lots that single
family homes could be built on, or also include the surrounding roads. After all, the roads are needed to serve the lots.
But they also serve the schools and parks, so maybe only a certain portion of the roads should be included? It gets messy,
the second image shows only non-institutional and non-park properties (no roads) coloured by zone, interactive version
<a href="http://mountainmath.ca/map/assessment?zoom=14&amp;lat=49.2517&amp;lng=-123.1232&amp;layer=6">here</a>.</p>

<p>The numbers between 70% and 56% mentioned up top are (probably) derived using some version of zoned area, possibly excluding
parks or schools for some, but including roads within RS zoning. It is easy to underestimate
the space roads take up in the City of Vancouver, overall roads right of ways make up 28% of City of Vancouver land.</p>

<p>At the end of this though process, we are starting to gravitate away from zoning and toward land use.</p>

<h3>Land Use</h3>

<p>We can simplify the discussion by asking how much space currently is taken up by single family properties. The answer
to this is 33%. I have previously written about the
<a href="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2016/02/29/land-use/">land use breakdown</a> for Metro Vancouver municipalities, but
single detached homes were not broken out separately, single detached and duplex properties combined take up 34% of
Vancouver&rsquo;s land. One can play the numbers a little more, maybe only look at single detached properties within RS zoning.
That puts the number at 28%. Throw in Shaugnessy and it rises to 29%. Recall that this excludes roads right of way.</p>

<p><a href="https://mountainmath.ca/land_use/map?zoom=13&lat=49.2544&lng=-123.1268&mu_filter=[%22VA%22]&lu_filter_n=[]" target="_blank"><img  src="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/images/land_use_van.png" style="width:50%;float:right;margin-left:10px;"></a>
Here is an interactive (data-heavy) map that shows the land use for
<a href="https://mountainmath.ca/land_use/map?zoom=13&amp;lat=49.2544&amp;lng=-123.1268&amp;mu_filter=[%22VA%22]&amp;lu_filter_n=[]">just for the City of Vancouver (plus Musqueam 2)</a>.</p>

<h3>Multi-Unit Housing</h3>

<p>One can ask the same question about other housing types, and we can read off the numbers from the
<a href="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2016/02/29/land-use/">land use breakdown</a>. 3.2% of land is taken up with low rise
apartments, 1.9% with townhouses, 1.2% with high rise, 0.3% by non-market housing, 0.9% by mixed use low rise and 0.7%
by mixed use high rise. Adding all of this up we get that 8.2% of land is taken up by housing that is not single detached
or duplex. And it also includes some commercial space in the mixed use developments.</p>

<p>That means that overall in Vancouver 42.2% of the land is used for residential purposes, 81% of which is occupied by
single detached and duplex properties and the remaining 19% is occupied by all other building forms.</p>

<h3>Share of Households in Different Land Uses</h3>

<p>We may be interested in the population density these different land use patterns entail. That&rsquo;s where things get a little
tricky, we will turn to the census for answers. From the standard census releases we can only discern the share of
dwellings that are single detached and duplex properties combined, and that number is 93,370 dwelling units. Overall
there are 264,575 dwelling units, so single family and duplex units make up 35% of all dwelling units in CoV. Glossing
over the issue that some of these may not be occupied we conclude that 35% of all households live on single family and
duplex properties making up 81% of Vancouver&rsquo;s residential land,
while the remaining 65% of households live on 19% of the residential land.</p>

<h3>Fine Print</h3>

<p>There are a number of issues with the data that might change the numbers slightly, but not by much. The first is that
the land use dataset I use lump the City of Vancouver together with Musqueam 2. That slightly changes the land use mix
and areas reported, but the effect on all numbers mentioned here is very small. Next up is the number of dwelling units
on single detached or duplex properties. The census number is likely to under report some secondary suites (although it
captures more than BCAssessment does), and properties with more than one secondary suite (so some illegal suites) will
show up as an apartment building in census data. Moreover, the census data is from 2011, the land use data we used is
about a year old, and we have manually adjusted for some recent upzoning. So there is some give or take in the numbers,
I would not expect more than a one percent move in the numbers I reported as a result.</p>

<h3>Further Questions</h3>

<p>This does not answer the question what percentage of the population lives on single family or duplex properties. To
estimate that one would have to first estimate the number of people per houshold for the different land uses, as we
expect them to differ significantly. One can start exploring how the number of people per dwelling unit varies
<a href="https://censusmapper.ca/maps/391">on CensusMapper</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[FSR]]></title>
    <link href="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2016/05/20/density/"/>
    <updated>2016-05-20T22:51:29-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2016/05/20/density</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="https://mountainmath.ca/map/assessment?layer=16" target="_blank"><img  src="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/images/fsr.png" style="width:50%;float:right;margin-left:10px;"></a>
Ever since I played with the <a href="http://mountainmath.ca/vancouver_lidar/map">LIDAR-generated building height data</a> I thought
that I should use that to map gross floor area (GFA) and floor space ratio (FSR). Gross floor area is the total floor area
inside the building envelope. So for a three storey building, it is the area of the footprint times three.
Floor space ratio is the GFA divided by the area of the parcel it sits on. There are several reasons why this may be
interesting.</p>

<p>GFA is the currency of the developer. Especially once we enter the world of apartment or commercial buildings,
gross floor area is directly proportional to the amount of money a developer can charge for a property, either when stratified
and sold or when rented out.</p>

<p>FSR on the other hand is a measure of density, and it is the currency of the zoning code. Height and site coverage are
also regulated in the zoning code and there is an obvious relationship to FSR. But because GFA is so important to the
developer, FSR usually receives more attention in public discussions.</p>

<p>Read on or <a href="https://mountainmath.ca/map/assessment?layer=16" target="_blank" class='btn btn-default'>head straight for the interactive map</a> to browse
Vancouver by FSR. Read the disclaimer at the bottom before using any data for purposes other than general reference.</p>

<!-- more -->


<h3>Maximum Allowable FSR and Spot Zoning.</h3>

<p>The maximum allowable FSR is set by the zoning code. Because land is so valuable in Vancouver, most people will try
to maximize GFA when building a new building, so they typically go right up to the maximum allowable FSR. Previously we have
<a href="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2016/03/05/physical-sfh-form-over-time/">examined the effects of various related metrics like height and site coverage</a>
for single family homes.</p>

<p><a href="https://mountainmath.ca/map/assessment?zoom=15&lat=49.2599&lng=-123.1583&layer=6" target="_blank"><img  src="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/images/spot-zoning.png" style="width:30%;float:right;margin-left:10px;"></a>
At least this is how it works for RS/RT zones. If you are looking to develop a different property, say a mixed use or
an apartment building or commercial building you will probably be looking to up-zone. That is, you will try to convince
the city (and the local population) to allow you to build more GFA than zoning would allow. If successful the city will
create a new zone just for your property and ask for some compensation in form of CACs (aiming to recoup about 80% of the
uplift in value the up-zoning creates) in return. That process is called
spot zoning and it can be seen in form of the little &ldquo;Comprehensive Development&rdquo; zones that are visible as yellow
sprinkles in the otherwise quite uniform zones on the map.</p>

<p>In reality the process of up-zoning a property is a lot more complex, arduous and time consuming, which favours larger
developers with deep pockets that can take the risk and sit out the long process of eventually obtaining higher GFA. One
of the many reasons why the &ldquo;missing middle&rdquo; is missing.</p>

<h3>Mapping Density</h3>

<p><a href="https://censusmapper.ca/maps/302#16/49.2375/-123.1573" target="_blank"><img  src="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/images/kerrisdale_people.png" style="width:30%;float:left;margin-right:10px;"></a>
From Census data we know the <a href="https://censusmapper.ca/maps/302">nighttime density</a>, that is where people live and sleep.
But we don&rsquo;t know where they are
during the daytime.</p>

<p><a href="https://mountainmath.ca/map/assessment?zoom=16&lat=49.238&lng=-123.154&layer=16" target="_blank"><img  src="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/images/kerrisdale_fsr.png" style="width:30%;float:right;margin-left:10px;"></a>
FSR is also often seen as such a measure of density, although it only focuses on density on property parcels and neglects
all the space between parcels, like roads right of ways and parks.</p>

<p>In mostly residential neighbourhoods the two densities correspond quite closely, but in areas with large commercial buildings
(nighttime) population density can be quite low while FSR is very high as can easily be seen by comparing the two maps.</p>

<p><a href="https://mountainmath.ca/assessment_gl/map?zoom=16&lat=49.2384&lng=-123.1567" target="_blank"><img  src="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/images/kerrisdale_tax.png" style="width:30%;float:left;margin-right:10px;"></a>
<a href="https://mountainmath.ca/assessment_gl/map">Tax density</a>, that is property taxes collected per area, give another view of
&ldquo;density&rdquo; in the city that highlights relative property values and emphasises commercial land use that pays five times
the residential tax rate.</p>

<p>There are lots of other measures of density that are important for different purposes, for example <a href="http://mountainmath.ca/census3">household density</a>
(in full 3D, requires modern computer),
<a href="https://censusmapper.ca/maps/359">the density of private dwelling units</a> or <a href="https://censusmapper.ca/maps/35">toddler density</a> just to name a few.</p>

<h3>Next Steps</h3>

<p>There are several directions I want to take this. Now that FSR is available for all properties, I can
compare purpose built rental buildings to strata buildings. For example, in my
<a href="http://mountainmath.ca/assessment/split_map">Buildings and Dirt map</a> I can&rsquo;t integrate purpose
built rentals because I don&rsquo;t know how many rental units they have. The assessment data from the Vancouver Open Data portal,
does not have that information, and BC Assessment won&rsquo;t share it (in a hassle-free way). But I can make a similar map based on GFA instead of
number of units and examine
how GFA effect land and building values across different land uses. And in many ways GFA may be a better unit for comparisons
than number of suites.</p>

<p><a href="https://mountainmath.ca/map/assessment?zoom=13&lat=49.2488&lng=-123.1211&layer=17&filter=res" target="_blank"><img  src="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/images/value_per_gfa.png" style="width:50%;float:right;margin-left:10px;"></a>
Or I can just make a <a href="https://mountainmath.ca/map/assessment?zoom=14&amp;lat=49.2684&amp;lng=-123.1354&amp;layer=17">straight-up map of total assessed value per GFA</a>.
And maybe add a filter to only show this for <a href="https://mountainmath.ca/map/assessment?zoom=13&amp;lat=49.2488&amp;lng=-123.1211&amp;layer=17&amp;filter=res">residential and mixed use units</a>
like in the image if that&rsquo;s what we are interested in.</p>

<p>Another interesting application is to use this data to do something along the lines of this
<a href="http://www.nytimes.com/interactive/2016/05/19/upshot/forty-percent-of-manhattans-buildings-could-not-be-built-today.html?_r=0">excellent analysis the New York Times published</a>
for Vancouver. FSR, next to building heights and lot coverage that I
<a href="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2016/03/05/physical-sfh-form-over-time/">have already analysed from a different angle</a>,
is an important metric to detect buildings that could not be rebuilt under regular zoning.</p>

<p>Lastly, having data on building GFA, together with assessment open data, allows for reverse-engineering of the GFA of individual
strata units. That makes the analysis of condo assessment data more meaningful as we can analyse assessed condo values by
unit size. One of the reasons why we are only talking about single family homes (or in some cases RS zoned homes) and
not condos is that it is very easy to compare single family homes. But comparing condos doesn&rsquo;t make much sense unless
one also has data on the size of each condo. And this has probably focused the public debate too much on single family
homes when we should be paying a lot more attention to condos. And purpose built rental units.</p>

<h3>Disclaimer</h3>

<p>The FSR was estimated using coarse building data extracted from LIDAR data. The motivation was to use the FSR for aggregate
analysis and not for getting accurate estimates of individual buildings.</p>

<p>Secondary buildings like garages or laneway houses are only inconsistently detected and mapped. The data is from 2009,
buildings built after that are greyed out.</p>

<p>The algorithm to compute FSR
from this building data is rather crude and only makes rudimentary attempts to adjust for varying floor heights of buildings
different for land uses, overhangs and eyebrows and dealing with pitched roofs or mechanical units.</p>

<p>Building data was clipped to property polygons to deal with cases of buildings spanning several legal lots or not properly
separated.</p>

<p>The FSR computed only roughly resembles the FSR defined in building codes. In particular our model with grossly
overestimate the FSR for buildings with overhanging features like
the Lookout on the Harbour Centre.</p>

<p>Block level aggregates will underestimate FSR in the presence of properties excluded from the FSR calculation.</p>

<p>Do not be use the FSR estimates as an authoritative source for any individual building FSR.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
