<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: census | Mountain Doodles]]></title>
  <link href="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/categories/census/feed.atom" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/"/>
  <updated>2016-07-08T13:46:17-07:00</updated>
  <id>http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[MountainMath]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Mixing Data]]></title>
    <link href="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2016/07/06/mixing-data/"/>
    <updated>2016-07-06T09:19:04-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2016/07/06/mixing-data</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Census data is very rich and with <a href="https://censusmapper.ca">CensusMapper</a> we now have about 1 billion fields right at
our fingertips. And we managed to open up some of our interfaces for everyone to <a href="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2016/05/04/census-mapping-for-everyone/">explore data and make their own maps
and freely share them</a>.</p>

<p>Things really get interesting when one mixes custom data with census data. While, at this point, these are not part of
the freely available CensusMapper functionality we still wanted to share what can be done.</p>

<p>At CensusMapper we have developed three basic ways to rapidly mix custom data with census data. So this is really three
blog posts in one.</p>

<!-- more -->


<h3>Overlay Mapping</h3>

<p>First up, advanced users can upload custom datasets and map them on top of census data.
<a href="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/images/restaurants_2.png"><img  src="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/images/restaurants_2.png" style="width:50%;float:right;margin-left:10px;"></a>
For example, we took the
<a href="http://data.vancouver.ca/datacatalogue/businessLicence.htm">business license dataset</a> from the City of Vancouver open
data catalogue, filtered it by the <em>BusinessType</em> field to only include anything starting with &ldquo;Restaurant&rdquo; or
&ldquo;Liquor Establishment&rdquo; and uploaded them to CensusMapper to map it on top of census data. In this case we used a map
for <em>median age</em> that was <a href="https://twitter.com/jofu_/status/750564269796823041">recently created using the public interface</a>
(have you made <a href="https://censusmapper.ca/maps/new">your own CensusMapper map</a> yet?),
and we faded out areas outside of Vancouver and colored <em>Liquor Establishments</em> in red and <em>Restaurants</em> in blue.</p>

<p>Giving a visual impression of your own dataset in relation to census data is the first step to location analysis.</p>

<h3>Populate Custom Data with Census Data</h3>

<p>Next
up is to populate your own dataset with census data for further analysis. For the restaurants, we may be interested in
attaching population in 5 minute walking distance to each location. Or maybe specific age brackets, recent immigrants
from specific countries we may want to target with a restaurant, or income data.</p>

<p>This can be a time consuming and painful process,
but we have automated this at CensusMapper.</p>

<p><a href="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/images/e-schools.png"><img  src="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/images/e-schools.png" style="width:50%;float:left;margin-right:10px;"></a>
To showcase how this works we turn to elementary school catchments in the City of Vancouver. The
<a href="http://data.vancouver.ca/datacatalogue/publicPlaces.htm">Vancouver Open Data Catalogue</a> for the catchment areas. The
areas are quite out of date, but that suits us well since we will compare it to 2011 census data. We will look at the
school aged population in each catchment.</p>

<p>The general census release data does not fit our task perfectly, the census splits by age in early May 2011 and not by
year born and it does not have fine enough age brackets to estimating accurate school catchment numbers.
<a href="http://www.bcstats.gov.bc.ca/StatisticsBySubject/Demography/PopulationEstimates.aspx">BC Stats</a> has finer age brackets
computed to school district (not catchment) boundaries, but their estimates are ridiculously far off of census numbers
when using matching age brackets and years that this is sure to give useless results.</p>

<p>Using the visual overlay we notice that the catchment areas do fit boundaries of Dissemination Areas shown on the map
reasonably well, with some exceptions. The same cannot be said for Census Tracts, and since we are using only census
data and not NHS data we can be reasonably confident that Dissemination Area data is fairly accurate.</p>

<p>Next we use the built-in CensusMapper functionality to automatically populate the catchment areas with the census
data we are interested
in. When Dissemination Areas don&rsquo;t line up with the catchment boundaries we go down to Dissemination Blocks to estimate
how many children live on what side of the catchment boundary. We
<a href="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2016/04/06/tod/">previously explained this process in more detail</a>, the result is
a spreadsheet with the population data by age for each catchment area.</p>

<div id='schools'></div>


<div><script src="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/javascripts/colorbrewer.js" charset="utf-8"></script></div>


<div><script src="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/javascripts/school_bar_graph.js" charset="utf-8"></script></div>


<p>Pretty simple, just a couple of mouse clicks.</p>

<h3>Custom Census Data Mapping</h3>

<p>Sometimes it is not practical to map custom data on CensusMapper. Maybe the custom data is too sensitive to be uploaded
to CensusMapper servers. Or it is quite complex and is better mapped separately. So we created an API to pull in
census data from CensusMapper to easily show census data on custom maps. And dynamically mix in your own data. As an
example we mix census data with data from BCAssessment, again obtained through the
<a href="http://vancouver.ca/your-government/open-data-catalogue.aspx">Vancouver Open Data Catalogue</a> (and enriched with
<a href="http://www.metrovancouver.org/data">open data from Metro Vancouver</a>).
For demonstration purposes take Dissemination Area
geographies and Dwelling Characteristic data from CensusMapper and mash it up with our
<a href="http://mountainmath.ca/map/assessment?zoom=14&amp;lat=49.2604&amp;lng=-123.1417&amp;layer=14&amp;mapBase=2">processed assessment data</a>
to explore the <a href="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2016/06/17/sdh-zoning-and-land-use/">differences in how single family properties are classified</a>.</p>

<p><a href="https://mountainmath.ca/census_mix/map?mapBase=2&layer=0" target="_blank"><img  src="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/images/sfh_unit_count.png" style="width:50%;float:right;margin-left:10px;"></a>
For example we can compare BCAssessment single family lot count to Stats Canada unit count in the dissemination areas
that are exclusively made up of single family lots. This gives an indication of how many suites and laneway houses there
are in those areas. The census is prone to undercount units, but generally does a better job than others counting them.</p>

<p><a href="https://mountainmath.ca/census_mix/map?mapBase=2&layer=5" target="_blank"><img  src="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/images/illegal_units.png" style="width:50%;float:left;margin-right:10px;"></a>
One of the reasons why census unit counts come up higher than other methods is that the census also counts illegal units,
which naturally are not part of other official government counts. There are different reasons why a suite may be illegal.
It could simply be that the owner has not made the effort to register it, more likely the suite may not be up to code.
And in some cases, a property may have more than one suite in the main building, which is illegal in the City of Vancouver.
The latter ones we can pick out in census data, since a house with two units &ndash; so three dwelling units in one house in
total &ndash; is classified as being an &ldquo;Apartment, building that has fewer than five storeys&rdquo;. So in dissemination areas that
only have duplex or single family lots as residential land uses based on assessment and land use data, we can look for
how many dwelling units the census places in an &ldquo;Apartment, building that has fewer than five storeys&rdquo;. And
<a href="https://mountainmath.ca/census_mix/map?mapBase=2&amp;layer=5">map them</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[SDH Zoning and Land Use]]></title>
    <link href="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2016/06/17/sdh-zoning-and-land-use/"/>
    <updated>2016-06-17T09:34:37-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2016/06/17/sdh-zoning-and-land-use</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Recently the question around the amount of space taken up (exclusively) by single detached houses has show up on my
Twitter feed citing that
SFH take up <a href="https://twitter.com/WayneFougere/status/743211599821844481">70%</a>,
<a href="https://twitter.com/MitchellReardon/status/739957295564476416">66%</a>,
and <a href="https://twitter.com/karensawa/status/743235428011020288">57%</a>,
<a href="http://www.cknw.com/2016/06/02/the-lynda-steele-show-bob-rennie-on-supply-and-demand/">56% (timestamp 3:50)</a>.
I personally have thrown in
<a href="https://twitter.com/vb_jens/status/738608945741238272">34%</a> as a contender. And, just for the fun of it, by the end of
this post I will have thrown 33% and 28% and my favorite, 81%, into the mix.</p>

<p>What&rsquo;s going on, how can there be such a large range of estimates for what seems to be a simple question? The answer
lies in the details of what exactly the question is asking, all of the above numbers are correct answers to one particular
version of very similar questions.</p>

<h3>TL;DR</h3>

<p>The takeaway I think is most useful for general purposes:</p>

<pre><code>35% of all households live on single family and duplex properties
making up 81% of Vancouver's residential land, while the     
remaining 65% of households live on 19% of the residential land. 
</code></pre>

<!-- more -->


<p>There are two fundamental ways to attack the question. One is through zoning, that is to look at area where only SDH can
be built. The other is through land use, that is looking at what area is currently occupied by SDH lots.</p>

<h3>Single Detached Houses</h3>

<p>First we need to understand what we mean by single detached house. There are two common, but quite different definitions
out there. One stems from the zoning code and refers to a property that is not stratified and has a single main structure
on it, possibly with one suite, and possibly a laneway house. This is the definition most commonly used. When someone says
they own a single family house, this is what they are talking about. Let&rsquo;s call them <em>single detached properties</em>.
There are around 75,000 of these in the City of Vancouver.</p>

<p>Stats Canada employs a different definition. To them a <em>single detached dwelling</em> is single dwelling unit comprised of a
free-standing (detached) structure. A <em>single detached property</em> may contain exactly one dwelling unit, in which case
Stats Canada would also call it a <em>single detached dwelling</em>. If the house has a secondary suite, Stats Canda would
classify it as a <em>duplex</em>. If it has a laneway house, Stats Canada would classify the laneway house as a separate
<em>single detached dwelling</em>. Stats Canada reports 47,530 <em>single detached dwellings</em> in the City of Vancouver.</p>

<p>Because of this discrepancy, sometimes it is useful to look as single family houses and duplexes combined. Especially
if one wants to mix in census data to for example look at the number of households that live in these dwellings. While
there are about 75,000 <em>single detached properties</em> in Vancouver, it is fair to assume that there are significantly more
than 75,000 households living on these properties once we account for secondary suites and laneway houses.</p>

<h3>Zoning</h3>

<p><a href="http://vancouver.ca/files/cov/Zoning-Map-Vancouver.pdf" target="_blank"><img  src="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/images/zoning_van_pdf.png" style="width:50%;float:right;margin-left:10px;"></a>
Vancouver is divided up into zones that determine what can (and cannot) be legally built on the land.
If one is primarily concerned with the area of land that where only single detached houses can be built, then zoning is
the right metric to look at.</p>

<p>There are two zones that essentially only allow single family houses as residential properties, the RS zones and,
to some extent, First Shaughnessy. Each of these has it&rsquo;s own pitfalls. The first issue is that parks are generally zoned
RS, but one cannot build single family homes in parks. Moreover, while RS does not allow residential land uses other
than single detached houses, it does allow for other land uses, like parks, schools, assisted living and other institutional
uses. So RS zoned land area is a poor proxy for the question of where single family houses could be built. At the very
<a href="https://mountainmath.ca/map/assessment?zoom=13&lat=49.2517&lng=-123.1232&layer=6" target="_blank"><img  src="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/images/zoning_van.png" style="width:50%;float:left;margin-right:10px;"></a>
least we should exclude parks from the equation, but probably also schools and other institutional land uses. After all,
it is delusional to think that even if a school were to close down and the land be sold for development that single
detached dwelling would be built on that land. Next comes the question if we should only include the lots that single
family homes could be built on, or also include the surrounding roads. After all, the roads are needed to serve the lots.
But they also serve the schools and parks, so maybe only a certain portion of the roads should be included? It gets messy,
the second image shows only non-institutional and non-park properties (no roads) coloured by zone, interactive version
<a href="http://mountainmath.ca/map/assessment?zoom=14&amp;lat=49.2517&amp;lng=-123.1232&amp;layer=6">here</a>.</p>

<p>The numbers between 70% and 56% mentioned up top are (probably) derived using some version of zoned area, possibly excluding
parks or schools for some, but including roads within RS zoning. It is easy to underestimate
the space roads take up in the City of Vancouver, overall roads right of ways make up 28% of City of Vancouver land.</p>

<p>At the end of this though process, we are starting to gravitate away from zoning and toward land use.</p>

<h3>Land Use</h3>

<p>We can simplify the discussion by asking how much space currently is taken up by single family properties. The answer
to this is 33%. I have previously written about the
<a href="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2016/02/29/land-use/">land use breakdown</a> for Metro Vancouver municipalities, but
single detached homes were not broken out separately, single detached and duplex properties combined take up 34% of
Vancouver&rsquo;s land. One can play the numbers a little more, maybe only look at single detached properties within RS zoning.
That puts the number at 28%. Throw in Shaugnessy and it rises to 29%. Recall that this excludes roads right of way.</p>

<p><a href="https://mountainmath.ca/land_use/map?zoom=13&lat=49.2544&lng=-123.1268&mu_filter=[%22VA%22]&lu_filter_n=[]" target="_blank"><img  src="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/images/land_use_van.png" style="width:50%;float:right;margin-left:10px;"></a>
Here is an interactive (data-heavy) map that shows the land use for
<a href="https://mountainmath.ca/land_use/map?zoom=13&amp;lat=49.2544&amp;lng=-123.1268&amp;mu_filter=[%22VA%22]&amp;lu_filter_n=[]">just for the City of Vancouver (plus Musqueam 2)</a>.</p>

<h3>Multi-Unit Housing</h3>

<p>One can ask the same question about other housing types, and we can read off the numbers from the
<a href="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2016/02/29/land-use/">land use breakdown</a>. 3.2% of land is taken up with low rise
apartments, 1.9% with townhouses, 1.2% with high rise, 0.3% by non-market housing, 0.9% by mixed use low rise and 0.7%
by mixed use high rise. Adding all of this up we get that 8.2% of land is taken up by housing that is not single detached
or duplex. And it also includes some commercial space in the mixed use developments.</p>

<p>That means that overall in Vancouver 42.2% of the land is used for residential purposes, 81% of which is occupied by
single detached and duplex properties and the remaining 19% is occupied by all other building forms.</p>

<h3>Share of Households in Different Land Uses</h3>

<p>We may be interested in the population density these different land use patterns entail. That&rsquo;s where things get a little
tricky, we will turn to the census for answers. From the standard census releases we can only discern the share of
dwellings that are single detached and duplex properties combined, and that number is 93,370 dwelling units. Overall
there are 264,575 dwelling units, so single family and duplex units make up 35% of all dwelling units in CoV. Glossing
over the issue that some of these may not be occupied we conclude that 35% of all households live on single family and
duplex properties making up 81% of Vancouver&rsquo;s residential land,
while the remaining 65% of households live on 19% of the residential land.</p>

<h3>Fine Print</h3>

<p>There are a number of issues with the data that might change the numbers slightly, but not by much. The first is that
the land use dataset I use lump the City of Vancouver together with Musqueam 2. That slightly changes the land use mix
and areas reported, but the effect on all numbers mentioned here is very small. Next up is the number of dwelling units
on single detached or duplex properties. The census number is likely to under report some secondary suites (although it
captures more than BCAssessment does), and properties with more than one secondary suite (so some illegal suites) will
show up as an apartment building in census data. Moreover, the census data is from 2011, the land use data we used is
about a year old, and we have manually adjusted for some recent upzoning. So there is some give or take in the numbers,
I would not expect more than a one percent move in the numbers I reported as a result.</p>

<h3>Further Questions</h3>

<p>This does not answer the question what percentage of the population lives on single family or duplex properties. To
estimate that one would have to first estimate the number of people per houshold for the different land uses, as we
expect them to differ significantly. One can start exploring how the number of people per dwelling unit varies
<a href="https://censusmapper.ca/maps/391">on CensusMapper</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[FSR]]></title>
    <link href="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2016/05/20/density/"/>
    <updated>2016-05-20T22:51:29-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2016/05/20/density</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="https://mountainmath.ca/map/assessment?layer=16" target="_blank"><img  src="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/images/fsr.png" style="width:50%;float:right;margin-left:10px;"></a>
Ever since I played with the <a href="http://mountainmath.ca/vancouver_lidar/map">LIDAR-generated building height data</a> I thought
that I should use that to map gross floor area (GFA) and floor space ratio (FSR). Gross floor area is the total floor area
inside the building envelope. So for a three storey building, it is the area of the footprint times three.
Floor space ratio is the GFA divided by the area of the parcel it sits on. There are several reasons why this may be
interesting.</p>

<p>GFA is the currency of the developer. Especially once we enter the world of apartment or commercial buildings,
gross floor area is directly proportional to the amount of money a developer can charge for a property, either when stratified
and sold or when rented out.</p>

<p>FSR on the other hand is a measure of density, and it is the currency of the zoning code. Height and site coverage are
also regulated in the zoning code and there is an obvious relationship to FSR. But because GFA is so important to the
developer, FSR usually receives more attention in public discussions.</p>

<p>Read on or <a href="https://mountainmath.ca/map/assessment?layer=16" target="_blank" class='btn btn-default'>head straight for the interactive map</a> to browse
Vancouver by FSR. Read the disclaimer at the bottom before using any data for purposes other than general reference.</p>

<!-- more -->


<h3>Maximum Allowable FSR and Spot Zoning.</h3>

<p>The maximum allowable FSR is set by the zoning code. Because land is so valuable in Vancouver, most people will try
to maximize GFA when building a new building, so they typically go right up to the maximum allowable FSR. Previously we have
<a href="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2016/03/05/physical-sfh-form-over-time/">examined the effects of various related metrics like height and site coverage</a>
for single family homes.</p>

<p><a href="https://mountainmath.ca/map/assessment?zoom=15&lat=49.2599&lng=-123.1583&layer=6" target="_blank"><img  src="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/images/spot-zoning.png" style="width:30%;float:right;margin-left:10px;"></a>
At least this is how it works for RS/RT zones. If you are looking to develop a different property, say a mixed use or
an apartment building or commercial building you will probably be looking to up-zone. That is, you will try to convince
the city (and the local population) to allow you to build more GFA than zoning would allow. If successful the city will
create a new zone just for your property and ask for some compensation in form of CACs (aiming to recoup about 80% of the
uplift in value the up-zoning creates) in return. That process is called
spot zoning and it can be seen in form of the little &ldquo;Comprehensive Development&rdquo; zones that are visible as yellow
sprinkles in the otherwise quite uniform zones on the map.</p>

<p>In reality the process of up-zoning a property is a lot more complex, arduous and time consuming, which favours larger
developers with deep pockets that can take the risk and sit out the long process of eventually obtaining higher GFA. One
of the many reasons why the &ldquo;missing middle&rdquo; is missing.</p>

<h3>Mapping Density</h3>

<p><a href="https://censusmapper.ca/maps/302#16/49.2375/-123.1573" target="_blank"><img  src="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/images/kerrisdale_people.png" style="width:30%;float:left;margin-right:10px;"></a>
From Census data we know the <a href="https://censusmapper.ca/maps/302">nighttime density</a>, that is where people live and sleep.
But we don&rsquo;t know where they are
during the daytime.</p>

<p><a href="https://mountainmath.ca/map/assessment?zoom=16&lat=49.238&lng=-123.154&layer=16" target="_blank"><img  src="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/images/kerrisdale_fsr.png" style="width:30%;float:right;margin-left:10px;"></a>
FSR is also often seen as such a measure of density, although it only focuses on density on property parcels and neglects
all the space between parcels, like roads right of ways and parks.</p>

<p>In mostly residential neighbourhoods the two densities correspond quite closely, but in areas with large commercial buildings
(nighttime) population density can be quite low while FSR is very high as can easily be seen by comparing the two maps.</p>

<p><a href="https://mountainmath.ca/assessment_gl/map?zoom=16&lat=49.2384&lng=-123.1567" target="_blank"><img  src="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/images/kerrisdale_tax.png" style="width:30%;float:left;margin-right:10px;"></a>
<a href="https://mountainmath.ca/assessment_gl/map">Tax density</a>, that is property taxes collected per area, give another view of
&ldquo;density&rdquo; in the city that highlights relative property values and emphasises commercial land use that pays five times
the residential tax rate.</p>

<p>There are lots of other measures of density that are important for different purposes, for example <a href="http://mountainmath.ca/census3">household density</a>
(in full 3D, requires modern computer),
<a href="https://censusmapper.ca/maps/359">the density of private dwelling units</a> or <a href="https://censusmapper.ca/maps/35">toddler density</a> just to name a few.</p>

<h3>Next Steps</h3>

<p>There are several directions I want to take this. Now that FSR is available for all properties, I can
compare purpose built rental buildings to strata buildings. For example, in my
<a href="http://mountainmath.ca/assessment/split_map">Buildings and Dirt map</a> I can&rsquo;t integrate purpose
built rentals because I don&rsquo;t know how many rental units they have. The assessment data from the Vancouver Open Data portal,
does not have that information, and BC Assessment won&rsquo;t share it (in a hassle-free way). But I can make a similar map based on GFA instead of
number of units and examine
how GFA effect land and building values across different land uses. And in many ways GFA may be a better unit for comparisons
than number of suites.</p>

<p><a href="https://mountainmath.ca/map/assessment?zoom=13&lat=49.2488&lng=-123.1211&layer=17&filter=res" target="_blank"><img  src="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/images/value_per_gfa.png" style="width:50%;float:right;margin-left:10px;"></a>
Or I can just make a <a href="https://mountainmath.ca/map/assessment?zoom=14&amp;lat=49.2684&amp;lng=-123.1354&amp;layer=17">straight-up map of total assessed value per GFA</a>.
And maybe add a filter to only show this for <a href="https://mountainmath.ca/map/assessment?zoom=13&amp;lat=49.2488&amp;lng=-123.1211&amp;layer=17&amp;filter=res">residential and mixed use units</a>
like in the image if that&rsquo;s what we are interested in.</p>

<p>Another interesting application is to use this data to do something along the lines of this
<a href="http://www.nytimes.com/interactive/2016/05/19/upshot/forty-percent-of-manhattans-buildings-could-not-be-built-today.html?_r=0">excellent analysis the New York Times published</a>
for Vancouver. FSR, next to building heights and lot coverage that I
<a href="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2016/03/05/physical-sfh-form-over-time/">have already analysed from a different angle</a>,
is an important metric to detect buildings that could not be rebuilt under regular zoning.</p>

<p>Lastly, having data on building GFA, together with assessment open data, allows for reverse-engineering of the GFA of individual
strata units. That makes the analysis of condo assessment data more meaningful as we can analyse assessed condo values by
unit size. One of the reasons why we are only talking about single family homes (or in some cases RS zoned homes) and
not condos is that it is very easy to compare single family homes. But comparing condos doesn&rsquo;t make much sense unless
one also has data on the size of each condo. And this has probably focused the public debate too much on single family
homes when we should be paying a lot more attention to condos. And purpose built rental units.</p>

<h3>Disclaimer</h3>

<p>The FSR was estimated using coarse building data extracted from LIDAR data. The motivation was to use the FSR for aggregate
analysis and not for getting accurate estimates of individual buildings.</p>

<p>Secondary buildings like garages or laneway houses are only inconsistently detected and mapped. The data is from 2009,
buildings built after that are greyed out.</p>

<p>The algorithm to compute FSR
from this building data is rather crude and only makes rudimentary attempts to adjust for varying floor heights of buildings
different for land uses, overhangs and eyebrows and dealing with pitched roofs or mechanical units.</p>

<p>Building data was clipped to property polygons to deal with cases of buildings spanning several legal lots or not properly
separated.</p>

<p>The FSR computed only roughly resembles the FSR defined in building codes. In particular our model with grossly
overestimate the FSR for buildings with overhanging features like
the Lookout on the Harbour Centre.</p>

<p>Block level aggregates will underestimate FSR in the presence of properties excluded from the FSR calculation.</p>

<p>Do not be use the FSR estimates as an authoritative source for any individual building FSR.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Census Mapping for Everyone]]></title>
    <link href="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2016/05/04/census-mapping-for-everyone/"/>
    <updated>2016-05-04T11:45:39-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2016/05/04/census-mapping-for-everyone</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>At CensusMapper, we have come a long way from first <a href="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2015/06/23/vancouver-2011-census-data-on-housing/">dabbling in census data</a> to
building out a <a href="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2015/09/28/census-mapper/">platform to map data Canada wide</a>, adding
the ability to <a href="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2015/10/24/census-drilldown/">easily drill down into individual census regions</a>,
<a href="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2015/12/27/canvas-vs-svg/">improving mapping efficiency</a>, adding the ability to
<a href="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2016/04/20/tod-mode-share/">automatically populate custom geographic data with census variables</a>
and <a href="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2016/05/02/census-week/">adding older census data</a>.</p>

<p>We believe all of these are comparatively small steps compared to the opening up of map making capabilities for everyone
that we are rolling out today. Free to use, free of charge. Statistic Canada <a href="http://www.statcan.gc.ca/eng/reference/licence-eng">opened up census data</a>
for anyone to use, but the sheer volume of available data and complexities of mapping geographic data has kept this
inaccessible to many.</p>

<p>By opening up basic map making capabilities to everyone we are putting the liberating that data from depth of spreadsheets and
database servers and opening it up to everyone. One map at a time.  Read on for tips and tricks or head right on over
to <a href="https://censusmapper.ca" class="btn btn-primary">Censusmapper</a> to make your first CensusMapper map!</p>

<!-- more -->


<h3>Simple Maps</h3>

<p><img  src="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/images/make_a_map.png"  style="width:30%;float:right;margin-left:10px;">
To make your own map, start by choosing &ldquo;Start New 2011 Map&rdquo; from the &ldquo;Make a Map&rdquo; menu. If you are planning on saving
and sharing your map you should log in or create an account first, but you can play with mapping census data without an account.</p>

<p><img  src="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/images/signin.png"  style="width:25%;float:left;margin-right:10px;">
We tried to make logging in super simple by providing oAuth signup with popular providers, but you can also go the old
fashioned way and create an account manually by providing username (email) and custom password.</p>

<p><img  src="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/images/census_variables_menu.png"  style="width:30%;float:right;margin-left:10px;">
To start your new map, navigate down to the census variable picker at the bottom of the sidebar. Click the bars
to expand or collapse them. Once you found a variable you want to map, click
the &lsquo;globe&rsquo; icon and select how you want to map the variable.</p>

<p><img  src="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/images/map_variable.png"  style="width:50%;float:left;margin-right:10px;">
Depending on what variable you choose you have the option to map simply map the variable, in this case the total number
of people that are married or living with a common law partner, or map the variable as a percentage of a &ldquo;parent&rdquo; variable,
so in this case map the percentage of people that are married or living with a common law partner out of all people 15 years
or over. If in doubt what the variables mean, head over to the
<a href="https://www12.statcan.gc.ca/census-recensement/2011/ref/dict/98-301-X2011001-eng.pdf">Census Dictionary</a>
to look up the definitions.</p>

<p><img  src="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/images/finished_map_1.png"  style="width:50%;float:right;margin-left:10px;">
Once you press the button CensusMapper will do it&rsquo;s magic and map the data for you. Zoom pan and use the search bar to expore
the data across different regions and geographic aggregation levels in Canada. You may want to edit the automatically
generated map label to make it more concise.</p>

<p><img  src="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/images/finished_map_2.png"  style="width:30%;float:left;margin-right:10px;">
To style your map you can select the &ldquo;Colors&rdquo; option in the orange map editor menu in the sidebar.</p>

<p><img  src="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/images/finished_map_3.png"  style="width:50%;float:right;margin-left:10px;">
There you can style your map by selecting a custom color scheme and fine tune your domain cutoffs.</p>

<p><img  src="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/images/finished_map_4.png"  style="width:50%;float:left;margin-right:10px;">
If you were signed in you could now select the &ldquo;Save Map&rdquo; option from the map editor menu and add a map title and a map
description. Map descriptions can be styled in <a href="https://daringfireball.net/projects/markdown/">markdown</a>.</p>

<p>Maps can tell many different stories, use the map description to give some background and rational for your
map. A good map story might link to different views of the map to support the story telling. You can use the &ldquo;Paste link
to current view into description&rdquo; button to link to different map views. You can also link to different CensusMapper maps
to create deeply integrated map stories. Rich map stories can provide powerful insights into our communities.</p>

<p>If you want to share your map with others, make sure you set the map visibility from &ldquo;Private&rdquo; to &ldquo;Published&rdquo;. Otherwise
others will get an &ldquo;access denied&rdquo; message when they attempt to view the map. Published maps will automatically appear on
the extended map list, so please take some time and write appropriate descriptions that others can enjoy them.</p>

<p>Head on over to <a href="https://censusmapper.ca" class="btn btn-primary">Censusmapper</a> to get started.</p>

<h3>Advanced Maps</h3>

<p>The ability to quickly map any census variable is quite liberating. At the same time it is also restrictive. Imagine
all the things that could be mapped if you could combine census variables in other ways. And CensusMapper has that
capability to dynamically weave a number of census variables into a function to be mapped. But with that comes another
level of complexity and potential pitfalls that, at the moment, prevents us from opening this up to the general public.</p>

<p>At the same time, we are still trying to figure out the overall funding model at CensusMapper. We believe that we have
plenty of value in our advanced mapping capabilities, as well as in our ability to
<a href="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2016/04/20/tod-mode-share/">automatically populate custom geographic data with census variables</a>
and our backend data analysis capabilities to focus on paid products that allows us to open up the Simple Map model
for everyone for free. At CensusMapper, we love open data. And with time as we refine our funding model we may open up
more advanced mapping capabilities to put more data into the palm of everyone&rsquo;s hands.</p>

<h3>Our Worries</h3>

<p>We are also a bit worried about how CensusMapper will be used. The internet has the ability to turn the most beautiful
thing into something ugly, and we are hoping that mappers will use the tool responsibly and make meaningful maps that
tell a story, instead of vanity maps or maps meant to isolate or smear specific groups of people. If we feel that the
tool is being abused we might have to enforce a real name policy or partially close down CensusMapper. Please map responsibly.</p>

<h3>Bugs</h3>

<p>If you find any, let us know. The tool should work well on Mac using Chrome, Safari or Firefox and should work reasonably
well on Windows with Chrome and Firefox. iPad, iPhone and modern Android should also work well. Please contact us if you find
anything not working properly.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Census Week]]></title>
    <link href="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2016/05/02/census-week/"/>
    <updated>2016-05-02T11:07:07-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2016/05/02/census-week</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img  src="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/images/census.jpg"  style="width:50%;float:right;margin-left:10px;">
At CensusMapper we are super excited about Census Week 2016. Data is increasingly getting incorporated into local and
regional decision making. At CensusMapper we have been working to facilitate this by making this wealth of information
more accessible to everyone. To celebrate Census Week 2016 we have updated CensusMapper with 2006 census data for easy
comparisons with the 2011 data. And we have given CensusMapper a face lift by adding a histogram widget that interacts
with the mapping data. Watch for more exciting updates this week or read on for a sneak peak!</p>

<!-- more -->


<h3>2006 Census</h3>

<p><a href="http://http://censusmapper.ca/maps/37" target="_blank"><img  src="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/images/affordability2011.png"  style="width:50%;float:right;margin-left:10px;"></a>
<a href="http://http://censusmapper.ca/maps/293" target="_blank"><img  src="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/images/affordability2006.png"  style="width:50%;float:left;margin-right:10px;"></a>
We re-worked the backend to make it easy to add and map older censuses. And of course the 2016 census, once it becomes
available. At the first step, this allows side-by-side comparisons between different census years through our map-based
interface. As we explore this further we will add better ways to simultaneously browse two difference censuses, and we
will add a way to map data from two censuses on one the same map. Apart from some technical challenges that we know how
to handle, this also presents challenges when directly comparing the long form census to the 2011 NHS, which had different
collection methods that introduced biases that can be of the same magnitude as the changes one may want to measure.</p>

<h3>Widgets</h3>

<p>At CensusMapper we are all about interaction. We love exploring data visually, and our dynamic zoomable maps make browsing
census data very easy. But the maps are just scratching the surface. Often it is also usefuly to view a simple graph. That&rsquo;s
where the graph widgets come in, the first of which is the histogram that dynamically shows a histogram of the data visible
in the current map view.
<a href="http://censusmapper.ca/maps/76" target="_blank"><img  src="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/images/animated_rent.gif" style="margin:10px;"></a></p>

<p>And of course the widget is fully linked with the map. Hover over a map region, and it will show where the mapped value fits into
histogram. Pan and zoom and the histogram updates automatically. The other way around, hover over a histogram bin and the
corresponding regions on the map get highlighted. That makes exploring the data so much easier.</p>

<h3>Make your own maps</h3>

<p>We will roll out basic map making capabilities for everyone later this week. How will this work? Census data is huge, so
it won&rsquo;t go completely without pain. But we try to make it as easy as possible. Once the new &ldquo;Make a Map&rdquo; option becomes
available you can browse through the list of census variables and simply select which one you want to map. You will have
the option to map the value or, if it makes sense, the value as a percentage of a &ldquo;parent&rdquo; variable.
<a href="http://censusmapper.ca" target="_blank"><img  src="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/images/animated_simple.gif" style="margin:10px;"></a></p>

<p>A click of the mouse and you have a new map. Head over to the colour scheme picker and select the colour cutoffs to customize it.
You can even log in and save the map and write your own map story for the side bar, so that you can share and interactive
version of your map online. We can&rsquo;t wait getting census data into everyone&rsquo;s hands!</p>

<script>
function resetImages(){
    $('img').each(function(img){
        imgsrc = $(img).attr('src');
        if (imgsrc.slice(imgsrc.length-4)=='.gif') {
            $(img).attr('src', '');
            $(img).attr('src', imgsrc);
            
        }
    });
    setTimeout(function(){
        resetImages();
    },25000);
}
setTimeout(function(){
    resetImages();
},25000);
</script>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
