<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: canada | Mountain Doodles]]></title>
  <link href="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/categories/canada/feed.atom" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/"/>
  <updated>2017-08-06T22:35:16-07:00</updated>
  <id>http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[MountainMath]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Millennials Redux]]></title>
    <link href="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2017/08/06/millennials-redux/"/>
    <updated>2017-08-06T20:54:48-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2017/08/06/millennials-redux</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Catching up with my local news reading last night I stumbled about another
<a href="https://beta.theglobeandmail.com/real-estate/vancouver/priced-out-of-downtown-vancouver-millennials-are-building-hipsturbia/article35884038/">new report on millennials</a>.</p>

<p>The notion that millennials are fleeing Vancouver is a recurring theme in the Vancouver press, and we have addressed
some of the <a href="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2017/05/16/lifeblood/">problems in the data used to support that claim before</a>.</p>

<p>Sadly, this new article&rsquo;s use of data is no less problematic, and the topic, as well as the data misrepresentations, are serious enough that
I felt they need addressing so as not do distract from the actual real problems that millennials are facing. Problems that are quite
different from those the 25 to 39 year old age cohort was facing 20 years ago. Groups like Generation Squeeze
have done a good job nailing some of that down in the data.</p>

<h3>The Data Rabbit Hole Trap</h3>

<p>To the data-minded person reading the article there are a number of red flags that go off throughout. Many of these can
be attributed to today&rsquo;s typical data-adverse journalism, but typically the actual hard numbers in the article hold up and are just
misrepresented to varying degrees. What got me stumbling in this article was the data chart at the bottom claiming that the 25 to 39 year old age cohort
in the &ldquo;UEL&rdquo; grew by 5% between 1996 and 2016. The UEL of course is a quasi-municipality that sits wedged between the City of Vancouver and UBC,
but many people less attuned to data and administrative details use the term to refer to various portions of the region west of the Pacific Spirit Park,
sometimes including &ldquo;Little Australia&rdquo; which is west of the Park but an actual part of the UEL and sometimes excluding it.</p>

<p>I took it to mean some version of UEL and UBC/UNA combined, and the 5% number looked suspicious to me. The population in that area more than tripled
during that period, one would expect the change in that age cohort to be much larger. So I started to dig into the numbers.</p>

<p>The first step was to look up the numbers for the City of Vancouver since there are no issues with administrative boundaries between 1996 and 2016,
just to make sure that the data was labelled correctly and it was really representing the percentage change in the number of millennials between 1996 and 2016.
But the number I got was different from the one in the article. The article lists a 10% increase, I calculated an 11% increase. 11.2% to be precise, so
there was no chance that this was a rounding issue.</p>

<p>And the data rabbit hole opens up, sucks me in and the trap closes.</p>

<h3>The Data</h3>

<p>The data is, for the most part, reasonably straight forward. I just grabbed the 1996 count og 25 to 39 year olds, then the 2016 counts and compared them.
One problem is boundary changes. Administrative boundaries don&rsquo;t stay fixed. And boundary changes don&rsquo;t always show up when just looking at non-geographic
data, names or even the uniqe geographic identifiers don&rsquo;t necessarily change when census boundaries change. Looking that the geographic data for both
censuses one immediately notices that the UEL/UBC/UNA area changed a lot (and also got new geographic identifiers), and Coquitlam changed too.
That complicates things a little, the UEL/UBC/UNA part is easy enough to deal with. In 1996 that area was called the &ldquo;University Endowment Area&rdquo;, in 2016
that same area can be obtained by adding to census tracts. Coquitlam is a little trickier and I wasn&rsquo;t interested enough in figuring out the details so
I decided to ignore it.</p>

<p>Step one, trying to reproduce the graph in the newspaper, is below with blue bars, with the graph from the newspaper in red bars for reference.</p>

<div class="half-image"><a href="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/images/millennial_grap_1.png"><img src="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/images/millennial_grap_1.png" ><p>News Story</p></a></div>


<div class="half-image"><a href="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/images/millennial_grap_2.png"><img src="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/images/millennial_grap_2.png" ><p>Actual Data</p></a></div>


<p>There is definitely a correspondence between the graphs, but the numbers don&rsquo;t quite match up. I have no idea how the &ldquo;UEL&rdquo; numbers were derived for
the article. But I have an explanation for the difference in the other municipality&rsquo;s numbers. Looking at the graphs
suggests that a larger denominator was used in the article, and indeed the numbers match up perfectly if I were to divide the
difference of population in the 25-39 year
old cohort by the 2016 number instead of the 1996 number. An embarrassing data mistake to be sure, but nothing out of the ordinary for today&rsquo;s
news stories.</p>

<p>I can&rsquo;t explain why Surrey, the city with the largest gain in millennials, was dropped from the data used for the story.</p>

<h3>Data Representation</h3>

<p>But these data problems are really only a side show to the real issue.
The most important question is what data to use for what purpose. The article chose to use the change in the total number of millennials
to support the notion that the 25 to 39 year old cohort are shunting the City of Vancouver for some of the more outlying regions.
The obvious issue with that
is that that measure is confounded by population growth. If the population is growing, so will the number of millennials,
even if the share of millennials
in the population did not change. For this story, this is clearly a very poor choice of data representation.</p>

<p>As a first approximation to understanding where that age cohort settles in 2016 compared to 1996 one can look at the respectives shares of the
population in those age cohorts. The only problem, the pretext of the story goes away when one represents the data in this way.
<a href="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/images/millennial_grap_3.png"><img  src="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/images/millennial_grap_3.png" style="width:50%;float:right;margin-left:10px;"></a></p>

<p>What stands out is that the share of 25-39 year olds dropped in all areas. Some of that is just part of the
changing makeup of the population in general. And
one sees that the City of Vancouver not only has the highest share of 25-39 year olds, it also experienced the lowest drop.</p>

<h3>Framing of the Data</h3>

<p>The other part of the story that irks me is the deep confusion and free mixing of two different concepts. One is that of migration, that is
(the same) people moving from one area to another over some time period. The other is that of the number or share of (different)
people in a secific age cohort at two distinct points in time. Nathan Lauster has added some very
<a href="https://homefreesociology.wordpress.com/2016/02/12/is-the-lifeblood-of-vancouver-leaving/">good analysis</a> to this topic, and has
followed up with a series of blog posts. And this was picked up in various news articles too.</p>

<p>This article not only lacks appreciation for this important distinction by talking about &ldquo;migration&rdquo; when really comparing age cohorts, but
it takes it to the next level by talking about &ldquo;millennials&rdquo; as being 25-39 year old in 1996 (as well as in 2016), which is
comically absurd.</p>

<p>Not sure what to make of the authors assertion that BC Assessment is in the business of enumerating 25 to 39 year olds between 1996 and 2016,
I wonder how people get stuff like this past their editors.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Lifeblood]]></title>
    <link href="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2017/05/16/lifeblood/"/>
    <updated>2017-05-16T13:52:05-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2017/05/16/lifeblood</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="https://censusmapper.ca/maps/731"><img src="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/images/net_animated.gif" style="width:50%;float:right;margin-left:10px;"></a>
Ever since that <a href="https://www.bloomberg.com/news/articles/2016-03-14/millennials-flee-vancouver-for-cities-with-more-affordable-homes">Bloomberg article whose claims nobody could reproduce</a>,
where the author refused to disclose what data was used, but that
got recycled all across the local press there has been a hightened interest
in migration patterns in Vancouver. Nathan Lauster took it upon himself to
dig deeper and look if <a href="https://homefreesociology.wordpress.com/2016/02/12/is-the-lifeblood-of-vancouver-leaving/">Vancouver&rsquo;s lifeblood was really leaving</a>,
which he kept elaborating on as better data became available until the
<a href="https://homefreesociology.wordpress.com/2017/05/05/good-age-specific-net-migration-estimates-come-in-threes/">most recent iteration</a>
that compares Metro Vancouver to other Candian metropolitan areas as well
as the City of Vancouver to other cities within Metro Vancouver using 2016 census data.</p>

<p>This is seriously good work and we thought it would be helpful to reproduce Lauster&rsquo;s methods
in CensusMapper. The result is a series of maps, one for each five-year age cohort, that
visualized net migration of the cohort geographically, while hovering over a
region reproduces Lauster&rsquo;s net migration bar graph for that region.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>With CensusMapper, we instantly get the ability to dig into areas to observe
finer net migration patterns, and to pan across the country to compare different
regions.</p>

<p>For Metro Vancouver, we can see how we have strong net in-migration in all younger
cohorts, including children. And as Lauster observed, we see a net out-migration
of 50 to 60 year olds.</p>

<p>For the City of Vancouver we see a net in-migration for 5 to 30 year olds, with
basically all other age groups exhibiting net out-migration. This is echoed by
Burnaby and New Westminster, and to a lesser extend Richmond. We can zoom in
further to the Census Tract level to observe spacial patterns of net migration
at the sub-municipal level. There we see that net migration of the under 5 cohort
and the 20 to 24 cohort are almost exact mirror images. The strongest signal
comes from the town centres of the region, that get flooded as the 20 to 24 year
old cohort ages into the 25 to 29 year old cohort. As they form families and have kids,
the flood reverses and as many children that under 5 that lived in these areas don&rsquo;t
live there any more when they advance to the 5 to 9 cohort.</p>

<p>Sadly we don&rsquo;t have common tiles for other censuses that would allow for hassle-free
comparisons to detect changes over time. (It&rsquo;s a surprising amount of work
to get those common tilings right.) But we can compare this pattern to other
population centres in Canada, and this trend seems to hold true universally.</p>

<div class="half-image"><img src="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/images/net_van.png" ><p>Vancouver</p></div>


<div class="half-image"><img src="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/images/net_tor.png" ><p>Toronto</p></div>


<div class="half-image"><img src="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/images/net_mon.png" ><p>Montreal</p></div>


<div class="half-image"><img src="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/images/net_cal.png" ><p>Calgary</p></div>


<p>Metro Vancouver as a region certainly looks quite healthy in terms of the net migration of it&rsquo;s age groups.
The migration patterns within the region also seem to be consistent with other population centres in Canada.
These alone, at least at the qualitative level that we are mapping, does not seem to explain the
prevalent feeling of millennials &ldquo;fleeing&rdquo; Vancouver. Maybe a more quantitative approach could
dig up more. Or it could be that families moving away from the central regions is generally
perceived as a &ldquo;move up&rdquo; in most cities, but in Vancouver it is viewed as &ldquo;moving down&rdquo;.</p>

<h3>Technical Details</h3>

<h4>Common Geographies</h4>

<p>The first (and biggest) problem is that the 2011 and 2016 census geographies
don&rsquo;t necessarily match up. But we <a href="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2017/03/22/comparing-censuses/">solved that problem</a>
for the 2011 and 2016 censuses.</p>

<h4>Easier said than done</h4>

<p>The devil is of course always in the details, and as usual it is not until
one has reproduced something until one can fully appreciate the work that
went into the original piece. There were two main challenges for us to
reproduce this within CensusMapper.</p>

<h4>The basics</h4>

<p>What is net migration? To compute the net migration for an age group,
say the &ldquo;under 5&rdquo; (in 2011) age group, we want to compare them to an age
group in 2016. To do that we need to &ldquo;age them forward&rdquo;. Children that were
under 5 in 2011 were 5 to 9 years old in 2016. But some, in the case of
the under 5 age group only a very small fraction, won&rsquo;t have lived to 2016.
So we need to subtract those out. More formally, we need to apply the
apporpriate mortality rates as we age them forward. Then we compare
the aged-forward group to the 5 to 9 year old cohort that the 2016 census
counted, and we divide by the size of the original under 5 year old cohort
(from 2011) to get the percentage net migration.</p>

<h4>Mortality</h4>

<p>This basic fact of life makes net migration really tricky to get right.
Once we get into the older age groups, and thus higher mortality rates,
the process is extremely sensitive to changes in the mortality rates. In
CensusMapper we are using effective mortality rates of 5 year cohorts from
<a href="http://www5.statcan.gc.ca/cansim/a26?lang=eng&amp;id=1020504">CANSIM</a> for
Canada as a whole and the provinces and territories. A fair amount of
massaging is needed to make sure this works properly, in particular it
is important to interpolate the effective mortality rates as we age a
cohort forward. And one should recognise that the mortality rates are
based on the age at death, but that an age cohort in the census is, on average,
already half way through a given year in their life.</p>

<p>Additionally, there is little reason to believe that there is no geographic
variation in mortality rates within the provinces. To deal with that we
decided to add an uncertainty band to the graph that allows for a 5%
variation in mortality rates.</p>

<h4>Uncertainty</h4>

<p>The next issue is that census data underwent random rounding to an adjacent
number that&rsquo;s divisible by 5, which leads to an expected error of 1.6.
(Actual rounding gives an expected error of 1.2.)
When taking differences between censuses, that yields an expected error of 2.2.
Additionally, we don&rsquo;t know the actual number of people in each age group,
just the one the census found. The &ldquo;census undercount&rdquo; can be quite
sizable. Overall it is around 3%, but it varies by age group and geography.</p>

<p>To deal with this we add an error term of a mis-count of 5 people that
also shows up in our error bars in the graph.</p>

<h4>Fine geographies</h4>

<p>CensusMapper is great for exploring all geographic levels. But that can
lead to problems when our age cohorts become small in size. We divide
by the size of the original 2011 age group cohort, and to avoid running
into small denominator issues we cut our estimates off when there are
fewer than 50 people in a cohort. Our error bars partially take care of
this issue, but at 50 people our error bar already spans 10% points of
net migration on either side of the computed value, showing values with
even larger error bars is likely to do more harm than good.</p>

<script>
function resetImages(){
    $('img').each(function(img){
        imgsrc = $(img).attr('src');
        if (imgsrc.slice(imgsrc.length-4)=='.gif') {
            $(img).attr('src', '');
            $(img).attr('src', imgsrc);

        }
    });
    setTimeout(function(){
        resetImages();
    },35000);
}
setTimeout(function(){
    resetImages();
},35000);
</script>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Surprise Maps]]></title>
    <link href="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2017/04/10/surprise/"/>
    <updated>2017-04-10T08:43:58-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2017/04/10/surprise</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="https://censusmapper.ca/maps/668"><img src="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/images/surprise.png" style="width:50%;float:right;margin-left:10px;"></a>
At CensusMapper we like building models based on census data. We now
have a <a href="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2017/03/22/comparing-censuses/">common tiling for 2011 and 2016 geographies</a>
that allows us to easily model changes over time. After building a model
we often want to see how well the model performs. An easy way to do this is to
simply map the difference of observations and model predictions.</p>

<p>Those maps are great and it is easy to understand what is mapped. But they are difficult to interpret properly. In many cases
a better metric to map is how consistent the observations in each region are with the model. Which brings us to Bayesian surprise maps.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>There is a <a href="https://medium.com/@uwdata/surprise-maps-showing-the-unexpected-e92b67398865">great post</a> making the rounds on the
web, and when it recently <a href="https://twitter.com/LGeospatial/status/850806648201388032">showed up again in my Twitter feed</a>
I finally decided to get in on the fun.</p>

<h3>The Problem</h3>

<p><a href="https://censusmapper.ca/maps/584#15/49.2089/-123.1141"><img src="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/images/marine_gateway_nbhd.png" style="width:50%;float:left;margin-right:10px;"></a>
To understand why surprise maps can be so useful, let&rsquo;s look a a concrete example. Suppose we want to understand dwelling units
that are not used as primary residences. (And incidentally it seems that everyone currently living in Vancouver or Toronto wants to do this.) To
that end we can simply consult <a href="https://censusmapper.ca/maps/584">the map of these</a> based on the 2016 census. As we try and
understand better what is happening in each region and we zoom in more and more we start to run into issues. Consider
<a href="https://censusmapper.ca/maps/584#15/49.2089/-123.1141">this example looking at the Marine Gateway neighbourhood in Vancouver</a>. We
see two areas coloured in dark blue, indicating a high rate. The left is the site of the MC2 development that got completed
just before the census and we discussed <a href="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2017/04/03/joyce-collingwood/">earlier in detail</a>.
The right one is a large area with exactly one private dwelling unit, which happens not to be a primary residence for anyone. If
someone did use it as primary residence it would show up on the other extreme end of our colour spectrum. Either way, it does not
really give much useful information, it is mostly a distraction that takes attention away from MC2 that has a more important story
to tell.</p>

<p>More generally, areas with very low dwelling counts are much more likely to see high variations of rates of non-permanent residence buildings
purely for statistical reasons. This results in a <a href="https://censusmapper.ca/maps/584#16/49.2425/-123.1777">&ldquo;checkerboard&rdquo; pattern</a>
that is mostly due to statistical noise and hides meaningful variations in the data.</p>

<h3>Surprise maps</h3>

<p><a href="https://censusmapper.ca/maps/669#15/49.2089/-123.1141"><img src="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/images/marine_gateway_nbhd2.png" style="width:50%;float:right;margin-left:10px;"></a>
That&rsquo;s were surprise maps come in. As a first step, instead of colouring by the rate of non-primary residence dwellings,
let&rsquo;s colour by how this rate differs from our expectations. So we re-interpret our original map as mapping the difference from expectations
where the expectation is that all dwellings are used as primary residences. Alternatively we can also take the regional average
rate of non-primary residence dwellings and map the deviation from the average. Or we could build a
<a href="https://censusmapper.ca/maps/669">more elaborate model</a> using the 2011 rates and the Canada-wide average rates per net new dwelling unit.</p>

<p>Either way, what we are doing here is we make a guess what we think the rate of non-primary residence units should be in each area
and we compare it with observations. The better our guess is, the stronger the &ldquo;checkerboard&rdquo; pattern will become as the residuals
will be reduced to statistical noise. This as can easily be seen when
<a href="https://censusmapper.ca/maps/669#16/49.2425/-123.1777">comparing the more advanced model</a>
to the <a href="https://censusmapper.ca/maps/584#16/49.2425/-123.1777">checkerboard observed using the &ldquo;zero&rdquo; model</a>. In practice that
means that we have to click into each region to see the number of dwelling units, as well as the rate, to understand how we want
to interpret the result. Through this labour intensive process we will then weed out the area with just 1 dwelling unit and ignore
it.</p>

<p>Surprise maps don&rsquo;t map the actual difference of model and observation, they map how consistent the model is with the observation
in each area. In our initial example of an area with only one dwelling unit in it, no matter if that unit is used as
primary residence or not, this cannot be taken as strong evidence that our model is wrong. We should assign this a neutral colour.
The MC2 development on the other hand contained 570 dwelling units in 2016, a large deviation from the model indicates that
our model prediction might have some problems for that region.</p>

<p>In surprise maps, we colour each area by the amount of evidence observations in a that area gives against our model. To have good evidence
against our model, observations should deviate from model prediction, and we should be able to exclude regular statistical noise as
a cause for this.</p>

<p>For this example, we chose a mixture of the &ldquo;base rate&rdquo; and &ldquo;de Moivre funnel&rdquo; models
<a href="http://idl.cs.washington.edu/files/2017-SurpriseMaps-InfoVis.pdf">described in this excellent paper</a> where we essentially modify
the de Moivre funnel model by allowing an arbitrary model to take the place of the average of our variable. We also keep track
of the sign of the evidence we collect against our model, so whether our model underpredicted or overpredicted the rate of
non-primary residence dwelling units.</p>

<p><a href="https://censusmapper.ca/maps/668#15/49.2089/-123.1141"><img src="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/images/marine_gateway_nbhd3.png" style="width:50%;float:left;margin-right:10px;"></a>
The <a href="https://censusmapper.ca/maps/668">result is a map that makes it much easier to sport &ldquo;surprising&rdquo; areas</a>,
that is areas where observations provide good evidence
that our model does not hold well there.</p>

<p>We can now go back to check the <a href="https://censusmapper.ca/maps/668#16/49.2425/-123.1777">Marine Gateway area</a> we looked at before,
and we see that the only areas that contribute solid evidence against our model are the unexpectedly high rates at the MC2 development,
as well as the unexpectedly low rates at the area to the east between Main and Frasier streets.</p>

<h3>Surprise Maps in CensusMapper</h3>

<p><a href="https://censusmapper.ca/maps/671"><img src="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/images/child_poverty_surprise.png" style="width:50%;float:right;margin-left:10px;"></a>
We baked these kind of surprise maps into CensusMapper, so now we can easily apply this to any other kind of observable.</p>

<p>The CensusMapper surprise maps that are implemented right now require as input a &ldquo;model&rdquo; , an &ldquo;observation&rdquo; a &ldquo;base&rdquo; variable
(the number of dwelling units, averaged over the 2011 and 2016 censuses in our case) and a standard deviation of the difference
between model and predictions. For now, that standard deviation will have to be entered manually for technical reasons.
Moreover, other parameters like estimates of accuracy of census counts as well ask statistical rounding and other
operations that may have been performed on the data, can be added in to account for the fact that the rate observed in the census
is different from the actual rate. We added the ability to make the standard deviation region dependent, which allows us to
account for estimates of the accuracy of the census data based on region dependent variables.</p>

<p>For a simple example what this might look like consider child poverty. We have
<a href="https://censusmapper.ca/maps/132">mapped this variable in CensusMapper</a>, but at times
it can be hard to distill out the really important areas that have high child poverty rates as well as a high number of
children overall.
We have added a scatter plot of the rate vs the total number of children in poverty to the
map story, so that the user can more easily determine how significant a high child poverty rate in each particular region is.</p>

<p>Reliability of the data can also be tainted by low NHS return rates,
so CensusMapper maps automatically shade to regions that have particularly low NHS return rates
(and similarly for the full census return rates) to give some indication of reliability,
and we display the return rate on hover. But it is cumbersome to keep track of all this information.</p>

<p>Another way to deal with these issues is to make a <a href="https://censusmapper.ca/maps/671">child poverty surprise map</a>.
As model we can simply use the assumption that there
are zero children in poverty in each area. We scale the standard deviation of the child poverty rate linearly by the return rate
to weight down areas with low return rate. The result is a map that colours each region by the amount of evidence they provide
against the model assumption of zero children in poverty.</p>

<p>This makes it easier to filter out regions that have a low number
of children overall, where high rates of child poverty might just be a statistical fluke.</p>

<h3>Where to go from here</h3>

<p>Should all maps be surprise maps? No, there is value in just mapping straight up census variables, or mapping plain differences
of observations from the model. But there are many good reasons why such maps should be complemented,
or in some cases even replaced by, surprise maps.</p>

<p>Some kind of automation to aid the selection of appropriate standard deviation for the surprise model is needed before we can
open this up to a wider user base. Or CensusMapper server has an R server running that ties directly into the database and
communicates with the web server, so we need to build the appropriate scripts that can automate this task.</p>

<p>Another logical extension is to include proximity data into the Bayesian estimates. If one Census Tract provides good evidence
against our model, but that evidence is distributed uniformly across Dissemination Areas within it, then our surprise map
will show weaker evidence at the dissemination area level simply because each area has a smaller base population. But we could
check if the deviation from the model is localized in just one Dissemination Area, or also present in neighbouring
Dissemination Areas, and include that information in our estimates. This approach would also help with the problem if the evidence
is concentrated in an area that is split between to Census Tracts and drowned out by outher data in these respective tracts. So
it won&rsquo;t show up at the Census Tract level because of the particular ways the boundaries were drawn (MAUP), and it will get
diluted out at the Dissemination Area level because of low base population counts. Adding in proximity measures could recover
this evidence at the Dissemination Area level.</p>

<p>There are lots of other interesting possibilities of using surprise maps while leveraging the dynamic nature of CensusMapper.
One may allow for several models and let
relative importance of the models self-adjust with the map view. The output would then be for each map view a linear combination
of the models that provides the best fit for the current map view, as well as the evidence each region in the current map view provides
against the model.</p>

<p>We will keep experimenting with surprise models and at some point open up some of it&rsquo;s capabilities to a wider group
of CensusMapper users.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Marine Gateway and Joyce-Collingwood]]></title>
    <link href="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2017/04/03/joyce-collingwood/"/>
    <updated>2017-04-03T12:46:47-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2017/04/03/joyce-collingwood</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="https://censusmapper.ca/maps/584#11/49.2389/-123.0977"><img src="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/images/non-primary.png" style="width:50%;float:right;margin-left:10px;"></a>
There has been some <a href="http://www.theglobeandmail.com/real-estate/vancouver/bcs-empty-home-problem-moving-beyond-just-vancouver/article34130746/">recent confusion</a>
that got <a href="http://vancouversun.com/business/local-business/three-transit-oriented-communities-in-metro-rival-coal-harbour-for-empty-or-underused-housing">confounded further</a>
about transit-oriented development
in Vancouver harbouring a large number of non-primary residence homes. Good data is
important in moving forward in Vancouver&rsquo;s crazy housing market. Without proper
context, a couple of data points can serve to paint a very misleading picture
of what is happening. So I decided to fill in some gaps on the very narrow
question of understanding the CT level numbers that get tossed around.
No deep analysis, just looking into the CTs in question to see where the numbers that the census
picked up came from.</p>

<h3>TL;DR</h3>

<p>To understand the overall rate of 24.4% non-primary residence dwelling units at the Joyce census tract,
one should split the area into the Wall Centre Central Park development (99.2% non primary residence units)
and the rest of the CT (3.4% non-primary residence units).</p>

<p>To understand the Marine Gateway CT (24% non-primary residence dwellings),
it should be split inte the block with Marine Gateway development (13.7%),
the block containing the MC2 development (67.4%), and the rest (10.1%).</p>

<p>Comparing any of these very recent developments to the much older Coal Harbour makes no sense.
Coal Harbor is still &ldquo;filling in&rdquo; although at a stubbornly slow rate. It will be interesting
to see if the new vacancy tax can help speed that up.</p>

<!-- more -->


<h3>Marine Gateway</h3>

<p><a href="https://www.google.ca/maps/@49.2114587,-123.1170704,3a,75y,94.33h,114.49t/data=!3m6!1e1!3m4!1sdPusgUyW9gIfMiDEYVcduw!2e0!7i13312!8i6656!6m1!1e1"><img src="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/images/ec2_streetview.png" style="width:50%;float:left;margin-right:10px;"></a></p>

<p>To understand the 24% non-primary residence units in the census tract containing the
Marine Gateway development, we split the area into three parts.
The block with the Marine Gateway
development has in 460 dwelling units, 63 (13.7%) of which were found not to be
primary residences. The block north of that containing MC2 had 570 dwelling units
394 (67.4%) of which were not used as primary dwellings. The remaining part of the
CT as 1,507 dwelling units, 152 (10.1%) of which were not used as primary dwellings.</p>

<p>What we see here quite nicely is how the rates of non-primary residence units
are changing as the buildings they are in get older. Both Marine Gateway and MC2 are fairly
recent projects, but Marine Gatway itself got completed about a year before MC2,
and have significantly lower rates of non-primary residence homes.</p>

<p>What needs further sleuthing is the rate of 10.1% for the rest of the CT,
which is significantly higher than the baseline of 5.4% in 2011. There are no
other larger pockets of increase of non-primary residence units in that area.
This is might be best analysed in conjunction with similar increases in non-primary
residence dwellings in some other single
family neighbourhoods and goes beyond the scope of this short note.</p>

<h4>Data:</h4>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://censusmapper.ca/maps/584#16/49.2117/-123.1146">Non-primary residences</a></li>
<li><a href="https://censusmapper.ca/maps/586#15/49.2155/-123.1105">Change in non-primary residence dwellings</a></li>
<li><a href="https://censusmapper.ca/maps/650#15/49.2155/-123.1105">Total change in non-primary residence dwellings</a></li>
</ul>


<h3>Joyce-Collingwood</h3>

<p><a href="https://www.google.ca/maps/@49.2342503,-123.0248672,3a,75y,147.43h,109.85t/data=!3m6!1e1!3m4!1s22enJ14Z6DaYnXcsXcqYqw!2e0!7i13312!8i6656!6m1!1e1"><img src="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/images/wall_centre.png" style="width:50%;float:right;margin-left:10px;"></a>
The story for Joyce-Collingwood is quite a bit cleaner (but holds some data complexities that
manifest themselves in geocoding changes between censuses that can mess with fine-grained data).</p>

<p>The articles focus on the increase by 609 CT-level non-primary residence dwelling units at Joyce. The articles
hypothesise that &ldquo;Speculation is one of our prime suspects&rdquo; and
&ldquo;We don’t know why, but we know it’s concentrated in a few neighbourhoods.&rdquo;
without making any effort to look beyond CT-level data to find out.</p>

<p>Diving in we see immediately that the Dissemination Block at the north-west
corner of Kingsway and Boundary had 707 non-primary residence dwelling units in 2016,
vs 3 in 2011. That&rsquo;s a net change of 704 non-primary residence dwelling units
in just that block. It
block contains the Wall Centre Central Park development, that completed
shortly before the census. The census counted 713 units, only 6 of
which it found occupied.</p>

<p>At the same time, population dropped by 161 people in this block, as the
previous single family homes made way to the new development, easily
explaining the drop in population by 57 in the CT level data that
<a href="https://twitter.com/Ayan604/status/848952053435047936">has people scratching their heads</a>.</p>

<p>So what&rsquo;s the rate of non-primary residence buildings once we take out the
Wall Centre Central Park that got completed just before the census?</p>

<p>It&rsquo;s 3.4%. Which explains why Jennifer Gray-Grant, executive director at Collingwood Neighbourhood House,
was quoted finding the stat of 24% non-primary residence home &ldquo;perplexing&rdquo;.</p>

<p>It is also interesting to look back through time to see
<a href="https://censusmapper.ca/maps/400#16/49.2348/-123.0310">the rates in 2006</a>, when
the area around Aberdeen Park had 18.1% non-primary residence units. I am guessing
that some major building projects got completed in the year before the census,
by 2011 the number of non-primary residence units dropped dramatically.</p>

<h4>Data:</h4>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://censusmapper.ca/maps/584#16/49.2358/-123.0287">Non-primary residences</a></li>
<li><a href="https://censusmapper.ca/maps/586#16/49.2358/-123.0287">Change in non-primary residence dwellings</a></li>
<li><a href="https://censusmapper.ca/maps/650#16/49.2358/-123.0287">Total change in non-primary residence dwellings</a></li>
</ul>


<h3>Olympic Village</h3>

<p>The high rate of non-primary resident units in 2011 in the Olympic Village should
be seen in the context of the City&rsquo;s decision not to sell the units below cost
but hold onto the units and sell them
at a later point when the market recovers, which eventually paid off.</p>

<p>To understand the current overall rate of 9.4% non-primary residence units, it is
instructional to simply zoom into the block level data and observe how the
rates change depending on the completion time of the building.</p>

<h4>Data:</h4>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://censusmapper.ca/maps/584#15/49.2665/-123.1159">Non-primary residences</a></li>
<li><a href="https://censusmapper.ca/maps/586#15/49.2665/-123.1159">Change in non-primary residence dwellings</a></li>
<li><a href="https://censusmapper.ca/maps/650#15/49.2665/-123.1159">Total change in non-primary residence dwellings</a></li>
</ul>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Comparing Censuses]]></title>
    <link href="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2017/03/22/comparing-censuses/"/>
    <updated>2017-03-22T13:28:51-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2017/03/22/comparing-censuses</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="https://censusmapper.ca/maps/624#14/49.2608/-123.1556"><img src="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/images/pop_change.png" style="width:50%;float:right;margin-left:10px;"></a>
It&rsquo;s great to have fresh census data to play with. Right now we only have
three variables, population, dwellings and households. There is still lots
of <a href="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2017/02/10/2016-census-data/">interesting information that can be extracted</a>.</p>

<p>So we started exploring in our <a href="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2017/03/06/rs-population-change/">last post</a>,
things get really interesting when looking at change between censuses. But as we noted, there are
several technical difficulties that need to be overcome.</p>

<p>So we at CensusMapper took that as and invitation to do what we love most: breaking down barriers.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>The biggest difficulty in comparing censuses is that census geographies change over time to adapt to new
demographic realities on the ground. Whenever that happens, there is no easy way to compare data across
censuses.</p>

<h3>Custom Tabulations</h3>

<p>The best way to compare data across censuses is to pull a custom tabulation for data on a common geography,
there are a couple of things to keep in mind though:</p>

<p>1) It costs money (or at least time if part of a specific research project with access to a StatCan data centre),
2) it takes time to complete a custom tabulation, and
3) custom tabulations are typically not available at fine geographic levels.</p>

<p>For these reasons, comparing data across censuses is usually confined to select university research projects
or well-resourced private interest. And to make matters worse, custom tabulations are rarely shared. I have
asked university research groups if they were willing to share custom tabulations through CensusMapper, but got turned down
every time so far. While the
<a href="http://www.science.gc.ca/eic/site/063.nsf/eng/h_F6765465.html?OpenDocument">Tri-Agency Open Access Policy on Publications</a>,
postulates that research needs to be published in open access journals and the data also needs to be made available, in practice
research groups often keep their data locked up long after publication.</p>

<p>But some public agencies do make their custom tabulations available, for example the City of Vancouver has custom tabulations
for neighbourhood boundaries <a href="http://data.vancouver.ca/datacatalogue/index.htm">available on their open data catalogue</a>.</p>

<h3>Comparable Regions</h3>

<p>But even without custom tabulations we can compare regions if they have not changed across censuses. For example, we can compare
how the City of Vancouver or Metro Vancouver have change over time by tracing them through censuses, as their geography has not
changed. Census regions are tracked through their unique region identifier, which allows people to establish
timelines for regions. When doing so one quickly runs into issues with this approach though.</p>

<p>Just because a region has the same name and unique geographic identifier does not guarantee that the region has not changed. Simple
examples of this are Census Metropolitan Areas that can change quite dramatically over time without this being reflected in the name
or region identifier. For example, Ottawa, Montreal or Abbotsford were all expanded, some substantially) from the 2011 to the 2016 census.</p>

<p>For example, by just comparing Census Metropolitan Area data, Montreal&rsquo;s population grew by 7.2% between 2011 and 2016. But a good
chunk of that was simply due to the geographic region of the CMA being expanded, taking the 2016 expanded region as a base and
including all people that lived in that region in 2011, including the ones that lived outside of the 2011 CMA of Montreal but
that are now included in the 2016 CMA, the region&rsquo;s population only grew by 4.2%.</p>

<p>On top of large changes like this, many smaller regions have undergone slight boundary adjustments while keeping their unique identifier,
which move some people from one geographic region to another. And as one drills down into finer geographies one can easily
find geocoding errors in the data, where people were moved from one region to another between censuses without any region
adjustment taking place. These geocoding problems may persists in custom tabulations, but they are likely to even out as one
moves to higher aggregation levels.</p>

<h3>CensusMapper comparable regions</h3>

<p><a href="https://censusmapper.ca/maps/648"><img src="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/images/pop_adjusted.png" style="width:50%;float:left;margin-right:10px;"></a>
At CensusMapper we decided that it would be in the general interest to be able to compare standard census variables
across all aggregation levels. So we wrote some scripts to create a &ldquo;least common denominator&rdquo; tiling for all of
Canada for all aggregation levels,
ranging from Census Blocks to all of Canada. The idea is to keep regions that have not changed and, for regions that did change,
join regions together in a way that the joins match again across censuses. While this sounds simple in principle, there are lots
of issues and pitfalls along the way. Hopefully we have properly dealt with all of them now. We have done some testing, and
there are still have 285 regions (36 CTs, 245 CSDs and 4 CMAs) where the adjusted and computed 2011 population counts don&rsquo;t
quite add up. For example, 348 people were moved between Coquitlam and Port Coquitlam in this fashion, most of it due to an
adjustment between CTs 9330287.01 and 9330291.01 that is not due to a change in geographic boundary. In the example of Airdrie
trading 705 people with Rocky view this is associated with a change of the census geography, but no change in name or
geographic identifier. In most cases the adjustment is much smaller than this. Even more extreme than Airdrie is the case
of CTs 5350512.00 and 5350511.01 in Mississauga that swapped 1074 people without any apparent boundary change.</p>

<p>We have a <a href="https://censusmapper.ca/maps/648">map that highlights all these difference at or above the CT zoom level</a>, and in all maps we shade areas with adjusted
population counts and we indicate the actual population adjustment on hover.</p>

<h3>The Good, the Bad and the Ugly</h3>

<p><a href="https://censusmapper.ca/maps/588#14/49.2613/-123.1568"><img src="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/images/dw_change.png" style="width:50%;float:right;margin-left:10px;"></a>
So what does all of this buy us? For now, we get comprehensive maps comparing population, dwellings and households across the
2011 and 2016 censuses at all geographic levels, including Dissemination Blocks. As new census data rolls in, we will be
able to compare data down to the Dissemination Area level. That&rsquo;s pretty cool, we think.</p>

<p>What could be bad about this? Census data is far from perfect. And mapping differences tends to bring out the problems in
Census Data. Incorrectly enumerated dwellings, households or population, geocoding issues, as well as changes in geographies.</p>

<p>And things start to get really ugly when the rest of the census data comes in where statistical rounding was applied. Even if
everything was perfectly enumerated and geocoded, statistical rounding means that inevitably some areas will have census data
that has been rounded up in one year and rounded down in the next. And taking differences will bring this out very strongly,
especially at the Dissemination Area level. It is hard to overstate the effect of this, statistical rounding means that when
mapping change at small aggregation levels we will map lots of statistical noise.</p>

<p>There is however still value in showing and
working with differences of census variables at small aggregation levels, but the results are much harder to interpret.
One very simple workflow that we use regularly is to generally use Census Tract level data, but zoom in to Dissemination Areas
when we want more context for particular Census Tract values. Doing this, salted and peppered with a good dose of caution and
ideally some ground truthing, we can greatly refine our insights in what is going on in that Census Tract.</p>

<p>For this
reason we are decided to, at this point, keep fine grained data publicly available. We are aware that this will lead to
some people misinterpreting census data, but this is already happening at any aggregation level and is generally not a
sufficient argument to lock up data in our view. We may add more visual aids to warn the user of unreliable results, like adding
pattern shading to results that could be dramatically effected by small difference errors due to statistical rounding or
sampling/enumeration issues.</p>

<h3>Maps</h3>

<p>We opened up a number of maps on CensusMapper that explore changes between the 2011 and 2016 censuses down to the block level.</p>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://censusmapper.ca/maps/624">Population Change</a></li>
<li><a href="https://censusmapper.ca/maps/588">Dwelling Change</a></li>
<li><a href="https://censusmapper.ca/maps/586">Change in Non-Primary Residence Dwellings</a></li>
<li><a href="https://censusmapper.ca/maps/590">Change in Household Size</a></li>
<li><a href="https://censusmapper.ca/maps/596">Components of Population Change</a></li>
</ul>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
