<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: transit | Mountain Doodles]]></title>
  <link href="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/categories/transit/feed.atom" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/"/>
  <updated>2017-05-16T17:19:02-07:00</updated>
  <id>http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[MountainMath]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Transit Explorer]]></title>
    <link href="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2017/03/01/transit-explorer/"/>
    <updated>2017-03-01T12:10:29-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2017/03/01/transit-explorer</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="https://www.mountainmath.ca/transit/map"><img src="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/images/transit_vancouver.png" style="width:50%;float:right;margin-left:10px;"></a>
I have played with <a href="https://mapzen.com/documentation/mobility/isochrone/api-reference/#isochrone-service-api-reference">Mapzen&rsquo;s Isochrone serivce</a>
in the past with a simple <a href="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2016/11/18/interactive-isochrones/">visualization of walksheds</a>.</p>

<p>Recently Mazen <a href="https://mapzen.com/blog/exclusion/">updated the isochrone API</a> to allow for a more
fine-grained selection of exactly what transit services to include
or exclude in transit routing, and they created an <a href="https://mapzen.com/mobility/explorer/">amazing mobility explorer</a>
based on that.</p>

<p>Partially motivated by chatting with two TransLink planners I decided to riff off of that and
<a href="https://mountainmath.ca/transit/map">take a look at how well TransLink serves different parts of Vancouver</a>.
At different times of day.
And how susceptible TransLink&rsquo;s network is
to Skytrain service disruptions.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>To do this I decided to allow users to drag a location pin around that sets the start location, allow to change the time of day,
and call Mapzen&rsquo;s API to compute transit isochrones to visualize what areas can be reached
from the start location in 15, 30, 45 and 60 minutes.</p>

<p>To add some fun I made the Skytrain stations clickable, allowing the user to toggle the station status from open to closed,
so users can explore how mobility options change if a station is closed for boarding and no Skytrains pass through
any more. Essentially this cuts the transit network.</p>

<p>This does neglect bottlenecks that will emerge when alternative routes become overcrowded in the event of a skytrain failure,
and it does not take into account countermeasures by TransLink to deploy parallel buses, but it nonetheless gives
interesting conclusions about how crucial certain nodes are to the overall network.</p>

<p>Do you feel that your area is not served well enough by transit? Or under served in the evenings? Or are you worried about
what happens if the Skytrain breaks down somewhere? Just
<a href="https://mountainmath.ca/transit/map" target="_blank" class='btn btn-default'>launch the Vancouver Transit Explorer</a>
and play around to see how transit serves your needs.</p>

<p>Don&rsquo;t live in Vancouver and want to explore transit in your region? Not a problem. Use the search bar to jump to whatever city you
are interested in and click on the map to move the start location there. Then drag it around to explore that region.</p>

<p>If transit services in your city are already part of the <a href="https://transit.land/feed-registry/">TransitLand feed registry</a> that is.
If not, this visualization won&rsquo;t do you much good right now. If you are keen to use it to explore transit in your city,
just help TransitLand <a href="https://transit.land/news/2016/02/19/get-started-add-feeds.html">add your local transit agency to their feed registry</a>.</p>

<h3>Details</h3>

<p>I used settings that assume we have some happy walkers that are willing to walk quite a bit to get to and from transit, as
well as walking between stations. It seemed to me that the visualization is already overloaded with options that I did not want
to throw in another leaver.</p>

<p>The Mapzen Isochrone API also allows for routes or operators to be excluded from the calculations, so one can build more
complex &ldquo;what if&rdquo; type simulations.</p>

<p>And the service does not include bike share, which really is another piece in the whole mobility puzzle that can
significantly shorten travel time (or increase travel distance).</p>

<h3>Issues and Caveats</h3>

<p>Times after midnight may run into some issues, in some places, like e.g. Vancouver or Toronto, the early morning hour
isochrones won&rsquo;t work properly using this visualization. The technical reason seems to be that some GTFS used times past
24 hours, so 25:01 for one minute past 1AM the next day. And that breaks things somewhere. The good news is it&rsquo;s just a matter
of time for this to get fixed one way or another. But for now it&rsquo;s broken. :-(</p>

<p>Also, the tools this is built on are quite fresh. So there might be some glitches and opportunities to improve. Exciting times
when services like the isochrone API by Mapzen become publicly, and freely, available.</p>

<h3>5pm transit sheds around the world</h3>

<p><img src="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/images/transit_vancouver.png" style="display:inline-block; width:30%; padding:1%">
<img src="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/images/transit_toronto.png" style="display:inline-block; width:30%; padding:1%">
<img src="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/images/transit_calgary.png" style="display:inline-block; width:30%; padding:1%">
<img src="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/images/transit_seattle.png" style="display:inline-block; width:30%; padding:1%">
<img src="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/images/transit_san_francisco.png" style="display:inline-block; width:30%; padding:1%">
<img src="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/images/transit_new_york.png" style="display:inline-block; width:30%; padding:1%">
<img src="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/images/transit_london.png" style="display:inline-block; width:30%; padding:1%">
<img src="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/images/transit_paris.png" style="display:inline-block; width:30%; padding:1%">
<img src="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/images/transit_melbourne.png" style="display:inline-block; width:30%; padding:1%"></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[TOD Mode Share]]></title>
    <link href="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2016/04/20/tod-mode-share/"/>
    <updated>2016-04-20T23:26:35-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2016/04/20/tod-mode-share</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/skytrain_mode_map.html" target="_blank"><img  src="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/images/mode_share.png"  style="width:50%;float:right;margin-left:10px;"></a>
Just saw a <a href="https://pricetags.wordpress.com/2016/04/20/surprising-densities-at-some-skytrain-stations/">comment on the Pricetags blog</a>
pointing to a nice <a href="http://summit.sfu.ca/system/files/iritems1/9819/ETD4936.pdf">master&rsquo;s thesis</a>
investigating various TOD metrics around skytrain stations. I got curious how the 2011 transit mode share compares to the earlier
census years listed in the thesis. And how the mode share varies spatially.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>With <a href="http://censusmapper.ca/maps/316">CensusMapper</a> at my finger tips and building on the
<a href="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2016/04/06/tod/">visuals from the previous post</a> this is an easy exercise.</p>

<p>We again simply map our concentric circles around the stations, but this time we turn them into pie charts to show the
commute to work mode share. And we show the values for the inner 400m circle and the 400m to 800m annulus separately. I
also added some basic land use data, green for parks, pink for instututional and light blue for commercial or industrial
to provide more context.</p>

<p>What we would expect to see is that the transit mode share is larger in the 400m buffer, but curiously this is not always the case.</p>

<p>Click, touch or hover to get the exact values. And sorry again, only new computers will get a meaningful result. Most
smart phones and tablets will have no problems.</p>

<iframe src="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/skytrain_mode_map.html" width="80%" height="500", style="margin:5px 10%;"></iframe>


<p><a href="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/skytrain_mode_map.html#11/49.2430/-123.0350" class="btn btn-primary">Full screen view</a></p>

<p>The City of Vancouver average transit mode share is 30%, for Metro it&rsquo;s 20%. Head over to <a href="http://censusmapper.ca/maps/316">CensusMapper</a>
to explore transit mode share in the region (or anywhere else in Canada) in more detail.</p>

<h3>What I missed</h3>

<p>The master&rsquo;s thesis was careful enough to exclude areas across the river from the analysis. That&rsquo;s good thinking, I only
took circular buffers around the stations to do this. As indicated in the <a href="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2016/04/06/tod/">previous post</a>,
in the future we will add the capability to automatically generate isochrones, so areas
within 5 or 10 minutes walking distance, and use these
as regions, instead of using circular 400m and 800m buffers around the stations.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[TOD]]></title>
    <link href="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2016/04/06/tod/"/>
    <updated>2016-04-06T16:22:36-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2016/04/06/tod</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/skytrain_tod_map.html" target="_blank"><img  src="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/images/skytrain_tod.png"  style="width:50%;float:right;margin-left:10px;"></a>
Just saw <a href="http://michaelmortensenblog.com/2016/04/05/transit-oriented-development-room-for-smart-growth-in-greater-vancouver/">this excellent post looking at density around transit stations</a>
today and though I should pull out some numbers
to go with the pretty visuals. And with CensusMapper&rsquo;s new capabilities of populating custom geometries with census data
estimates it&rsquo;s super-easy to do.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>Population density is only one measure of interest here, job density or amenities density would be others. But for now let&rsquo;s
focus on population, so how many people live near the rapid transit stations. To keep things simple we checked for a 400m
and an 800m radius circle around the stations. At least roughly, if you need to know the details check the bottom.</p>

<p>To visualize this we simply map our concentric circles around the stations and use the population density as height.
Click, touch or hover to get the exact values. And sorry again, only new computers will get a meaningful result. Most
smart phones and tablets will have no problems.</p>

<iframe src="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/skytrain_tod_map.html" width="80%" height="500", style="margin:5px 10%;"></iframe>


<p><a href="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/skytrain_tod_map.html#11/49.2430/-123.0350" class="btn btn-primary">Full screen view</a></p>

<p>What immediately stands out is that for some stations inner orange circle is lower than the outer yellow circle. That means
the 400m radius area is less dense than the 800m radius area. It&rsquo;s as if
there was an inverse-TOD development. That&rsquo;s where local knowlege becomes important to see how exectly things are like
around the stations. Maybe the station primarily servers jobs or amenities, which we did not map. This definitely deserves
more scrutiny.</p>

<p><a href="http://censusmapper.ca/maps/302" target="_blank"><img  src="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/images/population_density.png"  style="width:50%;float:left;margin-right:10px;"></a>
Of course we can also view this on the <a href="http://censusmapper.ca/maps/302?zoom=12&amp;lat=49.2545&amp;lng=-123.0433">CensusMapper population density map</a>
comes in handy, if we zoom in it breaks it down to the census block level. And CensusMapper will also function on your
old computer if that&rsquo;s what you are using.</p>

<h3>Next steps</h3>

<p>One clear drawback of the analysis is that it uses 2011 numbers, which are quite old by now. So it&rsquo;s probably worthwhile to
re-visit this once 2016 population numbers become available. In the meantime I should run the same analysis on the 2006
data to see how density around transit stations changed. Some other day.</p>

<h3>Details</h3>

<p>This section is only interesting for people who want to know how exactly the numbers were derived. Conveniently
<a href="https://twitter.com/dshkol/status/717768801664651264">Dmitry had the station data handy</a>, which I took and then threw out
the duplicates data for each station platform.</p>

<p>Getting exact number
of people in a given circle radius around a station would require a getting custom tabulation for Stats Canada. This
is clearly overkill for the application we are looking at, and if we really wanted to be more precise we should probably start
by using an isochrone, that is an area that is at a 10 minute walking distance from the station, instead of using a circle.</p>

<p>In the future we will bake the ability to compute isochrones right into CensusMapper. Right now CensusMapper
estimates population data for arbitrary regions, including circular ones, by checking which census blocks intersect
each circle and add up the populations. Actually, we have three differnt ways to do this</p>

<ol type="a">
<li>by just taking all dissemination blocks that intersect</li>
<li>by just taking all dissemination blocks with the majority of its area in the intersection with the region</li>
<li>by scaling all properties of the dissemination block according to the proportion of its area in the overlap with our region.</li>
</ol>


<p>Each has its own advantages and disadvantages, we felt that option 2 is best suited for our purposes.</p>

<p>So we end up with a slightly different areas from the circle, the area given by the
census blocks we included, and we compute population densities based on that area. Since we visualize the circles instead
of the union of the census blocks used the visualization is a little bit misleading, but there is some value in the simplicity
of sticking with circles.</p>

<p>Since we are only interested in population data
we are done. In the more general case, when we are interested in estimating other census variables, for example the average rent in the
area, CensusMapper would now go through the census geographies and match up appropriate geographies with the census blocks
to derive the appropriate estimates. The actual algorithm gets quite complex here. Extra weights, like the proportion of
households that rent (and not own), come into play, as well as data quality estimates. And yes, if we did opt to use area overlap
weights in the block level computation, we would base them on households instead of population. If I am vague here it&rsquo;s
because the algorithm is quite complex and not really fit for a blog post.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
