<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: transit | Mountain Doodles]]></title>
  <link href="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/categories/transit/feed.atom" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/"/>
  <updated>2016-05-02T13:45:57-07:00</updated>
  <id>http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[MountainMath]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[TOD Mode Share]]></title>
    <link href="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2016/04/20/tod-mode-share/"/>
    <updated>2016-04-20T23:26:35-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2016/04/20/tod-mode-share</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/skytrain_mode_map.html" target="_blank"><img  src="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/images/mode_share.png"  style="width:50%;float:right;margin-left:10px;"></a>
Just saw a <a href="https://pricetags.wordpress.com/2016/04/20/surprising-densities-at-some-skytrain-stations/">comment on the Pricetags blog</a>
pointing to a nice <a href="http://summit.sfu.ca/system/files/iritems1/9819/ETD4936.pdf">master&rsquo;s thesis</a>
investigating various TOD metrics around skytrain stations. I got curious how the 2011 transit mode share compares to the earlier
census years listed in the thesis. And how the mode share varies spatially.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>With <a href="http://censusmapper.ca/maps/316">CensusMapper</a> at my finger tips and building on the
<a href="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2016/04/06/tod/">visuals from the previous post</a> this is an easy exercise.</p>

<p>We again simply map our concentric circles around the stations, but this time we turn them into pie charts to show the
commute to work mode share. And we show the values for the inner 400m circle and the 400m to 800m annulus separately. I
also added some basic land use data, green for parks, pink for instututional and light blue for commercial or industrial
to provide more context.</p>

<p>What we would expect to see is that the transit mode share is larger in the 400m buffer, but curiously this is not always the case.</p>

<p>Click, touch or hover to get the exact values. And sorry again, only new computers will get a meaningful result. Most
smart phones and tablets will have no problems.</p>

<iframe src="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/skytrain_mode_map.html" width="80%" height="500", style="margin:5px 10%;"></iframe>


<p><a href="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/skytrain_mode_map.html#11/49.2430/-123.0350" class="btn btn-primary">Full screen view</a></p>

<p>The City of Vancouver average transit mode share is 30%, for Metro it&rsquo;s 20%. Head over to <a href="http://censusmapper.ca/maps/316">CensusMapper</a>
to explore transit mode share in the region (or anywhere else in Canada) in more detail.</p>

<h3>What I missed</h3>

<p>The master&rsquo;s thesis was careful enough to exclude areas across the river from the analysis. That&rsquo;s good thinking, I only
took circular buffers around the stations to do this. As indicated in the <a href="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2016/04/06/tod/">previous post</a>,
in the future we will add the capability to automatically generate isochrones, so areas
within 5 or 10 minutes walking distance, and use these
as regions, instead of using circular 400m and 800m buffers around the stations.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[TOD]]></title>
    <link href="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2016/04/06/tod/"/>
    <updated>2016-04-06T16:22:36-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2016/04/06/tod</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/skytrain_tod_map.html" target="_blank"><img  src="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/images/skytrain_tod.png"  style="width:50%;float:right;margin-left:10px;"></a>
Just saw <a href="http://michaelmortensenblog.com/2016/04/05/transit-oriented-development-room-for-smart-growth-in-greater-vancouver/">this excellent post looking at density around transit stations</a>
today and though I should pull out some numbers
to go with the pretty visuals. And with CensusMapper&rsquo;s new capabilities of populating custom geometries with census data
estimates it&rsquo;s super-easy to do.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>Population density is only one measure of interest here, job density or amenities density would be others. But for now let&rsquo;s
focus on population, so how many people live near the rapid transit stations. To keep things simple we checked for a 400m
and an 800m radius circle around the stations. At least roughly, if you need to know the details check the bottom.</p>

<p>To visualize this we simply map our concentric circles around the stations and use the population density as height.
Click, touch or hover to get the exact values. And sorry again, only new computers will get a meaningful result. Most
smart phones and tablets will have no problems.</p>

<iframe src="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/skytrain_tod_map.html" width="80%" height="500", style="margin:5px 10%;"></iframe>


<p><a href="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/skytrain_tod_map.html#11/49.2430/-123.0350" class="btn btn-primary">Full screen view</a></p>

<p>What immediately stands out is that for some stations inner orange circle is lower than the outer yellow circle. That means
the 400m radius area is less dense than the 800m radius area. It&rsquo;s as if
there was an inverse-TOD development. That&rsquo;s where local knowlege becomes important to see how exectly things are like
around the stations. Maybe the station primarily servers jobs or amenities, which we did not map. This definitely deserves
more scrutiny.</p>

<p><a href="http://censusmapper.ca/maps/302" target="_blank"><img  src="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/images/population_density.png"  style="width:50%;float:left;margin-right:10px;"></a>
Of course we can also view this on the <a href="http://censusmapper.ca/maps/302?zoom=12&amp;lat=49.2545&amp;lng=-123.0433">CensusMapper population density map</a>
comes in handy, if we zoom in it breaks it down to the census block level. And CensusMapper will also function on your
old computer if that&rsquo;s what you are using.</p>

<h3>Next steps</h3>

<p>One clear drawback of the analysis is that it uses 2011 numbers, which are quite old by now. So it&rsquo;s probably worthwhile to
re-visit this once 2016 population numbers become available. In the meantime I should run the same analysis on the 2006
data to see how density around transit stations changed. Some other day.</p>

<h3>Details</h3>

<p>This section is only interesting for people who want to know how exactly the numbers were derived. Conveniently
<a href="https://twitter.com/dshkol/status/717768801664651264">Dmitry had the station data handy</a>, which I took and then threw out
the duplicates data for each station platform.</p>

<p>Getting exact number
of people in a given circle radius around a station would require a getting custom tabulation for Stats Canada. This
is clearly overkill for the application we are looking at, and if we really wanted to be more precise we should probably start
by using an isochrone, that is an area that is at a 10 minute walking distance from the station, instead of using a circle.</p>

<p>In the future we will bake the ability to compute isochrones right into CensusMapper. Right now CensusMapper
estimates population data for arbitrary regions, including circular ones, by checking which census blocks intersect
each circle and add up the populations. Actually, we have three differnt ways to do this</p>

<ol type="a">
<li>by just taking all dissemination blocks that intersect</li>
<li>by just taking all dissemination blocks with the majority of its area in the intersection with the region</li>
<li>by scaling all properties of the dissemination block according to the proportion of its area in the overlap with our region.</li>
</ol>


<p>Each has its own advantages and disadvantages, we felt that option 2 is best suited for our purposes.</p>

<p>So we end up with a slightly different areas from the circle, the area given by the
census blocks we included, and we compute population densities based on that area. Since we visualize the circles instead
of the union of the census blocks used the visualization is a little bit misleading, but there is some value in the simplicity
of sticking with circles.</p>

<p>Since we are only interested in population data
we are done. In the more general case, when we are interested in estimating other census variables, for example the average rent in the
area, CensusMapper would now go through the census geographies and match up appropriate geographies with the census blocks
to derive the appropriate estimates. The actual algorithm gets quite complex here. Extra weights, like the proportion of
households that rent (and not own), come into play, as well as data quality estimates. And yes, if we did opt to use area overlap
weights in the block level computation, we would base them on households instead of population. If I am vague here it&rsquo;s
because the algorithm is quite complex and not really fit for a blog post.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
