<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: assessment | Mountain Doodles]]></title>
  <link href="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/categories/assessment/feed.atom" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/"/>
  <updated>2017-04-03T15:10:22-07:00</updated>
  <id>http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[MountainMath]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Bumper Year for Thumb Twiddlers]]></title>
    <link href="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2017/01/18/bumper-year-for-thumb-twiddlers/"/>
    <updated>2017-01-18T11:10:43-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2017/01/18/bumper-year-for-thumb-twiddlers</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="https://www.mountainmath.ca/map/assessment?zoom=12&amp;lat=49.2494&amp;lng=-123.1241&amp;layer=12"><img src="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/images/twiddling_thumbs_2006_2017.png" style="width:50%;float:right;margin-left:10px;"></a>
Almost a year has passed since we first noticed how
<a href="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2016/01/24/work-vs-twiddling-thumbs/">sitting on single family homes and twiddling thumbs generates more income than working</a>.
And not just at the level of individual single family households. In the
City of Vancouver, the cumulative
land value gains of just the single family homes eclipsed the cumulative taxable earnings
reported to the CRA for the entire population.</p>

<p>With the new assessment data available now, it is time to run the numbers
and see how our thumb-twiddlers fared vs workers this year. If you thought
last year&rsquo;s twiddling thumbs returns were crazy high, you better hold onto
your hats!</p>

<!-- more -->


<h3>Work</h3>

<p>Not much changed in terms of the income people earned. CANSIM does not make the
taxfiler data freely available at the municipal level, we we will again estimate
the cumulative income for residents of the City of Vancouver by using 2010
Census data and extrapolating by applying the Metro Vancouver rate of income
growth.</p>

<p>This way we get a cumulative $22.3bn pre-tax or $18.6bn after-tax income in 2010,
<a href="http://www5.statcan.gc.ca/cansim/a26?lang=eng&amp;retrLang=eng&amp;id=1110009&amp;&amp;pattern=&amp;stByVal=1&amp;p1=1&amp;p2=37&amp;tabMode=dataTable&amp;csid=">which grew around 13% between 2010 and 2014</a>.
Extrapolating this for another two years to 2016 we estimate an income growth of around 20% since 2010,
which then pegs the cumulative income for the City of Vancouver at
$26.8bn pre-tax or $22.3bn after-tax (ignoring financial drag and other issues).</p>

<h3>Twiddling Thumbs</h3>

<p>Let&rsquo;s compare this to how much Vancouver home owner households &ldquo;earned&rdquo; last year by twiddling thumbs while sitting on their
property. To keep things simple and consistent with last year, we again focus on just the single family homes (SFH).
And again, we only consider land value changes, after all changing the
building value because of renovation or rebuilding certainly does not happen by twiddling thumbs.</p>

<p>The median SFH land value increased was $435,000 (the average was $594,005), for a cumulative land value increase
of $46.7bn, accounting for about half of the
<a href="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2017/01/16/2017-assessment-data/">total land value increase of the City of Vancouver</a>
or two thirds of the land value increase for residential (and mixed) land uses.</p>

<p>So while last year the twiddling thumbs return were still comparable to the cumulative income in the City of Vancouver,
this year the thumb twiddlers blow the income earners out of the water.
<span style="font-weight:bolder;">Just by by twiddling their thumbs, the SFH property owners alone earned twice as much
as the entire population of the
City of Vancouver did by actually working</span>. And in most cases homeowners won&rsquo;t pay taxes on
their thumb-twiddle earnings, although the
<a href="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2016/10/04/secondary-suites-and-taxes/">CRA recently made it harder with their new reporting rules</a>.</p>

<p>We are glossing over a couple of details here, for example the numbers are not adjusted for inflation, and costs like
property taxes and property transfer tax are not taken into account.</p>

<p>Of course, comparing income from work to income from twiddling thumbs is not entirely fair. The income from twiddling thumbs
is frozen in the property until the owner sells. But gains accumulate over the years, and eventually everyone sells and realizes
the gains (or passes them on to the next generation). And it&rsquo;s always good to remember that
&ldquo;<a href="https://twitter.com/GRIDSVancouver/status/813516103490015232">house-rich cash-poor homeowners are one transaction away from simply being rich renters</a>&rdquo;.</p>

<h3>The Long Term</h3>

<p><a href="https://www.mountainmath.ca/map/values?filter=sfh&zoom=13&lat=49.2482&lng=-123.1213&layer=25&mapBase=2&year=2016"><img src="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/images/twiddling_thumbs_animated_2017.gif" style="width:50%;float:left;margin-right:10px;"></a>
Most people don&rsquo;t trade houses like stocks, so what really matters is the long term gains, not the year to year changes. The 11 year
timeframe for which we have data roughly matches the average holding time for a single family house. The year over year
changes in land value vary dramatically, as the image shows and can be explored further using the
<a href="https://www.mountainmath.ca/map/values?filter=sfh&amp;zoom=13&amp;lat=49.2482&amp;lng=-123.1213&amp;layer=25&amp;mapBase=2&amp;year=2016">interactive version</a>.</p>

<p>Over 11 years, the single family home land value quadrupled. The median (nominal) single family home land value increase over that timespan
was $1,233,000, or $112,000 per year. Broken down further, that&rsquo;s $2,339,000 ($213,000 per year) for the median west side home
and $1,031,000 ($94,000 per year) for the median east side home.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.mountainmath.ca/map/assessment?filter=sfh&amp;zoom=13&amp;lat=49.2494&amp;lng=-123.1241&amp;layer=12"><img  src="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/images/twiddling_thumbs_2006_2017.png" style="width:50%;float:right;"></a>
We <a href="https://www.mountainmath.ca/map/assessment?filter=sfh&amp;zoom=13&amp;lat=49.2494&amp;lng=-123.1241&amp;layer=12">mapped the land value gain averaged over 11 years</a>.
We can observe that the average yearly increase depends on the square footage of the property as well as the location. The rates are mostly uniform
throughout the city (with some notable exceptions), but properties starting out with a higher value will see higher total value
increases. It&rsquo;s probably fair to say that even using the 11 year average, most homeowners &ldquo;earned&rdquo; more money twiddling thumbs
than pursuing a more traditional employment.</p>

<h3>Hourly Rate for Twiddling Thumbs</h3>

<p>Using the <a href="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2016/01/24/work-vs-twiddling-thumbs/">same methods as last year</a>
we can compute the hourly earnings of thumb twiddlers. For the July 2016 to July 2017 timeframe, thumb twiddlers
in the City of Vancouver averaged a tidy $239 per hour.
Using the 11 year averaged numbers instead of focusing on just the last year we still get a healthy average
thumb twiddling rate of $62 per hour.</p>

<p>Another bumper year for thumb twiddlers!
Considering to change your line work to thumb twiddling? To bad thumb twiddling is so unaffordable!</p>

<h3>Data Dump</h3>

<p>Here is the raw output of the stats run on the single family properties for anyone interested.</p>

<h5>SFH Land Value Rise (2016 - 2017)</h5>

<ul>
<li>City Wide: Average $594,005 Median $435,000, Count: 78648, Total: $46,717,325,799, Hourly: $239</li>
<li>Eastside: Average $373,306 Median $358,000, Count: 47988, Total: $17,914,233,199, Hourly: $150</li>
<li>Westside: Average $939,435 Median $866,000, Count: 30660, Total: $28,803,092,600, Hourly: $378</li>
</ul>


<h5>SFH Land Value Rise (2006 - 2017)</h5>

<ul>
<li>City Wide: Average $153,777 Median $112,090, Count: 77809, Total: $11,965,271,272, Hourly: $62</li>
<li>Eastside: Average $96,892 Median $93,727, Count: 47545, Total: $4,606,748,985, Hourly: $39</li>
<li>Westside: Average $243,144 Median $212,636, Count: 30264, Total: $7,358,522,287, Hourly: $98</li>
</ul>


<p>The total number of units for the 2006 to 2017 analysis are a little lower since not all properties can be traced over that time
period without resorting to more tedious analysis.</p>

<script>
function resetImages(){
    $('img').each(function(img){
        imgsrc = $(img).attr('src');
        if (imgsrc.slice(imgsrc.length-4)=='.gif') {
            $(img).attr('src', '');
            $(img).attr('src', imgsrc);

        }
    });
    setTimeout(function(){
        resetImages();
    },25000);
}
setTimeout(function(){
    resetImages();
},25000);
</script>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Mixing Data]]></title>
    <link href="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2016/07/06/mixing-data/"/>
    <updated>2016-07-06T09:19:04-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2016/07/06/mixing-data</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Census data is very rich and with <a href="https://censusmapper.ca">CensusMapper</a> we now have about 1 billion data points right at
our fingertips. And we have managed to open up some of our interfaces for everyone to <a href="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2016/05/04/census-mapping-for-everyone/">explore data and make their own maps
and freely share them</a>.</p>

<p>Things really get interesting when one mixes custom data with census data. While, at this point, these are not part of
the freely available CensusMapper functionality we still wanted to share what can be done.</p>

<p>At CensusMapper we have developed three basic ways to rapidly mix custom data with census data. So this is really three
blog posts in one.</p>

<!-- more -->


<h3>1. Overlay Mapping</h3>

<p>First up, advanced users can upload custom datasets and map them on top of census data.
<a href="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/images/restaurants_2.png"><img  src="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/images/restaurants_2.png" style="width:50%;float:right;margin-left:10px;"></a>
For example, we took a
<a href="http://data.vancouver.ca/datacatalogue/businessLicence.htm">business license dataset</a> from the City of Vancouver open
data catalogue, filtered it by the <em>BusinessType</em> field to only include businesses starting with &ldquo;Restaurant&rdquo; or
&ldquo;Liquor Establishment&rdquo; and uploaded them to CensusMapper to map it on top of census data. We have used a map
for <em>median age</em> that was <a href="https://twitter.com/jofu_/status/750564269796823041">recently created using CensusMapper&rsquo;s free public interface</a>
(have you made <a href="https://censusmapper.ca/maps/new">your own CensusMapper map</a> yet?), we have faded out areas outside of
Vancouver and coloured <em>Liquor Establishments</em> in red and <em>Restaurants</em> in blue.</p>

<p>Giving a visual impression of your own dataset in relation to census data is the first step to location analysis.</p>

<h3>2. Populate Custom Data with Census Data</h3>

<p>Next
up is to populate your own dataset with census data for further analysis. For the restaurants, we may be interested in
attaching population estimates in 5 minute walking distance from each location. We might also be interested in specific
age brackets, or numbers of recent immigrants
from specific countries that we may want to target with a new restaurant, or maybe even     income data.</p>

<p>This can be a time consuming and painful process,
but we have automated this at CensusMapper.</p>

<p>To showcase how this works we will show an example using elementary school catchment areas in the City of Vancouver. The
areas we have (from the <a href="http://data.vancouver.ca/datacatalogue/publicPlaces.htm">Vancouver Open Data Catalogue</a>) are
quite out of date, but for the purpose of this example they work as we will compare them to 2011 census data. We will look at the
<a href="https://censusmapper.ca/maps/419">school aged population</a> in each catchment.</p>

<!--
The general census release data does not fit our task perfectly, the census splits by age in early May 2011 and not by
year born and it does not have fine enough age brackets to estimating accurate school catchment numbers.
[BC Stats](http://www.bcstats.gov.bc.ca/StatisticsBySubject/Demography/PopulationEstimates.aspx) has finer age brackets
computed to school district (not catchment) boundaries, but their estimates are ridiculously far off of census numbers
when using matching age brackets and years that their usefulness is highly questionable. 
-->


<p><a href="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/images/e-schools.png"><img  src="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/images/e-schools.png" style="width:50%;float:left;margin-right:10px;"></a>
Using the visual overlay we notice that the catchment areas do fit boundaries of Dissemination Areas shown on the map
reasonably well, with some exceptions. The same cannot be said for Census Tracts, we can be reasonably confident that
Dissemination Area data is fairly accurate.</p>

<p>Next we use the built-in CensusMapper functionality to automatically populate the catchment areas with the census
data we are interested
in. When Dissemination Areas don&rsquo;t line up with the catchment boundaries we go down to Dissemination Blocks to estimate
how many children live on what side of the catchment boundary. We
<a href="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2016/04/06/tod/">previously explained this process in more detail</a>, the result is
a spreadsheet with the population data by age for each catchment area.</p>

<div id='schools'></div>


<div><script src="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/javascripts/colorbrewer.js" charset="utf-8"></script></div>


<div><script src="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/javascripts/school_bar_graph.js" charset="utf-8"></script></div>


<p>Here we show the results by school, the select element can be used to select any school of interest. The whole process
of populating the school data with census data just required uploading the catchment boundaries and selecting which
variables to attach.</p>

<h3>3. Custom Census Data Mapping</h3>

<p>Sometimes it is not practical to map custom data on CensusMapper. Maybe the custom data is too sensitive to be uploaded
to CensusMapper servers. Or it is quite complex and is better mapped separately. So we created an API to pull in
census data from CensusMapper to easily show census data on custom maps. And dynamically mix in your own data. As an
example we mix census data with data from BCAssessment, again obtained through the
<a href="http://vancouver.ca/your-government/open-data-catalogue.aspx">Vancouver Open Data Catalogue</a> (and enriched with
<a href="http://www.metrovancouver.org/data">open data from Metro Vancouver</a>).
For demonstration purposes take Dissemination Area
geographies and Dwelling Characteristic data from CensusMapper and mash it up with our
<a href="http://mountainmath.ca/map/assessment?zoom=14&amp;lat=49.2604&amp;lng=-123.1417&amp;layer=14&amp;mapBase=2">processed assessment data</a>
to explore the <a href="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2016/06/17/sdh-zoning-and-land-use/">differences in how single family properties are classified</a>.</p>

<p><a href="https://mountainmath.ca/census_mix/map?mapBase=2&layer=0" target="_blank"><img  src="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/images/sfh_unit_count.png" style="width:50%;float:right;margin-left:10px;"></a>
For example we can <a href="https://mountainmath.ca/census_mix/map?mapBase=2&amp;layer=0">compare BC Assessment single family lot count to Stats Canada unit count</a>
in the dissemination areas
that are exclusively made up of single family lots. This gives an indication of how many suites and laneway houses there
are in those areas. The census is prone to undercount units, but still does a better job at estimating them than other data sources,
like the city or BC Assessment.</p>

<p>One of the reasons why census unit counts come up higher than other methods is that the census also counts illegal units,
which naturally are not part of other official government counts. There are different reasons why a suite may be illegal:
<a href="https://mountainmath.ca/census_mix/map?mapBase=2&layer=5" target="_blank"><img  src="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/images/illegal_units.png" style="width:50%;float:left;margin-right:10px;"></a>
It could simply be that the owner has not made the effort to register it. Or the suite may not be up to code.
And in some cases, a property may have more than one suite in the main building, which is illegal in the City of Vancouver.
The latter ones we can pick out in census data, since a house with two secondary suites &ndash; so three dwelling units in one building in
total &ndash; is classified as being an &ldquo;Apartment, building that has fewer than five storeys&rdquo;. So, in census dissemination areas that
only have duplex or single family lots as residential land uses based on assessment and land use data, we can look for
how many dwelling units the census places in an &ldquo;Apartment, building that has fewer than five storeys&rdquo;. And
<a href="https://mountainmath.ca/census_mix/map?mapBase=2&amp;layer=5">map them</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[FSR]]></title>
    <link href="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2016/05/20/density/"/>
    <updated>2016-05-20T22:51:29-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2016/05/20/density</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="https://mountainmath.ca/map/assessment?layer=16" target="_blank"><img  src="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/images/fsr.png" style="width:50%;float:right;margin-left:10px;"></a>
Ever since I played with the <a href="http://mountainmath.ca/vancouver_lidar/map">LIDAR-generated building height data</a> I thought
that I should use that to map gross floor area (GFA) and floor space ratio (FSR). Gross floor area is the total floor area
inside the building envelope. So for a three storey building, it is the area of the footprint times three.
Floor space ratio is the GFA divided by the area of the parcel it sits on. There are several reasons why this may be
interesting.</p>

<p>GFA is the currency of the developer. Especially once we enter the world of apartment or commercial buildings,
gross floor area is directly proportional to the amount of money a developer can charge for a property, either when stratified
and sold or when rented out.</p>

<p>FSR on the other hand is a measure of density, and it is the currency of the zoning code. Height and site coverage are
also regulated in the zoning code and there is an obvious relationship to FSR. But because GFA is so important to the
developer, FSR usually receives more attention in public discussions.</p>

<p>Read on or <a href="https://mountainmath.ca/map/assessment?layer=16" target="_blank" class='btn btn-default'>head straight for the interactive map</a> to browse
Vancouver by FSR. Read the disclaimer at the bottom before using any data for purposes other than general reference.</p>

<!-- more -->


<h3>Maximum Allowable FSR and Spot Zoning.</h3>

<p>The maximum allowable FSR is set by the zoning code. Because land is so valuable in Vancouver, most people will try
to maximize GFA when building a new building, so they typically go right up to the maximum allowable FSR. Previously we have
<a href="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2016/03/05/physical-sfh-form-over-time/">examined the effects of various related metrics like height and site coverage</a>
for single family homes.</p>

<p><a href="https://mountainmath.ca/map/assessment?zoom=15&lat=49.2599&lng=-123.1583&layer=6" target="_blank"><img  src="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/images/spot-zoning.png" style="width:30%;float:right;margin-left:10px;"></a>
At least this is how it works for RS/RT zones. If you are looking to develop a different property, say a mixed use or
an apartment building or commercial building you will probably be looking to up-zone. That is, you will try to convince
the city (and the local population) to allow you to build more GFA than zoning would allow. If successful the city will
create a new zone just for your property and ask for some compensation in form of CACs (aiming to recoup about 80% of the
uplift in value the up-zoning creates) in return. That process is called
spot zoning and it can be seen in form of the little &ldquo;Comprehensive Development&rdquo; zones that are visible as yellow
sprinkles in the otherwise quite uniform zones on the map.</p>

<p>In reality the process of up-zoning a property is a lot more complex, arduous and time consuming, which favours larger
developers with deep pockets that can take the risk and sit out the long process of eventually obtaining higher GFA. One
of the many reasons why the &ldquo;missing middle&rdquo; is missing.</p>

<h3>Mapping Density</h3>

<p><a href="https://censusmapper.ca/maps/302#16/49.2375/-123.1573" target="_blank"><img  src="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/images/kerrisdale_people.png" style="width:30%;float:left;margin-right:10px;"></a>
From Census data we know the <a href="https://censusmapper.ca/maps/302">nighttime density</a>, that is where people live and sleep.
But we don&rsquo;t know where they are
during the daytime.</p>

<p><a href="https://mountainmath.ca/map/assessment?zoom=16&lat=49.238&lng=-123.154&layer=16" target="_blank"><img  src="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/images/kerrisdale_fsr.png" style="width:30%;float:right;margin-left:10px;"></a>
FSR is also often seen as such a measure of density, although it only focuses on density on property parcels and neglects
all the space between parcels, like roads right of ways and parks.</p>

<p>In mostly residential neighbourhoods the two densities correspond quite closely, but in areas with large commercial buildings
(nighttime) population density can be quite low while FSR is very high as can easily be seen by comparing the two maps.</p>

<p><a href="https://mountainmath.ca/assessment_gl/map?zoom=16&lat=49.2384&lng=-123.1567" target="_blank"><img  src="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/images/kerrisdale_tax.png" style="width:30%;float:left;margin-right:10px;"></a>
<a href="https://mountainmath.ca/assessment_gl/map">Tax density</a>, that is property taxes collected per area, give another view of
&ldquo;density&rdquo; in the city that highlights relative property values and emphasises commercial land use that pays five times
the residential tax rate.</p>

<p>There are lots of other measures of density that are important for different purposes, for example <a href="http://mountainmath.ca/census3">household density</a>
(in full 3D, requires modern computer),
<a href="https://censusmapper.ca/maps/359">the density of private dwelling units</a> or <a href="https://censusmapper.ca/maps/35">toddler density</a> just to name a few.</p>

<h3>Next Steps</h3>

<p>There are several directions I want to take this. Now that FSR is available for all properties, I can
compare purpose built rental buildings to strata buildings. For example, in my
<a href="http://mountainmath.ca/assessment/split_map">Buildings and Dirt map</a> I can&rsquo;t integrate purpose
built rentals because I don&rsquo;t know how many rental units they have. The assessment data from the Vancouver Open Data portal,
does not have that information, and BC Assessment won&rsquo;t share it (in a hassle-free way). But I can make a similar map based on GFA instead of
number of units and examine
how GFA effect land and building values across different land uses. And in many ways GFA may be a better unit for comparisons
than number of suites.</p>

<p><a href="https://mountainmath.ca/map/assessment?zoom=13&lat=49.2488&lng=-123.1211&layer=17&filter=res" target="_blank"><img  src="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/images/value_per_gfa.png" style="width:50%;float:right;margin-left:10px;"></a>
Or I can just make a <a href="https://mountainmath.ca/map/assessment?zoom=14&amp;lat=49.2684&amp;lng=-123.1354&amp;layer=17">straight-up map of total assessed value per GFA</a>.
And maybe add a filter to only show this for <a href="https://mountainmath.ca/map/assessment?zoom=13&amp;lat=49.2488&amp;lng=-123.1211&amp;layer=17&amp;filter=res">residential and mixed use units</a>
like in the image if that&rsquo;s what we are interested in.</p>

<p>Another interesting application is to use this data to do something along the lines of this
<a href="http://www.nytimes.com/interactive/2016/05/19/upshot/forty-percent-of-manhattans-buildings-could-not-be-built-today.html?_r=0">excellent analysis the New York Times published</a>
for Vancouver. FSR, next to building heights and lot coverage that I
<a href="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2016/03/05/physical-sfh-form-over-time/">have already analysed from a different angle</a>,
is an important metric to detect buildings that could not be rebuilt under regular zoning.</p>

<p>Lastly, having data on building GFA, together with assessment open data, allows for reverse-engineering of the GFA of individual
strata units. That makes the analysis of condo assessment data more meaningful as we can analyse assessed condo values by
unit size. One of the reasons why we are only talking about single family homes (or in some cases RS zoned homes) and
not condos is that it is very easy to compare single family homes. But comparing condos doesn&rsquo;t make much sense unless
one also has data on the size of each condo. And this has probably focused the public debate too much on single family
homes when we should be paying a lot more attention to condos. And purpose built rental units.</p>

<h3>Disclaimer</h3>

<p>The FSR was estimated using coarse building data extracted from LIDAR data. The motivation was to use the FSR for aggregate
analysis and not for getting accurate estimates of individual buildings.</p>

<p>Secondary buildings like garages or laneway houses are only inconsistently detected and mapped. The data is from 2009,
buildings built after that are greyed out.</p>

<p>The algorithm to compute FSR
from this building data is rather crude and only makes rudimentary attempts to adjust for varying floor heights of buildings
different for land uses, overhangs and eyebrows and dealing with pitched roofs or mechanical units.</p>

<p>Building data was clipped to property polygons to deal with cases of buildings spanning several legal lots or not properly
separated.</p>

<p>The FSR computed only roughly resembles the FSR defined in building codes. In particular our model with grossly
overestimate the FSR for buildings with overhanging features like
the Lookout on the Harbour Centre.</p>

<p>Block level aggregates will underestimate FSR in the presence of properties excluded from the FSR calculation.</p>

<p>Do not be use the FSR estimates as an authoritative source for any individual building FSR.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Work vs Twiddling Thumbs]]></title>
    <link href="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2016/01/24/work-vs-twiddling-thumbs/"/>
    <updated>2016-01-24T10:28:37-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2016/01/24/work-vs-twiddling-thumbs</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="https://www.mountainmath.ca/map/assessment?zoom=12&amp;lat=49.2494&amp;lng=-123.1241&amp;layer=12"><img src="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/images/twiddling_thumbs.png" style="width:50%;float:left;margin-right:10px;"></a>
In the ongoing debate on affordability of housing in the City of Vancouver we regularly
hear voices expressing concern for <a href="http://news.nationalpost.com/full-comment/andrew-coyne-dont-blame-chinese-billionaires-for-vancouver-housing-prices">&ldquo;elderly folks of modest means who had been counting
on using their home as a pension&rdquo;</a> to argue against doing anything to ease the housing
affordability problems many (younger) people are facing. In these arguments the concern
for &ldquo;elderly folks of modest means&rdquo; seems curiously focused to those who own property as
opposed to, for example, the 20% of the elderly people in Vancouver that live in poverty (15k total).</p>

<p>Which got me a little thinking about “earning money” in this day and age.</p>

<!-- more -->


<h3>Work</h3>

<p>Most people earn money by working. We are interested in after tax household income,
for simplicity we will look at 2010 income data reported in the 2011 census. The median
after-tax household income in Vancouver was $50k (the average was $65k), although there is
<a href="http://censusmapper.ca/maps/224">large regional variability</a>.
The pre-tax households incomes were $56k for the median and $80k for the average income.</p>

<p>Incomes have grown a bit since then, median income levels in Vancouver grew by 7% from
2010 to 2013 (<a href="http://www5.statcan.gc.ca/cansim/a47">the latest year Stats Canada reports on</a>)
and will have grown a little more
since then, but these are relatively small changes compared to other numbers I want to talk about.</p>

<p><a href="http://censusmapper.ca/maps/189">Most of this income stems from employment income</a> which also includes self-employment,
but 22% of pre-tax income in Vancouver came from outher sources, mostly investment income
but also government transfer payments like child benefits.</p>

<p>Cumulative, the after tax income put $17.8bn into Vancouverite’s pockets.</p>

<h3>Twiddling Thumbs</h3>

<p>Let&rsquo;s compare this to how much Vancouver home owner households earned last year by twiddling thumbs while sitting on their
property. For simplicity we focus on SFH (&ldquo;Single Family&rdquo; or &ldquo;Single Detached&rdquo;) homes. We
will consider the change in land value only, changing the building value because of renovation or rebuilding certainly
does not happen by twiddling thumbs.</p>

<p>The typical SFH household made $262,000 last year by twiddling thumbs (so that&rsquo;s the median land value rise for SFH homes between 2015 and 2016
property tax assessment years, the average was $318,877), for a tidy total of $24,651,312,001. Not too shabby.
And considering that the typical owner household
lives in their home, these are tax-free earnings once the owners sell. That&rsquo;s substantially more than what the typical household
in Vancouver takes home. The total land value increase for just the SFH properties amounts to $24bn out of
<a href="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2016/01/17/updated-vancouver-assessment-data/">the $45.2bn by which land values in Vancouver increased overall</a>. For context,
recall that the overall income earned by all Vancouverites in 2010 was $17.8bn after tax (21.3bn before tax).</p>

<p>In other words, <span style="font-weight:bolder;">just the SFH property owners alone earned more by twiddling their thumbs than the entire population of the
City of Vancouver did by &ndash; actually working</span>. And in most cases homeowners don&rsquo;t even have to pay taxes on their thumb-twiddle earnings. Yet another
indication of how <a href="http://censusmapper.ca/maps/37">out of touch the property market is with the local enconomy</a>.</p>

<p>The numbers are just meant to provide a general frame of reference, they are not adjusted for inflation, and costs like
property taxes and property transfer tax are not taken into account.</p>

<h3>Mapping the Result of Thumb Twiddling</h3>

<p><a href="https://www.mountainmath.ca/map/assessment?filter=sfh&amp;zoom=14&amp;lat=49.253&amp;lng=-123.1244&amp;layer=12">There is a map for this</a>.
(I probably would not take the time to write about this otherwise.) Last year&rsquo;s assessment
increase was quite large, not every year is like this (although it looks like the coming one will also be substantial).
To even things out a little I mapped the average yearly gross land value increase for each property. For properties that I
could not trace back all the way to 2006 I averaged over as many years as I could find.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.mountainmath.ca/map/assessment?filter=sfh&amp;zoom=13&amp;lat=49.2494&amp;lng=-123.1241&amp;layer=12"><img  src="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/images/sfh_rise.png" style="width:50%;float:right;"></a>
<a href="https://www.mountainmath.ca/map/assessment?filter=sfh&amp;zoom=13&amp;lat=49.2494&amp;lng=-123.1241&amp;layer=12">Looking at the map</a> we see that
the average yearly increase depends to a large extend on the square footage of the property. Large properties naturally stand
out, unless they are stratified where the land value increase gets distributed across all the owners.</p>

<p>Averaged over 10 years, the yearly land value increase for the typical SFH property in Vancouver was $79,800. Using Main as
a divider the numbers are $66,700 for the
typical east of Main and $141,700 for the typical west of Main property (using median increases).</p>

<p>A good portion of the east-west difference is due to larger lot size, but even the land values increase per m&sup2; for properties
on the west side was 35% higher than that of properties on the
east side. These are yearly increases, to be accumulated and collected tax free in most cases when the property is sold.</p>

<h3>Twiddling in 3D</h3>

<p><a href="http://mountainmath.ca/assessment/split_map?zoom=17&lat=49.2362&lng=-123.1365&type=1&use3D=1&year=2015" target="_blank"><img  src="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/images/s_vanre.gif" loop="0" style="width:50%;float:left;margin-right:10px;"></a>
We can get even more fancy and show the effect the thumb-twiddling has on land values by <a href="http://www.mountainmath.ca/assessment/split_map">animating the land and building
value rise over time</a>. You will need a modern computer to view this.</p>

<p>If you are interested there is <a href="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2016/04/01/on-dirt-and-houses/">more background</a>
on the visualization. I put a little more work into this, the numbers in the animation are inflation adjusted and it also
includes duplexes and stratified condo units. There is a slider to filter by number of strata units in each building to
explore the effects of stratifying a standard lot into several units has on affordability.</p>

<h3>Hourly Rate for Twiddling Thumbs</h3>

<p>Just for fun we can work out the hourly rate for twiddling thumbs. All we need to do is divide by the number of work
hours by year. We can look up the average work weeks for a Vancouver worker in the 2011 census and, for style points also consider the
number of household maintainers. After all, when we compare household income with land value increases we should consider how many
people in the household work. 63% of Vancouver households have only one household maintainer, but
<a href="http://censusmapper.ca/maps/223">33% have two and 4% three or more household maintainers</a> contributing to household income.
On average a Vancouver household <a href="http://censusmapper.ca/maps/222">worked a total of 62 person-weeks per year</a> to earn
that income. Assuming a 40 hour work week, we compute the average after-tax earning to be $26 per hour from regular work
and average after tax earnings of $126 per hour from twiddling thumbs. That&rsquo;s assuming all household maintainers are twiddling
the same amount of time that they dedicate to regular work. (In this calculation we use average not median income and land value
increases, medians don&rsquo;t lend themselves well to these kind of reasoning.)</p>

<p>Using the 10 year averaged numbers instead of focusing on just the last year we still get a healthy average after-tax twiddling thumbs rate of $44 per hour.</p>

<p>I am not entirely sure why anyone would want twiddling thumbs to stay so lucrative. Unless maybe the super self-centered thumb-twiddlers.
Or why earnings from thumb-twiddling should remain tax-free. While employment income is taxed (as it should be).</p>

<p>Considering to change your line work to thumb twiddling? To bad thumb twiddling is so unaffordable!</p>

<h3>Data Dump</h3>

<p>Here is the raw output of the stats run on the single family properties for ayone interested.</p>

<h5>SFH Land Value Rise (2015 - 2016)</h5>

<ul>
<li>City Wide: Average $313,072 Median $262,000, Count: 78740, Total: $24,651,312,001, Hourly: $126</li>
<li>East of Main: Average $230,106 Median $230,000, Count: 46014, Total: $10,588,122,001, Hourly: $92</li>
<li>West of Main: Average $429,725 Median $375,000, Count: 32726, Total: $14,063,190,000, Hourly: $173</li>
</ul>


<h5>SFH Land Value Rise (2006 - 2016)</h5>

<ul>
<li>City Wide: Average $109,969 Median $79,800, Count: 77981, Total: $8,575,547,711, Hourly: $44</li>
<li>East of Main: Average $68,656 Median $66,700, Count: 45647, Total: $3,133,947,703, Hourly: $27</li>
<li>West of Main: Average $168,293 Median $141,700, Count: 32334, Total: $5,441,600,008, Hourly: $67</li>
</ul>


<p>The total number of units for the 2006 to 2016 analysis are a little lower since not all properties can be traced over that time
period without resorting to more tedious analysis.</p>

<script>
function resetImages(){
    $('img').each(function(img){
        imgsrc = $(img).attr('src');
        if (imgsrc.slice(imgsrc.length-4)=='.gif') {
            $(img).attr('src', '');
            $(img).attr('src', imgsrc);
            
        }
    });
    setTimeout(function(){
        resetImages();
    },25000);
}
setTimeout(function(){
    resetImages();
},25000);
</script>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
